<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Complementum fortunatarum insularum, p. II, Sive, Galathea vaticinans being part of an epithalamium upon the auspicious match of the most puissant and most serene Charles II and the most illustrious Catharina Infanta of Portugal : with a description of the fortunate islands / written originally in French by P.D.C. Gent. and since translated by him into Latin and English ; with the translations also of The description of S. James's Park, and the late fight at S. Lucar by Mr. Ed. Waller ; The panegyrick of Charles II by Mr. Dreyden ; and other peeces relating to the present times.</title>
            <author>Cardonnel, P. de (Pierre), d. 1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33689</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C498</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4318</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10629477</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10629477</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45449</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A33689)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45449)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1400:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Complementum fortunatarum insularum, p. II, Sive, Galathea vaticinans being part of an epithalamium upon the auspicious match of the most puissant and most serene Charles II and the most illustrious Catharina Infanta of Portugal : with a description of the fortunate islands / written originally in French by P.D.C. Gent. and since translated by him into Latin and English ; with the translations also of The description of S. James's Park, and the late fight at S. Lucar by Mr. Ed. Waller ; The panegyrick of Charles II by Mr. Dreyden ; and other peeces relating to the present times.</title>
                  <author>Cardonnel, P. de (Pierre), d. 1667.</author>
                  <author>Waller, Edmund, 1606-1687. Poem on St. James's Park. French &amp; English.</author>
                  <author>Dryden, John, 1631-1700. To His Sacred Majesty, a panegyrick on his coronation.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 8, 8, 80, [2] p. : ports.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W.G.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45449:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45449:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>COMPLEMENTUM <hi>FORTUNATARUM INSULARUM,</hi> P. II.
SIVE <hi>GALATHEA VATICINANS.</hi>
Being part of AN EPITHALAMIUM upon the Au<U+017F>picious Match OF THE MOST PUISSANT and MOST SERENE CHARLES II.
AND THE MOST ILLUSTRIOUS CATHARINA INFANTA of <hi>PORT<g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>GAL.</hi>
WITH A De<U+017F>cription of the <hi>FORTUNATE ISLANDS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written originally in <hi>French</hi> by <hi>P. D. C.</hi> Gent.
AND Since Tran<U+017F>lated by him in <hi>Latin</hi> and <hi>Engli<U+017F>h.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With the Tran<U+017F>lations al<U+017F>o of The De<U+017F>cription of S. <hi>James</hi>'s <hi>Park,</hi> and the <hi>late Fight</hi> at S. <hi>Lucar,</hi> By Mr. <hi>ED. WALLER.</hi>
The PANEGYRICK of <hi>CHARLES</hi> II.
By Mr. <hi>DREYDEN.</hi>
And other Peeces relating to the pre<U+017F>ent Times.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. G. M.DC.LXII.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:45449:2"/>
            <head>Sidera divifi <U+017F>unt h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> toto Orbe Britanni, Quae FORTUNATAS reant jàm Lumine TERRAS.</head>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Second CHARLES Heire to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Royall Martur<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
                  </head>
                  <p>CR</p>
                  <l>UN A<U+017F>tre de ce Prince annonça la Nai<U+017F><U+017F>ance,</l>
                  <l>L'E<U+017F>chole des Ce<U+017F>ars <U+017F>a jeune<U+017F><U+017F>e éleva;</l>
                  <l>Et dans mille dangers <U+017F>on courage éprouva:</l>
                  <l>Quel <U+017F>ort donc <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ words">
                        <desc><<U+25CA>…></desc>
                     </gap> bravera <U+017F>a Pui<U+017F><U+017F>ance?</l>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:45449:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>Don<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">¯</g>a Catharina Infanta of Portugal.</head>
                  <l>LE Ciel à ma Mai<U+017F>on rendant une Couronne,</l>
                  <l>Et r'a<U+017F><U+017F>eurant les droits de mon illu<U+017F>tre <U+017F>ang,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>u<U+017F>t peu fait pour l'éclat je tiens de mon rang,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ans celuy qu'à pre<U+017F>ent le Sceptre Anglois me donne.</l>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:45449:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45449:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc><1 page duplicate></desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:45449:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45449:4"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable <hi>JAMES BOTELER,</hi> EARL OF OSSERY AND VISCOUNT THORLE, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAD not this conjuncture of time put con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in me, I dur<U+017F>t never have ventur'd either the publi<U+017F>hing of the<U+017F>e unpoli<U+017F>h't rimes, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixing your Honourable name to the front of them.
<pb facs="tcp:45449:5"/>
For, having ever held <hi>Poëtry</hi> (however a dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, I mu<U+017F>t confe<U+017F>s, of my inclination) to be <hi>but an excu<U+017F>able trifling of precious time,</hi> mea<U+017F>ur'd to mankind by the Inch or narrowne<U+017F>s of a Span, though his thoughts and active part gra<U+017F>p the whole <U+017F>eries of Ages and flie at Eternity, and his task <U+017F>eems to be the reading here below of that great book of Nature, whereof near <U+017F>ix thou<U+017F>and years expir'd have taught to the mo<U+017F>t reaching Genius'es but the A B. C. of it, with no other <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s then to multiply contentions and debates: having, I <U+017F>ay, put no other e<U+017F>teeme upon the Art of making ver<U+017F>es, (although it has had its admirers and followers in all ages) then of a lawful and harmle<U+017F>s diver<U+017F>ion, and unbending of the mind when it has <U+017F>pent and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hau<U+017F>ted it<U+017F>elf upon <U+017F>everer <U+017F>tudies, and more <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious imployments; I could not have avoided by pre<U+017F>enting the<U+017F>e to your patronage, and inviting you to <U+017F>toop to the light entertainment of Poetry, the ju<U+017F>t cen<U+017F>ure and imputation of undervaluing your <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious lea<U+017F>ure, more u<U+017F>efully imployed in tho<U+017F>e publick thoughts wherein your High relations at Court, and your Noble zeal of <U+017F>erving your Prince and Country, in that <hi>Great Senate which coynes the Laws of this Nation,</hi> do at pre<U+017F>ent ingage you. But that, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ides the love and e<U+017F>teem I have ob<U+017F>erv'd (having
<pb facs="tcp:45449:5"/>
the honour to be <U+017F>ometimes in your Lord<U+017F>hips com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany) you have for the Mu<U+017F>es, and your capacity of judging right of the delicacies of the <hi>French</hi> ver<U+017F>e, which every ear and palate are not capable of; the Parliaments rece<U+017F>s, and your Lord<U+017F>hips journey for <hi>Ireland</hi> being now at hand, do furni<U+017F>h me with an unque<U+017F>tionable plea for the publi<U+017F>hing and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<U+017F>s to your Lord<U+017F>hip of this Poetical <hi>Rap<U+017F>ody and E<U+017F><U+017F>ay in <U+017F>everal languages,</hi> whereof your Lord<U+017F>hip is equally a competent judge. To make this good, I need not borrow records of antiquity, nor quote <hi>Ennius,</hi> always taken by that <hi>incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Roman Scipio</hi> for a companion in all his journeys; or <hi>Homer</hi>'s Poems cheri<U+017F>hed and read by <hi>Alexander</hi> in all his expeditions; <hi>Virgil</hi> and <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>race</hi> entertained by <hi>Augu<U+017F>tus</hi> and <hi>Mecaenas;</hi> as the lawfulle<U+017F>t diver<U+017F>ion they could pitch upon, when they would unbind and give a refre<U+017F>hment to their va<U+017F>t and undefatigable Minds, on which did turn the hinges and relyed the weight of mo<U+017F>t part of the then habitable World.</p>
            <p>This is well known to your Lord<U+017F>hip; as al<U+017F>o how much on the <U+017F>ame account <hi>Ron<U+017F>ard</hi> was e<U+017F>teemed by <hi>Charles</hi> the ninth of <hi>France;</hi> and this, My Lord, gives me the confidence, that (though nothing you can read here, bears proportion with
<pb facs="tcp:45449:6"/>
the excellent productions of tho<U+017F>e <hi>Primitive He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros</hi>'s <hi>of the Art,)</hi> yet <U+017F>ome thing may have the good luck to plea<U+017F>e and to divert your Lord<U+017F>hip, were it but the matter this Rap<U+017F>ody affords, and tho<U+017F>e <hi>Ideas</hi> it may rai<U+017F>e in your mind <hi>of the be<U+017F>t of Princes,</hi> re<U+017F>toring the hopes of the<U+017F>e Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (wherein you have <U+017F>o large a <U+017F>hare) to the greate<U+017F>t happine<U+017F>s they ever could enjoy. I might have had good opportunity to relate here among<U+017F>t one of the great cau<U+017F>es of it, tho<U+017F>e faithful and unwearied endeavors, and great <U+017F>ervices of your Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Family, which are <U+017F>ufficient pledges and <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curities them<U+017F>elves of perpetuating the Illu<U+017F>trious <hi>Name of</hi> ORMOND to future ages, to make it <hi>as la<U+017F>ting as</hi> the BRITISH MONARCHY, <hi>and equal in duration to the Sun and Moon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that being to va<U+017F>t a Sea too engage in with a <U+017F>lender skull, and too waighty a <U+017F>ubiect to venture upon unpreparedly, I have not dared to pre<U+017F>ume, My Lord, to touch it with a <U+017F>light hand, or crowde any part of it in a preliminary Epi<U+017F>tle a cu<U+017F>tome to much countenanc'd by mo<U+017F>t of our Modern Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. The height of my ambition, and utmo<U+017F>t <U+017F>cope of my de<U+017F><U+017F>eine at pre<U+017F>ent, My Lord, is onely (<U+017F>ince I have no other means left to provide for my attendance upon your Lord<U+017F>hip, and the Heads
<pb facs="tcp:45449:6"/>
of your Honourable Family in this your journey) that you will be pleas'd to accept of me in this <U+017F>len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>garbe,</hi> being every may otherwi<U+017F>e di<U+017F>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the frowns of Fortune, and <U+017F>o unfit to pretend admittance in <U+017F>o <U+017F>plendid a train, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<U+017F>s it be
<q>
                  <l>Nella <U+017F>corta di Phebo, ch' à voi s'inchina,</l>
                  <l>Tutta ridente, tutta di <U+017F>cherzi piena.</l>
               </q>
But, My Lord, to borrow my own words written on another acca<U+017F>ion,
<q>
                  <l>—Si quelque jour, la Fortune</l>
                  <l>Met en plus grande liberté</l>
                  <l>Mon Genie per<U+017F>ecuté</l>
                  <l>Des rigueurs de cette importune;</l>
                  <l>Peut e<U+017F>tre d'un burin plus <U+017F>eur,</l>
                  <l>Et d'un vers rempli de douceur,</l>
                  <l>D'ORMOND j'entreprendray l'image;</l>
                  <l>Et dans les beaux exploits de tous <U+017F>es De<U+017F>ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">¯</g>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">¯</g>s</l>
                  <l>La depeindray <U+017F>i bien, que la plus fiere rage</l>
                  <l>Re<U+017F>pectera <U+017F>es traits ju<U+017F>qu'a la fin des temps.</l>
               </q>
This is the vow, this is the <U+017F>erious wi<U+017F>h of him, My Lord, who de<U+017F>ires for no better end to be once again
<pb facs="tcp:45449:7"/>
re<U+017F>tored to the <U+017F>tate of his former Fortune, then to become thereby more ready and capable to wait hereafter on your Lord<U+017F>hip otherwi<U+017F>e then by his Pen, and to declare by <U+017F>ome more real deed then Poëtical expre<U+017F><U+017F>ions, how unfainedly he is</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
               <signed>YOUR LORDSHIPS Mo<U+017F>t humble, mo<U+017F>t true, and mo<U+017F>t devoted Servant, P. D. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="song">
            <pb facs="tcp:45449:7"/>
            <head>HYMENAEI PRAELUDIUM, SIVE GALATHEA VATICINANS.</head>
            <head type="song">BEING A SONG of the SEA NYMPH <hi>GALATEA,</hi> Upon the MARIAGE of CHARLES II.</head>
            <head>AND The PRINCESSE INFANTA of <hi>PORT<g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>GALL.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>FAir Godde<U+017F><U+017F>es of the wide Main!</l>
               <l>Who<U+017F>e nimble feet do never re<U+017F>t,</l>
               <l>Who<U+017F>e motion in a con<U+017F>tant <U+017F>train</l>
               <l>Sees the Sun break, &amp; brings him to his We<U+017F>t:</l>
               <l>Go, fair Nymphs, go; and to both Shores proclaim</l>
               <l>This matchle<U+017F>s Day, with the loud trump of Fame:</l>
               <l>And thou, who<U+017F>e Youth ne're quits her Spring,</l>
               <l>Sing, Fair <hi>Hymen!</hi> this ble<U+017F>t Day, <U+017F>ing;</l>
               <l>And in all places rai<U+017F>e</l>
               <l>To Great <hi>CHARLES</hi> an Immortal prai<U+017F>e.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:45449:8"/>
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>CHARLES,</hi> from the Earth about to drive</l>
               <l>That <hi>Hydra,</hi> which great States do'es rent,</l>
               <l>All Princes of the world will <U+017F>trive</l>
               <l>With his Stars henceforth ever to con<U+017F>ent:</l>
               <l>For him again <hi>A<U+017F>traea</hi> quits the Skye,</l>
               <l>Repairs her Altars, and to Earth draws nigh.</l>
               <l>Then thou; who<U+017F>e Youth ne're quits her Spring,</l>
               <l>Sing, Fair <hi>Hymen!</hi> this ble<U+017F>t Day, <U+017F>ing;</l>
               <l>And in all places rai<U+017F>e</l>
               <l>To Great <hi>CHARLES</hi> an Immortal prai<U+017F>e.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>I<U+017F>lands; which in the furthe<U+017F>t Clime</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aurora</hi> guilds, when <U+017F>he do's ri<U+017F>e,</l>
               <l>Behold a Sun breaks in his prime,</l>
               <l>Which with no le<U+017F><U+017F>er glory fills your eyes:</l>
               <l>Prepare your gums and <U+017F>pices for this Day,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Mogul</hi> leave, your vows to <hi>CHARL'S</hi> to pay:</l>
               <l>And thou, who<U+017F>e Youth ne're quits her Spring,</l>
               <l>Sing, Fair <hi>Hymen!</hi> this ble<U+017F>t Day, <U+017F>ing;</l>
               <l>And in all places rai<U+017F>e</l>
               <l>To Great <hi>CHARLES</hi> an Immortal prai<U+017F>e.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:45449:8"/>
               <head>IV.</head>
               <l>You happy Darlings of the Morn!</l>
               <l>Fair Lands! your gold and precious <U+017F>tone,</l>
               <l>When they His head henceforth adorne,</l>
               <l>A brighter glory to His beams <U+017F>hall owne;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Goa and Calecut His Cro<U+017F>s</hi> <U+017F>hall bear,</l>
               <l>And the <hi>Dutch Lions</hi> claw no longer fear:</l>
               <l>Then thou, who<U+017F>e Youth ne're quits her Spring,</l>
               <l>Sing, Fair <hi>Hymen!</hi> this ble<U+017F>t Day, <U+017F>ing;</l>
               <l>And in all places rai<U+017F>e</l>
               <l>To Great <hi>CHARLES</hi> an Immortal prai<U+017F>e.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>V.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Zeilan</hi> her Ivory <U+017F>hall <U+017F>end,</l>
               <l>And tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>weet Spices, which her <U+017F>tore</l>
               <l>Can our Navies more freely lend,</l>
               <l>Than all the Lands which do the Sun adore;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ganges</hi> with Diamonds more <U+017F>well'd <U+017F>hall <U+017F>peed,</l>
               <l>And Pearls for <hi>CHARLES</hi> alone <hi>Comorry</hi> breed.</l>
               <l>Then thou, who<U+017F>e Youth ne're quits her Spring,</l>
               <l>Sing, Fair <hi>Hymen!</hi> this ble<U+017F>t Day, <U+017F>ing;</l>
               <l>And in all places rai<U+017F>e</l>
               <l>To <hi>KATHARIN</hi> an Immortal prai<U+017F>e.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:45449:9"/>
               <head>VI.</head>
               <l>Of <hi>China</hi> the di<U+017F>tre<U+017F><U+017F>ed Prince</l>
               <l>By You alone, Great <hi>CHARLES,</hi> redre<U+017F>t,</l>
               <l>The World <U+017F>hall of this truth convince,</l>
               <l>You are his, and <U+017F>hould be <hi>Lord</hi> of the re<U+017F>t.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Great Cham</hi> <U+017F>trook by th' <hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi> Lions paw,</l>
               <l>Shall throw his quiver and receive your law:</l>
               <l>Then thou, who<U+017F>e Youth ne're quits her Spring,</l>
               <l>Sing, Fair <hi>Hymen!</hi> this ble<U+017F>t Day, <U+017F>ing;</l>
               <l>And in all places rai<U+017F>e</l>
               <l>To Great <hi>CHARLES</hi> an Immortal prai<U+017F>e.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Africa</hi> of th' <hi>A<U+017F>iatick</hi> <U+017F>oyl</l>
               <l>Grown rival by Your Princely <U+017F>miles,</l>
               <l>Will <U+017F>trive to <U+017F>end You richer <U+017F>poyl,</l>
               <l>And <U+017F>weeter Spices than the <hi>Ea<U+017F>tern</hi> I<U+017F>les;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Melinda</hi> <U+017F>hall and <hi>Quiloa</hi> both drain</l>
               <l>Their Veins of gold, Your trea<U+017F>ures to maintain</l>
               <l>Then thou, who<U+017F>e Youth ne're quits her Spring,</l>
               <l>Sing, Fair <hi>Hymen!</hi> this ble<U+017F>t Day, <U+017F>ing;</l>
               <l>And in all places rai<U+017F>e</l>
               <l>To Great <hi>CHARLES</hi> an Immortal prai<U+017F>e.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:45449:9"/>
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <l>From <hi>Jappon</hi> to <hi>Mozambick</hi>'s <U+017F>hore,</l>
               <l>And from thence to the <hi>We<U+017F>tern</hi> bond,</l>
               <l>The Trident's Power disjoyn'd before</l>
               <l>In <hi>CHARLES</hi> alone <U+017F>hall unite his command:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Olinda</hi> will in Him her Conque<U+017F>t crown,</l>
               <l>And <U+017F>oon be head of her va<U+017F>t body grown.</l>
               <l>Then thou, who<U+017F>e Youth ne're quits her Spring,</l>
               <l>Sing, Fair <hi>Hymen!</hi> this ble<U+017F>t Day, <U+017F>ing;</l>
               <l>And in all places rai<U+017F>e</l>
               <l>To Great <hi>CHARLES</hi> an Immortal prai<U+017F>e.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="9">
               <head>IX.</head>
               <l>You Nymphs! fre<U+017F>h ro<U+017F>es do not <U+017F>pare!</l>
               <l>Make ha<U+017F>t your beds therewith to <U+017F>trow;</l>
               <l>Look how they bud! how lovely fair<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
               </l>
               <l>Under his tall Ships they on <U+017F>uddain blow!</l>
               <l>Heav'ns influence is chang'd by KATHARIN's rays,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cypris</hi> each where her blu<U+017F>hing flow'r di<U+017F>plays.</l>
               <l>Then thou, who<U+017F>e Youth ne're quits her Spring,</l>
               <l>Sing, Fair <hi>Hymen!</hi> this ble<U+017F>t Day, <U+017F>ing;</l>
               <l>And in all places rai<U+017F>e</l>
               <l>To <hi>KATHARIN</hi> an Immortal prai<U+017F>e.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="10">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:45449:10"/>
               <head>X.</head>
               <l>Then let's joyn Mirtle to the flame</l>
               <l>Of this <U+017F>o cha<U+017F>te <U+017F>o lovely tree,</l>
               <l>Mirtle do's the White colour claim,</l>
               <l>Badge of her <U+017F>oul from all dark pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions free:</l>
               <l>Heav'ns influencies chang'd by KATHARIN's day,</l>
               <l>The<U+017F>e flow'rs henceforth will every where di<U+017F>play.</l>
               <l>Then thou, who<U+017F>e Youth ne're quits her Spring,</l>
               <l>Sing, Fair <hi>Hymen!</hi> this ble<U+017F>t Day, <U+017F>ing;</l>
               <l>And in all places rai<U+017F>e</l>
               <l>To <hi>KATHARIN</hi> an Immortal prai<U+017F>e.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="11">
               <head>XI.</head>
               <l>Behold! I <U+017F>pie the harmle<U+017F>s Dove,</l>
               <l>Through aery paths <hi>Venus</hi> to guide,</l>
               <l>Charm'd with this Day's delight and love,</l>
               <l>And on the banks of <hi>Thames</hi> <U+017F>moothly to glide;</l>
               <l>Love is her guide, and in her bill <U+017F>he holds</l>
               <l>A branch of Mirtle, which the bri<U+017F>e unfolds.</l>
               <l>Then thou, who<U+017F>e Youth ne're quits her Spring,</l>
               <l>Sing, Fair <hi>Hymen!</hi> this ble<U+017F>t Day, <U+017F>ing;</l>
               <l>And in all places rai<U+017F>e</l>
               <l>To <hi>KATHARIN</hi> an Immortal prai<U+017F>e.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="12">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:45449:10"/>
               <head>XII.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pallas</hi> on that great River <U+017F>ide</l>
               <l>Strives now to <U+017F>hift her Martial dre<U+017F>s;</l>
               <l>Her temples are with Olive tyed</l>
               <l>In <U+017F>tead of Bays, joy to expre<U+017F>s;</l>
               <l>Heavens influence is chang'd by this ble<U+017F>t Day,</l>
               <l>Concord and Peace their fruits will now di<U+017F>play.</l>
               <l>Then thou, who<U+017F>e Youth ne're quits her Spring,</l>
               <l>Sing, Fair <hi>Hymen!</hi> this ble<U+017F>t Day, <U+017F>ing;</l>
               <l>And in all places rai<U+017F>e</l>
               <l>To <hi>KATHARIN</hi> an Immortal prai<U+017F>e.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="13">
               <head>XIII.</head>
               <l>A Thou<U+017F>and <hi>Cupids</hi> <U+017F>pread abroad</l>
               <l>With palms in hand, o'recloud the ayre,</l>
               <l>And di<U+017F>play on the Princes road</l>
               <l>Their game<U+017F>om flock, <U+017F>til young &amp; void of care;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>KATHARIN</hi> of all eyes wonder and delight,</l>
               <l>Inlivens the Day, by which it <U+017F>hines <U+017F>o bright.</l>
               <l>Then thou, who<U+017F>e Youth ne're quits her Spring,</l>
               <l>Sing, Fair <hi>Hymen!</hi> this ble<U+017F>t Day, <U+017F>ing;</l>
               <l>And in all places rai<U+017F>e</l>
               <l>To <hi>KATHARIN</hi> an Immortal prai<U+017F>e.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="14">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:45449:11"/>
               <head>XIV.</head>
               <l>I <U+017F>ee, I <U+017F>ee! this happy I<U+017F>le</l>
               <l>Longing her pre<U+017F>ence to enjoy!</l>
               <l>At her owne Princes <U+017F>miles to <U+017F>mile,</l>
               <l>And <U+017F>econd with her mirth his pre<U+017F>ent joy;</l>
               <l>While<U+017F>t He on <U+017F>hore full of impatience <U+017F>tays,</l>
               <l>Reckons times flight and every moment weighs:</l>
               <l>Then ha<U+017F>t this day from which depends our Spring,</l>
               <l>Ha<U+017F>t, fair <hi>Hymen!</hi> this Day to bring,</l>
               <l>And in all places rai<U+017F>e</l>
               <l>To Great <hi>CHARLES</hi> an Immortal prai<U+017F>e.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ha<U+017F>t to fulfil the ju<U+017F>t de<U+017F>ires</l>
               <l>Of this Matchle<U+017F><U+017F>e and Princely Paire,</l>
               <l>Too much delay our Patience tires,</l>
               <l>And we all grieve at thy officious care:</l>
               <l>Then keep no longer with tedious delay</l>
               <l>This Pair, who<U+017F>e Love does every moment weigh;</l>
               <l>Come Nymphs, let's ha<U+017F>t, this Day to bring,</l>
               <l>Let's <hi>Hymen</hi> call, let's <hi>Hymen</hi> <U+017F>ing,</l>
               <l>And in all places rai<U+017F>e</l>
               <l>To this <U+017F>o Princely Pair an everla<U+017F>ting prai<U+017F>e.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="song">
            <pb facs="tcp:45449:11"/>
            <head>HYMENAEI PRAELUDIUM, SIVE GALATHEA VATICINANS.</head>
            <head>PRO EPITHALAMIUO CAROLI II.
Propediem in lucem prodituro Sub Nomine TAGI.</head>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>POnti Nereïdes! mitia Numina!</l>
               <l>Motu quae celeres littora <U+017F>edulo</l>
               <l>Unaqua<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> die curva recurritis,</l>
               <l>Quae cingit liquido Nereus ambitu:</l>
               <l>Currite, caeruleas Nymphae! &amp; narrate per oras,</l>
               <l>Quanta hodiè Cantus <U+017F>it mihi materies.</l>
               <l>Tu<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> <U+017F>olennes Hymenaee! ritus</l>
               <l>Adjuva Sacrae celebrans Diei;</l>
               <l>Et <U+017F>onet per te <hi>CAROLI</hi> triumphis</l>
               <l>Axis uterque.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:45449:12"/>
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>Jàm di<U+017F>cors <hi>CAROLI</hi> Numine territa</l>
               <l>Erynni<U+017F><expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ululans orbe fugabitur;</l>
               <l>Influxus Britici, Pace adamantinâ,</l>
               <l>Po<U+017F>thac fata aliis Principibus dabunt.</l>
               <l>Hoc Duce mox exul terras A<U+017F>traea revi<U+017F>et,</l>
               <l>Hoc aras recolet quae jacuere diù.</l>
               <l>Ergo <U+017F>olennes Hymenaee! ritus</l>
               <l>Adjuva <U+017F>acrae celebrans diei;</l>
               <l>Et <U+017F>onet per te <hi>CAROLINUM</hi> utro<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </l>
               <l>Nomen in axe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>O vos! quas alio cardine <U+017F>ub Poli</l>
               <l>Na<U+017F>cens irradiat Pho<U+017F>phorus, In<U+017F>ulae!</l>
               <l>Jam po<U+017F>thac <hi>CAROLI</hi> Sole tepebitis,</l>
               <l>Influxu<U+017F><expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dabit lux melior novos.</l>
               <l>Pandite odoratas ergo Illi pandite <U+017F>ylvas,</l>
               <l>Nec vobis ultrà dent <U+017F>ua jura Scythae.</l>
               <l>Tu<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> <U+017F>olennes Hymenaee! ritus<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
               </l>
               <l>Adjuva <U+017F>acrae celebrans diei;</l>
               <l>Et <U+017F>onet per te <hi>CAROLI</hi> triumphis</l>
               <l>Axis uterque.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:45449:12"/>
               <head>IV.</head>
               <l>Ve<U+017F>trum nam Britico <U+017F>i Diademate</l>
               <l>Aurum aut gemma micet, lumine vivido</l>
               <l>Fulgebit melius, majus &amp; his decus</l>
               <l>De Tanti veniet culmine Verticis:</l>
               <l>Nec <hi>Calecuthum</hi> aut <hi>Goa</hi> hujus <U+017F>ub Tegmine tutae</l>
               <l>Jam metuent iras, <U+017F>aeve <hi>Batave,</hi> tuas.</l>
               <l>Ergo <U+017F>olennes Hymenaee! ritus</l>
               <l>Adjuva <U+017F>acrae celebrans diei;</l>
               <l>Et <U+017F>onet per te <hi>CAROLI</hi> triumphis</l>
               <l>Axis uterque.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>V.</head>
               <l>Te <U+017F>ubmi<U+017F><U+017F>a colet dentibus <hi>Indicis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Zeilon</hi> antè alias, Maxime Principum,</l>
               <l>Divini<U+017F><expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ferax arbor odoribus,</l>
               <l>Ramo grata dabit cinnama <U+017F>upplice:</l>
               <l>Plure fluet <U+017F>olito <hi>Ganges</hi> adamante, Tibi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </l>
               <l>Sola <hi>Comorrinis</hi> concha natabit aquis.</l>
               <l>Ergo <U+017F>olennes Hymenaee! ritus</l>
               <l>Adjuva <U+017F>acrae celebrans diei;</l>
               <l>Et <U+017F>onet per te <hi>CAROLI</hi> triumphis</l>
               <l>Axis uterque.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:45449:13"/>
               <head>VI.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sinen<U+017F>is</hi> titubans Arbiter <hi>Imperî,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Po<U+017F>thac auxilio tutus erit tuo;</l>
               <l>Et cuncti Dominum, quo patet ambitu,</l>
               <l>Orbis Te meritâ laude fatebitur;</l>
               <l>Sub<U+017F>tratu<U+017F><expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Tuo <hi>Chamus, Rex Magne,</hi> Leoni,</l>
               <l>Abjiciet tremulâ spicula <U+017F>aeva manu.</l>
               <l>Ergo <U+017F>olennes Hymenaee! ritus</l>
               <l>Adjuva <U+017F>acrae celebrans diei;</l>
               <l>Et <U+017F>onet per te <hi>CAROLI</hi> triumphis</l>
               <l>Axis uterque.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <l>Jam <U+017F>ecura Tui militis <hi>Africa</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Tutis prae<U+017F>idiis, aemula divitum</l>
               <l>In <U+017F>ylvis <hi>Arabum</hi> thura dabit Tibi,</l>
               <l>Sulci<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ambro<U+017F>io nectare diffluent:</l>
               <l>Auriferos pandent <hi>Quiloa Melinda<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi> colles,</l>
               <l>Implebit<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> rates vena beata Tuas.</l>
               <l>Ergo <U+017F>olennes Hymenaee! ritus</l>
               <l>Adjuva <U+017F>acrae celebrans diei;</l>
               <l>Et <U+017F>onet per te <hi>CAROLINUM</hi> utro<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </l>
               <l>Nomen in axe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:45449:13"/>
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <l>A <hi>Jappone</hi> <U+017F>inus u<U+017F>que <hi>Mozambicos</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Et curvum <hi>He<U+017F>periae</hi> littus <hi>Atlantidis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Agno<U+017F>cet <hi>CAROLUM</hi> Nereus Arbitrum,</l>
               <l>Sceptri Tricipitis per vada caerula.</l>
               <l>Nec vanas <hi>Olinda</hi> fovet spes <U+017F>ub duce tanto,</l>
               <l>Dividat <note n="*" rend="inter">
                     <hi>Americae</hi> continenti.</note> adjuncto quin <U+017F>ua jura <U+017F>olo.</l>
               <l>Ergo <U+017F>olennes Hymenaee! ritus</l>
               <l>Adjuva <U+017F>acrae celebrans diei;</l>
               <l>Et <U+017F>onet per te <hi>CAROLI</hi> triumphis</l>
               <l>Axis uterque.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="9">
               <head>IX.</head>
               <l>Nymphae! ne teneris parcite jam Ro<U+017F>is,</l>
               <l>Lymphas purpureis spargite floribus,</l>
               <l>En! ut <U+017F>erta citis <U+017F>uavia puppibus</l>
               <l>Subcre<U+017F>cunt, liquidas per maris orbitas;</l>
               <l>Jam terras <hi>CATHARINA</hi> Beat melioribus A<U+017F>tris,</l>
               <l>Quilibet &amp; Veneris flore nite<U+017F>cet ager.</l>
               <l>Ergo <U+017F>olennes Hymenaee! ritus</l>
               <l>Adjuva <U+017F>acrae celebrans diei;</l>
               <l>Et <U+017F>onet per te <hi>CATHARINA</hi> cunctis</l>
               <l>Orbis in oris.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="10">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:45449:14"/>
               <head>X.</head>
               <l>Jungamus rutilis illius ignibus</l>
               <l>Myrthum delicias Cypridis aureae,</l>
               <l>Myrthi flos Scythicâ candidior nive</l>
               <l>Candorem Ingenii nobilis arguit;</l>
               <l>Ridebit po<U+017F>thac tellus his floribus omnis,</l>
               <l>Nam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Polo influxus dat <hi>CATHARINA</hi> novos.</l>
               <l>Ergo <U+017F>olennes Hymenaee! ritus</l>
               <l>Adjuva <U+017F>acrae celebrans diei;</l>
               <l>Et <U+017F>onet per te <hi>CATHARINA</hi> cunctis</l>
               <l>Orbis in oris.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="11">
               <head>XI.</head>
               <l>En! cerno placidum Cypridis alitem,</l>
               <l>Quo curru trahitur per liquidum aethera,</l>
               <l>Gaudentem populi plau<U+017F>ibus &amp; Die,</l>
               <l>Alae remigio radere <hi>Thame<U+017F>in:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ille Diem celebrans, &amp; habenâ ductus Amoris,</l>
               <l>Ramum fe<U+017F>tivo Myrtheum in ore tenet.</l>
               <l>Ergo <U+017F>olennes Hymenaee! ritus</l>
               <l>Adjuva <U+017F>acrae celebrans diei;</l>
               <l>Et <U+017F>onet per te <hi>CATHARINAE</hi> utroque</l>
               <l>Nomen in Axe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="12">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:45449:14"/>
               <head>XII.</head>
               <l>En! cerno Armigeram <hi>Pallada,</hi> ca<U+017F><U+017F>ide</l>
               <l>Ornantem nitidâ belligerum caput,</l>
               <l>Thorace &amp; pofito ludicra pro<U+017F>equi,</l>
               <l>Dum praefert Oleam Martis adoreae.</l>
               <l>Jam terras <hi>CATHARINA</hi> beat melioribus A<U+017F>tris,</l>
               <l>Concors Pacis amor <U+017F>aecula no<U+017F>tra reget.</l>
               <l>Ergo <U+017F>olennes Hymenaee! ritus</l>
               <l>Adjuva <U+017F>acrae celebrans diei;</l>
               <l>Et <U+017F>onet per te <hi>CATHARINAE</hi> utroque</l>
               <l>Nomen in Orbe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="13">
               <head>XIII.</head>
               <l>Ludunt palmigeri mille Cupidines,</l>
               <l>Spargentes ro<U+017F>eum <U+017F>erta per aera,</l>
               <l>Effundunt<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> jocos Cypridis in viâ,</l>
               <l>Illiu<U+017F><expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Ro<U+017F>as <U+017F>ub pedibus <U+017F>erunt:</l>
               <l>Sed <hi>CATHARINA</hi> ip<U+017F>os inter pulcherrima <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>mores,</l>
               <l>Praecipuum toto Sydus in Orbe micat.</l>
               <l>Ergo <U+017F>olennes Hymenaes! ritus</l>
               <l>Adjuva <U+017F>acrae celebrans diei;</l>
               <l>Et <U+017F>onet per te <hi>CATHARINAE</hi> utroque</l>
               <l>Nomen in Axe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="14">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:45449:15"/>
               <head>XIV.</head>
               <l>Jam pa<U+017F>cor <hi>Britico</hi> lumina <hi>Littore,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Tellurem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Caput quà nitet Imperî</l>
               <l>Jam cerno, officiis Principe cum <U+017F>uo</l>
               <l>Certantem, meritis imparibus licet:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>REX</hi> numerans momenta <U+017F>uum <U+017F>olatur amorem;</l>
               <l>Et putat in minimâ taedia longa morâ.</l>
               <l>Ergo <U+017F>olennes Hymenaee! ritus</l>
               <l>Ocyùs <U+017F>acrae accelera diei;</l>
               <l>Luceat per te Sacra Taeda, cunctis</l>
               <l>Orbis in oris.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="15">
               <head>XV.</head>
               <l>Indulgere morae parce diutiùs;</l>
               <l>Fe<U+017F>tinare Diem, pulchra Cupidinum</l>
               <l>Et fe<U+017F>tiva Parens, ocyùs impera,</l>
               <l>Regi, quo propior, grata magis venit;</l>
               <l>Ne momenta trahas Taedis illu<U+017F>tribus ob<U+017F>tans,</l>
               <l>Sunt<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> quibus in minimâ taedia longa morâ.</l>
               <l>Vo<U+017F><expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> <U+017F>olennes celebrate Nymphae,</l>
               <l>Quam Diem votis Hymenaeus ornat;</l>
               <l>Et <U+017F>onet Famâ <hi>CAROLI</hi> perenni,</l>
               <l>Axis uterque;</l>
               <l>Et Tuas narret <hi>CATHARINA</hi> Laudes,</l>
               <l>Axis uterque.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="song">
            <pb facs="tcp:45449:15"/>
            <head>CHANT DE GALATHEE.</head>
            <head type="sub">Sur le MARIAGE DE CHARLES II.
<hi>ET DE CATHERINE Infante de</hi> PORT<g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>GAL.</head>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>BElles Divinités de l' Onde!</l>
               <l>Qui d'un mouvement diligent,</l>
               <l>Tous les jours <U+017F>ur nos flots d'argent</l>
               <l>Vi<U+017F>ités l'enceinte du Monde;</l>
               <l>Allés Nymphes, allés publier <U+017F>ur vos bords,</l>
               <l>Le <U+017F>uiet nompareil de mes divins accords.</l>
               <l>Et Toy Hymen! O Hymenée!</l>
               <l>Chante à jamais cette iournée!</l>
               <l>Et rends de <hi>CHARLES</hi> en tous lieux,</l>
               <l>Le recit glorieux.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:45449:16"/>
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>CHARLES</hi> va bannir de la Terre</l>
               <l>La Di<U+017F>corde des Potentats,</l>
               <l>Répandant de<U+017F><U+017F>us leurs Etats</l>
               <l>Les Influences d' Angleterre;</l>
               <l>A<U+017F>trée en <U+017F>a faveur vient revoir les mortels,</l>
               <l>Et de<U+017F><U+017F>ous <U+017F>on appuy reparer <U+017F>es Autels.</l>
               <l>Celebrons donc cette journée,</l>
               <l>Chantans Hymen! O Hymenée!</l>
               <l>Rendons de <hi>CHARLES</hi> en tous lieux</l>
               <l>Le recit glorieux.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>I<U+017F>les! qu'en l'autre bout du Monde</l>
               <l>L' Aurore voit à <U+017F>on reveil,</l>
               <l>Vous allés d'un nouveau Soleil</l>
               <l>Sentir l'influence feconde:</l>
               <l>Preparés vos parfums pour honorer ce jour</l>
               <l>Et quittés <hi>le Mogul</hi> pour Luy faire la Cour.</l>
               <l>Celebrons donc cette journée,</l>
               <l>Et Toy Hymen! O Hymenée!</l>
               <l>Rends du Grand <hi>CHARLES</hi> en tous lieux</l>
               <l>Le recit glorieux.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:45449:16"/>
               <head>IV.</head>
               <l>Vo<U+017F>tre or, vos Pierres precieu<U+017F>es,</l>
               <l>Heureu<U+017F>es terres du Levant!</l>
               <l>Sur <U+017F>on Chef dore<U+017F>enavant</l>
               <l>Vont éclatter plus glorieu<U+017F>es:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Calecut</hi> &amp; <hi>Goa</hi> <U+017F>oumi<U+017F>es à <U+017F>a Loy,</l>
               <l>Du <hi>Belgique Lion</hi> ne craindront plus l'effroy.</l>
               <l>Celebrés donc cette journee,</l>
               <l>Chantans Hymen! O Hymenée!</l>
               <l>Rendés de <hi>CHARLES</hi> en tous lieux</l>
               <l>Le recit glorieux.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>V.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Zeilan</hi> envoyera <U+017F>on Ivoire,</l>
               <l>Et ces precieux aromats,</l>
               <l>Dont <U+017F>ur tous les autres climats</l>
               <l>Ses foréts remportent la gloire:</l>
               <l>Plus gros de Diamans le <hi>Gange</hi> roulera,</l>
               <l>Et l'<hi>Inde</hi> pour luy <U+017F>eul <U+017F>es perles nourrira.</l>
               <l>Celebrés donc cette journée,</l>
               <l>Chantans Hymen! O Hymenée!</l>
               <l>Rendés de <hi>CHARLES</hi> en tous lieux,</l>
               <l>Le recit glorieux.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:45449:17"/>
               <head>VI.</head>
               <l>Le Prince oppre<U+017F><U+017F>é de la <hi>Chine</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ne <U+017F>achant plus qui réclamer</l>
               <l>Le viendra bien to<U+017F>t proclamer</l>
               <l>Seigneur de la ronde <hi>Machine;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Et le <hi>Cham</hi> atterré <U+017F>ous le <hi>Lion Anglois;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Tremblant luy <U+017F>oumettra <U+017F>on Arc et <U+017F>on Carquois.</l>
               <l>Doncques Hymen! O Hymenée!</l>
               <l>Chante à jamais cette journée</l>
               <l>Et Rends de <hi>CHARLES</hi> en tous lieux</l>
               <l>Le recit glorieux.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <l>L'<hi>Afrique</hi> à l'envy de l'<hi>A<U+017F>ie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Sous l'abri de <U+017F>es bras pui<U+017F><U+017F>ans</l>
               <l>Va produire en <U+017F>es Bois l encens,</l>
               <l>Et dans <U+017F>es vergers l'Ambro<U+017F>ie:</l>
               <l>Et de leurs veines d'or pour enrichir nos ports,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Melinde</hi> &amp; <hi>Quiloa</hi> tariront les tre<U+017F>ors.</l>
               <l>Celebrons donc cette journée,</l>
               <l>Chantans Hymen! O Hymenée!</l>
               <l>Rendons de <hi>CHARLES</hi> en tous lieux</l>
               <l>Le recit glorieux.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:45449:17"/>
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <l>Du <hi>Jappon</hi> à la <hi>Mozambique,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>De là ju<U+017F>qu aux fins d'Occident,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>CHARLES</hi> des Honneurs du Trident</l>
               <l>Va <U+017F>e rendre l'Arbitre unique;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Olinde</hi> e<U+017F>pere, en Luy <U+017F>es conque<U+017F>tes bornant,</l>
               <l>Se voir bien to<U+017F>t le Chef de <U+017F>on grand Continent.</l>
               <l>Celebrons donc cette journée.</l>
               <l>Et Toy Hymen! ô Hymenée!</l>
               <l>Va de <hi>CHARLES</hi> rendre en tous lieux</l>
               <l>Le recit glorieux.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="9">
               <head>IX.</head>
               <l>Nymphes, n'épargnés point les Ro<U+017F>es,</l>
               <l>Par<U+017F>emés en toutes nos eaux,</l>
               <l>Voiés comme <U+017F>ous Ses Vai<U+017F><U+017F>eaux</l>
               <l>Elles <U+017F>ont promtement éclo<U+017F>es:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>CATHERINE</hi> à changé l'influence des Cieux,</l>
               <l>Et la <hi>Fleur de Cypris</hi> va regner en tous lieux.</l>
               <l>Celebrons donc cette journée</l>
               <l>Et Toy Hymen! O Hymenée!</l>
               <l>Rends de <hi>CATHERINE</hi> en teus lieux</l>
               <l>Le recit glorieux.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="10">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:45449:18"/>
               <head>X.</head>
               <l>Marions le myrthe à la flame</l>
               <l>De ces belles et cha<U+017F>tes fleurs,</l>
               <l>Le myrthe aime entre les couleurs</l>
               <l>Le blanc Symbole de Son Ame;</l>
               <l>Ces fleurs à l'advenir vont regner en tous lieux,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>CATHERINE</hi> a changé l'influence des Cieux.</l>
               <l>Doncques Hymen! ô Hymeneé!</l>
               <l>Chante cette heureu<U+017F>e journée,</l>
               <l>Rends de <hi>CATHERINE</hi> en tous lieux</l>
               <l>Le recit glorieux.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="11">
               <head>XI.</head>
               <l>Je voy voler l'Oi<U+017F>eau fidelle</l>
               <l>Qui traine le char de Cypris,</l>
               <l>Du plaisir de ce jour épris</l>
               <l>Vers la <hi>Tami<U+017F>e</hi> à tire d'aile;</l>
               <l>Portant dedans <U+017F>on bec <U+017F>ous les re<U+017F>nes d' Amour,</l>
               <l>Un rameau de <U+017F>on myrthe en faveur de ce jour:</l>
               <l>Celebrons donc cette journée;</l>
               <l>Et Toy Hymen! o Hymenée!</l>
               <l>Rends de <hi>CATHERINE</hi> en tous lieux</l>
               <l>Le recit glorieux..</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="12">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:45449:18"/>
               <head>XII.</head>
               <l>Je voy de<U+017F>ia <U+017F>ur cette rive</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pallas</hi> s'appre<U+017F>ter aux tournois,</l>
               <l>Po<U+017F>ant <U+017F>on belliqueux harnois</l>
               <l>Pour <U+017F>e couronner de l' Olive:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>CATHERINE</hi> a changé l'influence des Cieux,</l>
               <l>La Concorde &amp; la Paix vont regner en ces lieux.</l>
               <l>Celebrons donc cette journée;</l>
               <l>Et Toy Hymen! ô Hymenée!</l>
               <l>Rends de <hi>CATHERINE</hi> en tous lieux</l>
               <l>Le recit glorieux.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="13">
               <head>XIII.</head>
               <l>Mille Amours chargés de guirlandes</l>
               <l>Et tenans des Palmes en main,</l>
               <l>Ont di<U+017F>po<U+017F>é <U+017F>ur Son chemin</l>
               <l>Leurs jeunes et folâtres bandes;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Catherine</hi> des yeux la merveille et L' Amour,</l>
               <l>Fait l'ame et l'ornement de cet aimable jour<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
               </l>
               <l>Celebrons donc cette journée</l>
               <l>Et Toy Hymen! ô Hymenée!</l>
               <l>Rends de <hi>CATHERINE</hi> en tous lieux</l>
               <l>Le recitglorieux.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="14">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:45449:19"/>
               <head>XIV.</head>
               <l>Bref, je voy cette Heureu<U+017F>e Terre</l>
               <l>Qui doit bien to<U+017F>t la po<U+017F><U+017F>eder,</l>
               <l>Avec mille <U+017F>oins <U+017F>econder</l>
               <l>Les veux du <hi>Prince d'Angleterre;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Etce Prince amoureux, pour charmer <U+017F>on tourment</l>
               <l>Sur le rivage Anglois conter chaque moment.</l>
               <l>Sus donc Hymen! ô Hymenée!</l>
               <l>Ha<U+017F>te cette heureu<U+017F>e journée!</l>
               <l>Et va publier en tous lieux,</l>
               <l>Son éclat glorieux.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="15">
               <head>XV.</head>
               <l>Ha<U+017F>te toy d'accomplir l'attente</l>
               <l>De ce Couple cheri des Cieux,</l>
               <l>De tes delais officieux</l>
               <l>L'un et l'autre s'impatiente:</l>
               <l>Ne tiens plus en <U+017F>u<U+017F>pens ces Illu<U+017F>tres Amans,</l>
               <l>Dont l'amoureu<U+017F>e ardeur conte tous les momens;</l>
               <l>Nymphes ha<U+017F>tons cette journée<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
               </l>
               <l>Chantons Hymen! ô Hymenée!</l>
               <l>Allons de ces Amans publier en tous lieux</l>
               <l>Le renom glorieux.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FIN.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45449:19"/>
            <head>A POEM ON St. Iamess PARK.</head>
            <byline>Written by <hi>Edmund Waller</hi> 
               <abbr>E<U+017F>q.</abbr>
            </byline>
            <lg>
               <l>OF the fir<U+017F>t Paradi<U+017F>e there's nothing found,</l>
               <l>Plants <U+017F>et by heav'n are vani<U+017F>ht, &amp; the ground;</l>
               <l>Yet the de<U+017F>cription la<U+017F>ts, who knows the fate</l>
               <l>Of lines that <U+017F>hall this Paradi<U+017F>e relate?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In<U+017F>tead of Rivers rolling by the <U+017F>ide</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Edens</hi> Garden, here flowes in the tyde;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:45449:20"/>
The Sea which always <U+017F>erv'd his Empire, now</l>
               <l>Pays tribute to our Prince's plea<U+017F>ure too.</l>
               <l>Of famous Cities we the founders know:</l>
               <l>But Rivers, old as Seas, to which they go,</l>
               <l>Are natures bounty; 'tis of more renown</l>
               <l>To make a River then to build a Town.</l>
               <l>For future <U+017F>hade young Trees upon the banks</l>
               <l>Of the new <U+017F>tream appear in even ranks:</l>
               <l>The voice of <hi>Orpheus</hi> or <hi>Amphions</hi> hand</l>
               <l>In better order could not make them <U+017F>tand.</l>
               <l>May they increa<U+017F>e as fa<U+017F>t, and <U+017F>pread their boughs,</l>
               <l>As the high fame of their great Owner growes!</l>
               <l>May he live long enough to <U+017F>ee them all</l>
               <l>Dark <U+017F>hadows ca<U+017F>t, and as his Palace tall.</l>
               <l>Me thinks I <U+017F>ee the love that <U+017F>hall be made,</l>
               <l>The Lovers walking in that Amorous <U+017F>hade,</l>
               <l>The Gallants dancing by the Rivers <U+017F>ide,</l>
               <l>They bath in Summer, and in Winter <U+017F>lide.</l>
               <l>Methinks I hear the Mu<U+017F>ick in the boats,</l>
               <l>And the loud Eccho which returns the notes,</l>
               <l>Whil<U+017F>t over head a flock of new <U+017F>prung fowle</l>
               <l>Hangs in the Aire, and does the Sun controle:</l>
               <l>Darkning the Sky they hover o're, and <U+017F>hrowd</l>
               <l>The wanton Saylors with a feather'd cloud;</l>
               <l>Beneath a <U+017F>hole of <U+017F>ilver fi<U+017F>hes glides,</l>
               <l>And plays about the guilded Barges <U+017F>ides;</l>
               <l>The Ladies angling in the Chri<U+017F>tal lake,</l>
               <l>Fea<U+017F>t on the water with the prey they take;</l>
               <l>At once victorious with their lines and eyes</l>
               <l>They make the fi<U+017F>hes and the men their prize:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:45449:20"/>
A thou<U+017F>and Cupids on the billows <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ide,</l>
               <l>And Sea-nymphs enter with the <U+017F>welling tyde,</l>
               <l>From <hi>Thetis</hi> <U+017F>ent as <U+017F>pies to make report,</l>
               <l>And tell the wonders of her Soveraign's Court.</l>
               <l>All that can living feed the greedy eye,</l>
               <l>Or dead the Pallat here you may de<U+017F>cry.</l>
               <l>The choice<U+017F>t things that furni<U+017F>ht <hi>Noahs</hi> Ark,</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Peters</hi> <U+017F>heet inhabiting this Park:</l>
               <l>All with a border of rich fruit-trees crown'd,</l>
               <l>Who<U+017F>e loaded branches hide the lofty mound.</l>
               <l>Such various wayes the <U+017F>pacious Alleys lead,</l>
               <l>My doubtful Mu<U+017F>e knows not what path to tread:</l>
               <l>Yonder the harve<U+017F>t of cold Months laid up,</l>
               <l>Gives a fre<U+017F>h coolne<U+017F><U+017F>e to the Royal Cup,</l>
               <l>There Ice like Chri<U+017F>tal, firm and never lo<U+017F>t,</l>
               <l>Tempers hot <hi>July</hi> with <hi>Decembers</hi> fro<U+017F>t,</l>
               <l>Winters dark pri<U+017F>on whence he cannot flie,</l>
               <l>Though the warm Spring, his enemy draws nigh:</l>
               <l>Strange! that extreams <U+017F>hould thus pre<U+017F>erve the <U+017F>now,</l>
               <l>High on the <hi>Alpes,</hi> or in deep Caves below.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Here a well-poli<U+017F>ht Mall gives us the joy</l>
               <l>To <U+017F>ee our Prince his matchle<U+017F>s force imploy;</l>
               <l>His manly po<U+017F>ture and his graceful mine,</l>
               <l>Vigor and youth in all his motion <U+017F>een,</l>
               <l>His <U+017F>hape <U+017F>o lovely and his limbs <U+017F>o <U+017F>trong</l>
               <l>Confirm our hopes we <U+017F>hall obey him long.</l>
               <l>No <U+017F>ooner has he toucht the flying ball,</l>
               <l>But 'tis already more then half the mall,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:45449:21"/>
And <U+017F>uch a fury from his arm has got</l>
               <l>As from a <U+017F>moking Culverin 'twere <U+017F>hot:</l>
               <l>May that ill Fate my enemies befall</l>
               <l>To <U+017F>tand before his anger or his ball!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Near this my Mu<U+017F>e, what mo<U+017F>t delights her, <U+017F>ees</l>
               <l>A living Gallery of aged Trees;</l>
               <l>Bold <U+017F>ons of earth! that thru<U+017F>t their arms <U+017F>o high</l>
               <l>As if once more they would invade the sky;</l>
               <l>In <U+017F>uch green Palaces the fir<U+017F>t Kings reign'd,</l>
               <l>Slept in their <U+017F>hades, and Angels entertain'd:</l>
               <l>With <U+017F>uch old Coun<U+017F>ellors they did advi<U+017F>e,</l>
               <l>And by frequenting <U+017F>acred Groves grew wi<U+017F>e;</l>
               <l>Free from the impediments of light and noi<U+017F>e</l>
               <l>Man thus retir'd his nobler thoughts imploys.</l>
               <l>Here CHARLES contrives the ord'ring of his States,</l>
               <l>Here he re<U+017F>olves his neighb'ring Princes Fates:</l>
               <l>What Nation <U+017F>hall have Peace, where War be made,</l>
               <l>Determin'd is in this oraculous <U+017F>hade:</l>
               <l>The world, from <hi>India</hi> to the frozen North,</l>
               <l>Concern'd in what this Solitude brings forth.</l>
               <l>His Fancy objects from his view receives,</l>
               <l>The pro<U+017F>pect thought and contemplation gives:</l>
               <l>That Seat of Empire here <U+017F>alutes his eye,</l>
               <l>To which three Kingdomes do them<U+017F>elves apply,</l>
               <l>The <U+017F>tructure by a Prelate rais'd, <hi>White-Hall,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Built with the fortune of <hi>Romes</hi> Capitol;</l>
               <l>Both di<U+017F>proportion'd to the pre<U+017F>ent State</l>
               <l>Of their proud Founders, were approv'd by Fate.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:45449:21"/>
From hence he does that Antique Pile behold,</l>
               <l>Where Royal heads receive the <U+017F>acred gold;</l>
               <l>It gives them Crowns, and does their a<U+017F>hes keep;</l>
               <l>There made like gods, like mortals there they <U+017F>leep:</l>
               <l>When others fell, this <U+017F>tanding did pre<U+017F>age,</l>
               <l>The Crown <U+017F>hould triumph over popular rage,</l>
               <l>Hard by that Hou<U+017F>e where all our ills where <U+017F>hap'd</l>
               <l>Th' Au<U+017F>picious Temple <U+017F>tood, and yet e<U+017F>cap'd.</l>
               <l>So <U+017F>now on <hi>Aetna</hi> does unmelted lie,</l>
               <l>Whence rolling flames and <U+017F>catter'd cinders flie;</l>
               <l>The di<U+017F>tant Countrey in the ruine <U+017F>hares,</l>
               <l>What falls from heav'n the burning mountain <U+017F>pares.</l>
               <l>Next that capacious Hall, he <U+017F>ees the room,</l>
               <l>Where the whole Nation does for Ju<U+017F>tice come:</l>
               <l>Under who<U+017F>e large roof flouri<U+017F>hes the Gown,</l>
               <l>And Judges grave on high Tribunals frown.</l>
               <l>Here like the peoples Pa<U+017F>tor he does goe,</l>
               <l>His flock <U+017F>ubjected to his view below:</l>
               <l>On which reflecting in his mighty mind,</l>
               <l>No private pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion does indulgence find;</l>
               <l>The plea<U+017F>ures of his youth <U+017F>u<U+017F>pended are,</l>
               <l>And made a <U+017F>acrifice to publick care;</l>
               <l>Here free from Court compliances He walks,</l>
               <l>And with him<U+017F>elf, his be<U+017F>t advi<U+017F>er, talks;</l>
               <l>How peaceful Olive may his Temples <U+017F>hade,</l>
               <l>For mending Laws, and for re<U+017F>toring trade;</l>
               <l>Or how his Browes may be with Laurel charg'd</l>
               <l>For Nations conquer'd and our bounds inlarg'd:</l>
               <l>Of ancient Prudence here He ruminates,</l>
               <l>Of ri<U+017F>ing Kingdoms and of falling States:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:45449:22"/>
What Ruling Arts gave great <hi>Augu<U+017F>tus</hi> fame,</l>
               <l>And how <hi>Alcides</hi> purchas'd <U+017F>uch a name:</l>
               <l>His eyes upon his native Palace bent</l>
               <l>Clo<U+017F>e by, <U+017F>ugge<U+017F>t a greater argument,</l>
               <l>His thoughts ri<U+017F>e higher when he does reflect,</l>
               <l>On what the world may from that Star expect</l>
               <l>Which at his Birth appear'd to let us <U+017F>ee</l>
               <l>Day for his <U+017F>ake could with the night agree;</l>
               <l>A Prince on whom <U+017F>uch different lights did <U+017F>mile,</l>
               <l>Born the divided World to reconcile:</l>
               <l>What ever Heaven or high extracted blood,</l>
               <l>Could promi<U+017F>e or foretell, he will make good:</l>
               <l>Reform the<U+017F>e Nations, and improve them more,</l>
               <l>Then this fair Park from what it was before.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:45449:22"/>
            <head>LE PARC DE S. IAMES.</head>
            <byline>Traduit de l'Anglois de Mr. WALLER.</byline>
            <lg>
               <l>DU premier Paradis il n'y a plus de trace,</l>
               <l>Et ce fameux Jardin ne trouue aucune place,</l>
               <l>Quoy que Dieu l'eu<U+017F>t daigné cultiuer de <U+017F>es mains,</l>
               <l>Sinon dans les Cayers des premiers E<U+017F>crivains.</l>
               <l>Qui <U+017F>cait, <U+017F>i de mes vers l'heureu<U+017F>e de<U+017F>tinée,</l>
               <l>D'vn <U+017F>uccés au<U+017F><U+017F>i beau <U+017F>era point couronnée</l>
               <l>Chantant ce Paradis? ou le flot de la Mer,</l>
               <l>Au lieu des Eaux d'Eden vient <U+017F>es ondes calmer,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:45449:23"/>
Et ce fier Element de mon Roy Tributaire,</l>
               <l>Par de nouue aux devoirs <U+017F>'efforcant de luy plaire,</l>
               <l>Et contraint d'obeyr á <U+017F>on Royal de<U+017F><U+017F>ein,</l>
               <l>Pour remplir un Canal vuide <U+017F>on propre <U+017F>ein.</l>
               <l>Des fameu<U+017F>es Cités l'origine e<U+017F>t connüe,</l>
               <l>Les fleuues au<U+017F><U+017F>i vieils que leur mere chenue</l>
               <l>Sont vn don de Nature, et la po<U+017F>terité</l>
               <l>E<U+017F>time beaucoup moins l'Autheur d'une Cité,</l>
               <l>Que celuy qui rendant les ondes pri<U+017F>onnieres</l>
               <l>Fait reculer la Terre, &amp; naitre des riuieres.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Es bords de ce Canal maints ieunes arbri<U+017F><U+017F>eaux,</l>
               <l>Nous promettent de ioindre un iour auec <U+017F>es eaux</l>
               <l>La fre<U+017F>cheur de leur ombre, et leur ordre agreable</l>
               <l>D'Orphée et d'Amphion re<U+017F><U+017F>u<U+017F>cite la Fable:</l>
               <l>Mais leur Luth immortel et leurs charmantes voix,</l>
               <l>Eurent moins que mon Roy l'art d'animer les bois.</l>
               <l>Pui<U+017F><U+017F>ent vos frais rameaux, beau plant, croitre au<U+017F><U+017F>i vite,</l>
               <l>Que de votre Seigneur fait l'Illu<U+017F>tre merite!</l>
               <l>Et Luy, qu'il viue a<U+017F><U+017F>ez pour <U+017F>e voir faire vn Daiz</l>
               <l>De vôtre ombre, excedant en hauteur <U+017F>on Palais!</l>
               <l>Déia ma Mu<U+017F>e voit les mignardes care<U+017F><U+017F>es,</l>
               <l>Que feront mille Amans vn iour á leurs Maitre<U+017F><U+017F>es</l>
               <l>Sous vos beaux promenoirs, leurs dances, et leurs ieux;</l>
               <l>Sur le bord de ces eaux ie voy bruler leurs feux;</l>
               <l>On s'y baigne l'E<U+017F>té, puis quand l'huyuer decoche</l>
               <l>Sur les eaux <U+017F>a fureur, <U+017F>on beau cry<U+017F>tal de roche</l>
               <l>Y<U+017F>ert de galerie á mille audacieux,</l>
               <l>Tanto<U+017F>t <U+017F>ur le Patin, tanto<U+017F>t <U+017F>ur des e<U+017F><U+017F>ieux.</l>
               <l>Il me <U+017F>emble déia que i'entens la Mu<U+017F>ique</l>
               <l>De cent petits bateaux, <U+017F>ur qui l' Echo pratique</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:45449:23"/>
Ses curieux accens, <U+017F>e formant des lecons</l>
               <l>Du <U+017F>uiet amoureux de leurs douces chan<U+017F>ons.</l>
               <l>Cependant <U+017F>ur leur te<U+017F>te, un gros d'oi<U+017F>eau <U+017F>auvage</l>
               <l>Su<U+017F>pendu dans les airs au Soleil fait ombrage,</l>
               <l>Ob<U+017F>curci<U+017F><U+017F>ant le ciel, et ioüant <U+017F>ur ces flots</l>
               <l>D'un nuage emplumé voile les Matelots.</l>
               <l>Les poi<U+017F><U+017F>ons plus nombreux qu' és plaines azurées,</l>
               <l>S'y font voir au de<U+017F><U+017F>ous, et des Barges dorées</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>iennent en s'ebattant admirer les co<U+017F>tés,</l>
               <l>Sans crainte abandonnant leur vie á cent Beautés,</l>
               <l>Qui tendent <U+017F>ur ces eaux leurs amorces trompeu<U+017F>es,</l>
               <l>Pour en faire les mets de leurs tables pompeu<U+017F>es,</l>
               <l>Et par leurs yeux vainqueurs ioints à leurs hamecons,</l>
               <l>Font un doub'e butin d'hommes et de poi<U+017F><U+017F>ons;</l>
               <l>Cent Cupidons ai<U+017F>lés folâtrent <U+017F>ur ces ondes,</l>
               <l>Mille Nymphes de mer s'y coulent vagabondes</l>
               <l>Quand le flot y retourne, á de<U+017F><U+017F>ein de <U+017F>cavoir</l>
               <l>De la part de Thetys, quels objets s'y font voir,</l>
               <l>Et puis á leur retour, étallant les merveilles</l>
               <l>De la Cour de <U+017F>on Prince, y charmer <U+017F>es oreilles;</l>
               <l>Tout ce qui peut flatter, mort ou vivant les <U+017F>ens</l>
               <l>De la veüe ou du gou<U+017F>t, de plai<U+017F>irs innocens,</l>
               <l>Se trouve dans ce Parc, ou l'oeil <U+017F>urpris remarqne</l>
               <l>Autant d'objets divers qu'eut la premiere Barque,</l>
               <l>Ou le drap qui fut veu par l' Apo<U+017F>tre Pe<U+017F>cheur,</l>
               <l>Quand il vint convertir le Centenier pecheur.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Toute ce<U+017F>te abondance en <U+017F>uitte <U+017F>e couronne</l>
               <l>Par un riche E<U+017F>palier, que la belle Pomone</l>
               <l>Vient fournir tous les ans de <U+017F>es mets delicats</l>
               <l>Et charger de Pauys, d' Abricots, et Mu<U+017F>cats.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:45449:24"/>
               <l>Tant de beaux promenoirs charment ici la veiie.</l>
               <l>Que ma Mu<U+017F>e en leur choix <U+017F>e trouve confondue:</l>
               <l>Prés de la des hyvers les <U+017F>teriles moi<U+017F><U+017F>ons,</l>
               <l>Gardentau vin Royal leur neige et leurs glacons;</l>
               <l>Des cry<U+017F>taux de Januier les pointes violentes</l>
               <l>Temperent des E<U+017F>tés les haleines brulantes,</l>
               <l>Et du fievreux Lion les cui<U+017F>antes ardeurs,</l>
               <l>Cedent au moindre effort de leurs bru<U+017F>ques froideurs,</l>
               <l>Tant l'art a de pouvoir pour arre<U+017F>ter leur fuitte!</l>
               <l>Quoy que le chaud Printemps venant à leur pour<U+017F>uitte,</l>
               <l>Des Zephyrs ennemis emprunte les poulmons,</l>
               <l>Et les pou<U+017F><U+017F>e en fuyant iu<U+017F>qu' au fai<U+017F>te des monts,</l>
               <l>Ou precipite en bas, ou la neige en<U+017F>errée,</l>
               <l>Attend dans <U+017F>es cachots le <U+017F>ecours de Borée.</l>
               <l>Cho<U+017F>e etrange! de voir deux extrêmes s'unir,</l>
               <l>Et dans un me<U+017F>me effet comme amis convenir!</l>
               <l>Soit au coupeau gelé des Alpes <U+017F>ourceilleu<U+017F>es,</l>
               <l>Où dans la profondeur des grottes tenebreu<U+017F>es!</l>
               <l>Ici dans un long Mail, nous avons le plai<U+017F>ir</l>
               <l>De contempler <U+017F>ouvent <hi>no<U+017F>tre Prince</hi> á loi<U+017F>ir,</l>
               <l>Et luy voir exercer <U+017F>a force incomparable,</l>
               <l>Admirer <U+017F>on addre<U+017F><U+017F>e et <U+017F>a taille agreable,</l>
               <l>Son corps <U+017F>i bien placé, <U+017F>es iu<U+017F>tes monvemens,</l>
               <l>Sa vigueur, <U+017F>a Jeune<U+017F><U+017F>e, et <U+017F>es regards charmans:</l>
               <l>Pléges de no<U+017F>tre e<U+017F>poir, infaillible a<U+017F><U+017F>urance,</l>
               <l>Qu'il joüira long temps de no<U+017F>tre obéi<U+017F><U+017F>ance.</l>
               <l>A grand peine le coup e<U+017F>t parti de <U+017F>a main,</l>
               <l>Que la boule a de<U+017F>ia fait moitié du chemin</l>
               <l>De toute la longueur, et s' échappe á la veüe</l>
               <l>Recevant de <U+017F>on bras <U+017F>a vite<U+017F><U+017F>e impreveüe,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:45449:24"/>
Et <U+017F>e fait un pa<U+017F><U+017F>age au<U+017F><U+017F>i prompt dedans l'air,</l>
               <l>Qu'alors que du Canon la foudre <U+017F>uit l'eclair.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="bottom">ces 2 vers <U+017F>ont nece<U+017F><U+017F>airement adjoutés pour reprendre la rime ma<U+017F>culine, quoy qu'é oignés du texte de l'Autheur, qui e<U+017F>t une des contraintes de nótre poe<U+017F>ie Francoi<U+017F>e, qui en l'Angloi<U+017F>e auro't peu s'excu<U+017F>er. La Fable au <U+017F>urplus e<U+017F>t a<U+017F><U+017F>és connüe.</note> Plus <U+017F>oudain qu' autrefois pour <U+017F>es droits y deffendre,</l>
               <l>Jupiter ne parut <U+017F>ur les bords du Scamandre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Là contre, un long Berceau d'arbres chenus et vieux</l>
               <l>Delices d' Apollon, <U+017F>e pre<U+017F>ente á nos yeux:</l>
               <l>Leurs bras tendus au ciel, en vrays fils de la Terre,</l>
               <l>Semblent luy declarer une <U+017F>econde guerre:</l>
               <l>Sous les <U+017F>acrés Palais de tels Antiques bois,</l>
               <l>Les premiers des humains virent les premiers Roys:</l>
               <l>Des Anges vi<U+017F>ités <U+017F>ous ces manoirs <U+017F>auvages,</l>
               <l>Ils prirent leur repos de<U+017F><U+017F>ous leurs frais ombrages,</l>
               <l>S'y tinrent iour et nuit con<U+017F>ultans avec eux,</l>
               <l>Et parvindrent en fin au rang des Demi-dieux.</l>
               <l>L'homme ain<U+017F>i loin du jour et <U+017F>ans inquietude</l>
               <l>Se po<U+017F><U+017F>ede bien mieux dedans la <U+017F>olitude.</l>
               <l>Lá <hi>CHARLES</hi> ruminant au bien de <U+017F>es Etats</l>
               <l>Ordonne du De<U+017F>tin des autres Potentats:</l>
               <l>Balancant l'intere<U+017F>t du re<U+017F>te de la terre,</l>
               <l>Partage aux Nations ou la Paix ou la Guerre,</l>
               <l>Et <U+017F>elon <U+017F>on plai<U+017F>ir de l' Inde ou bien du Nort,</l>
               <l>Sous ces rameaux <U+017F>acrés determine le <U+017F>ort:</l>
               <l>Par les objets de l'oeil <U+017F>on ame e<U+017F>t élevée,</l>
               <l>Jusqu' á ce qu' à <U+017F>a <U+017F>phere elle <U+017F>oit arrivée:</l>
               <l>L' a<U+017F>pect des lieux frappant l'imagination,</l>
               <l>Excite et puis <U+017F>outient <U+017F>a contemplation.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Le <hi>Siege de <U+017F>on Throne</hi> e<U+017F>t le premier en veüe,</l>
               <l>Il <U+017F>emble qu'à l'enuy <U+017F>on Seigneur il Salüe,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:45449:25"/>
Cet Augu<U+017F>te Palais qui de trois Nations</l>
               <l>Unit l'obei<U+017F><U+017F>ance et les affections:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whital,</hi> qu'un grand Prelat fonda dans <U+017F>a Pui<U+017F><U+017F>ance,</l>
               <l>Et dont le Capitole auanca la nai<U+017F><U+017F>ance,</l>
               <l>Superbes Batimens! tous deux trop relevés</l>
               <l>Par de<U+017F><U+017F>us vos Autheurs! cependant approuvés</l>
               <l>Par le <U+017F>ecret con<U+017F>eil des <U+017F>ages De<U+017F>tinees,</l>
               <l>Pour recevoir chéz vous des Te<U+017F>tes couronnées.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ant plus outre il voit la Chapelle, ou nos Roys</l>
               <l>Recoivent l'or <U+017F>acré <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> leur gardent les Loix.</l>
               <l>Sa Terre au<U+017F><U+017F>i <U+017F>acrée également leur donne,</l>
               <l>Le droit de Sepulture et le droit de Couronne.</l>
               <l>Lá le Sceptre les rend un peu moindres que Dieux,</l>
               <l>Puis comme à des mortels la Mort fermant leurs yeux,</l>
               <l>Les égale á la poudre. Au<U+017F><U+017F>i cette Structure</l>
               <l>Quand les autres crolloyent, eut meilleure avanture,</l>
               <l>Et demeura debout, pre<U+017F>ageant que du fer</l>
               <l>Des Peuples mutinés on verroit triompher</l>
               <l>Le Sceptre rétabli, ce Monument Superbe</l>
               <l>Echapa du danger d'e<U+017F>tre caché <U+017F>ous l'herbe,</l>
               <l>Quoy qu'il avoi<U+017F>ina<U+017F>t eette <hi>fiere Mai<U+017F>on</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Qui de nos maux pa<U+017F><U+017F>és forgea la Trahi<U+017F>on.</l>
               <l>Ain<U+017F>i lors que l' Etna, de <U+017F>a cendre embra<U+017F>ée</l>
               <l>Ravage la Sicile á <U+017F>es <U+017F>tancs expo<U+017F>ée,</l>
               <l>La neige au haut du mont con<U+017F>erve <U+017F>a froideur,</l>
               <l>Et triomphe au milieu de la brulante ardeur;</l>
               <l>Un torrent tout de feu de<U+017F>cendant des montagnes</l>
               <l>Et <U+017F>oüillant le tapis des voi<U+017F>ines Campagnes,</l>
               <l>Prive le Laboureur de l'e<U+017F>poir des moi<U+017F><U+017F>ons,</l>
               <l>Cependant qu'aù <U+017F>ommet il nourrit des glacons.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:45449:25"/>
               <l>Apres tous ces objets, une ample et va<U+017F>te Salle,</l>
               <l>Son Antique <U+017F>tructure aux yeux du <hi>Prince</hi> étalle,</l>
               <l>Oú Themis expliquant les droits de Maje<U+017F>té,</l>
               <l>Range Trois Nations <U+017F>ous <U+017F>on Authorité:</l>
               <l>La violence icy devient calme, et revere</l>
               <l>La robbe et le regard de <U+017F>on Juge <U+017F>evere;</l>
               <l>Icy comme un Pa<U+017F>teur du <U+017F>ommet des coupeaux,</l>
               <l>Contemple avec plai<U+017F>ir <U+017F>es vagabonds troupeaux</l>
               <l>Repai<U+017F><U+017F>ans dans la Plaine, avec indifference</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>CHARLES</hi> partage aux <U+017F>iens et l'aise et l'abondance:</l>
               <l>Nul deplai<U+017F>ir <U+017F>ecret ne luy ronge le coeur,</l>
               <l>Aucun re<U+017F><U+017F>entiment de <U+017F>a rai<U+017F>on vainqueur,</l>
               <l>Ne trouble en <U+017F>es efforts le calme de <U+017F>on ame,</l>
               <l>Sa Jeune<U+017F><U+017F>e au public donne toute <U+017F>a flame,</l>
               <l>Il <U+017F>u<U+017F>pend pour <U+017F>on bien tous ces boüillans de<U+017F>irs,</l>
               <l>Qui <U+017F>oumettent cet âge aux appas des plai<U+017F>irs:</l>
               <l>Seul icy delivré de la foule Hypocrite</l>
               <l>Du flattur Courti<U+017F>an, qui juge du merite</l>
               <l>Par le <U+017F>eul intere<U+017F>t, il medite á l' écart,</l>
               <l>Sans qu' antre en <U+017F>es con<U+017F>eils que luy me<U+017F>me ait de part:</l>
               <l>Son âme en cet état, comme la plus fidelle</l>
               <l>De tous <U+017F>es Con<U+017F>eillers, luy fournit le modelle</l>
               <l>D'un Gouverneur parfait, luy met devant les yeux</l>
               <l>Ce qui peut rendre un jour un Prince glorieux,</l>
               <l>Luy <U+017F>uggere comment bien to<U+017F>t la voix publique</l>
               <l>Mettra de<U+017F><U+017F>us <U+017F>on front l'Olive pacifique,</l>
               <l>Pour avoir rétabli le Commerce et les Loix;</l>
               <l>Comment apres avoir <U+017F>oumis les autres Roys</l>
               <l>A <U+017F>es ju<U+017F>tes de<U+017F>irs, élargi <U+017F>es Domaines,</l>
               <l>De <U+017F>on los immortel les bouches <U+017F>eront plaines,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:45449:26"/>
Et <U+017F>on Chef de Lauriers; icy des vieils Heros</l>
               <l>La prudence il repa<U+017F><U+017F>e et leurs <U+017F>ages propos,</l>
               <l>La cheute des Etats, et quelles De<U+017F>tinées</l>
               <l>Avancent la grandeur des Te<U+017F>tes Couronées:</l>
               <l>Par quel art de regner Augu<U+017F>te eut tant de Nom,</l>
               <l>Comment Alcide peut <U+017F>e faire un tel renom;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Mais un plus haut <U+017F>uiet entretient <U+017F>a pen<U+017F>ée,</l>
               <l>Luy fai<U+017F>ant rappeler <U+017F>on Enfance pa<U+017F><U+017F>ée,</l>
               <l>Quand <U+017F>on Palais natal vient s'offrir á <U+017F>es yeux,</l>
               <l>Et porte <U+017F>es e<U+017F>prits ju<U+017F>qu' aux Spheres des Cieux.</l>
               <l>Il reflechit combien, cette Etoille éclattante</l>
               <l>Qu'on vit <U+017F>ur <U+017F>on berceau, tient l'Europe en attenté;</l>
               <l>Cet A<U+017F>tre, qu' á de<U+017F><U+017F>ein le Ciel <U+017F>embla former,</l>
               <l>Pour montrer que pour luy la Nuit pouvoit aimer</l>
               <l>L'embra<U+017F><U+017F>ement du jour, luy s'unir avec elle,</l>
               <l>Et faire en <U+017F>a faveur une ligue nouvelle.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O <hi>Prince <U+017F>ans égall</hi> duquel en me<U+017F>me temps</l>
               <l>Deux A<U+017F>tres <U+017F>e <U+017F>ont veus, entr' eux <U+017F>i differens,</l>
               <l>Re<U+017F>pecter la nai<U+017F><U+017F>ance! e<U+017F>t ce pas cho<U+017F>e ju<U+017F>te,</l>
               <l>Qu'on e<U+017F>pere de voir <U+017F>ous Ton Empire Augu<U+017F>te</l>
               <l>Le Monde divi<U+017F>é compo<U+017F>er <U+017F>es di<U+017F>cords,</l>
               <l>Et <U+017F>ous un me<U+017F>me Chef ne faire plus qu'un corps?</l>
               <l>Tout ce que nous pouvoit Ta Nai<U+017F><U+017F>ance promettre,</l>
               <l>Ou le Ciel pre<U+017F>ager alors qu'il te vit naitre,</l>
               <l>Tu le vas accomplir; ne reformant pas moins</l>
               <l>Tes Peuples cultivés pas Tes Augu<U+017F>tes <U+017F>oins,</l>
               <l>Qu'ils ont changé ce Parc, qui nous <U+017F>emble renaitre</l>
               <l>Et comme rajeunir depuis qu'il Ta' pour Maitre,</l>
               <l>Et par qui Tes Suiets peuvent dés icy bas,</l>
               <l>Ioüir d'un Paradis <U+017F>ans gouter le Trépas.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FIN.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:45449:26"/>
            <head>
               <hi>DE VIVARIO S. Iacobi</hi> WESTMON. <hi>à Sereni<U+017F><U+017F>ima MAJESTATE CAROLI II. nuper Exculto &amp; Reparato.</hi>
            </head>
            <byline>Ex Anglico Dom. EDM. WALLER. M.DC.LXII.</byline>
            <lg>
               <l>NUlla <note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Quamvis <U+017F>ecundùm pro<U+017F>odiae gr. leges, duae primae Syllabae breves e<U+017F><U+017F>e debere videantur, tamen quia nomen e<U+017F>t exoticum Parde<U+017F>. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
                        </gap>, licentiam fingendi quantit. <U+017F>umo. appo<U+017F><gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>è autem ad vivarium <U+017F>ive eju<U+017F>modi <U+017F>eptum de<U+017F>ignandum, ubi ferae aliaque animalia ad delicias nutriuntur, &amp; virgulto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum arborumque amoenitas ad voluptatem in quinquuncem compo<U+017F>itarum oculos pa<U+017F>cit, u<U+017F>urpatur; quales praecipué Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipum Per<U+017F>iae amoeni <U+017F>ece<U+017F><U+017F>us hoc nomine de<U+017F>ignati fuerunt. Inde Religio ad Coeli fruitionem Beatorumque <U+017F>edes per Metaphoram tran<U+017F>tulit.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Paradi<U+017F>i</hi> remanent ve<U+017F>tigia pri<U+017F>ci,</l>
               <l>Et quamvis cultore Deo jàm vanuit arbos</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:45449:27"/>
Atque <U+017F>olum foelix, <U+017F>ervat <U+017F>acra Pagina tantùm</l>
               <l>Quód <U+017F>upere<U+017F>t; quis <U+017F>cit, no<U+017F>tra haec quo carmina fato,</l>
               <l>Ip<U+017F>a <hi>Paradi<U+017F>um</hi> quoque de<U+017F>cribentia, <U+017F>urgent?</l>
               <l>Regis ubi virgulta manu plantata vire<U+017F>cunt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Hic fluvios imitata Thetys queis fertilis Eden</l>
               <l>Crevit, inoffeu<U+017F>os <U+017F>tagno infert languida fluctus;</l>
               <l>Utque fuit no<U+017F>tro <U+017F>emper famulata <hi>Monarchae<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
                  </hi>
               </l>
               <l>Delicias <hi>Briticae</hi> nunc &amp; Dea promovet <hi>Aulae.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fama refert urbes per quos crevêre vetu<U+017F>tae,</l>
               <l>Flumina verò annis Ponto certantia, cujus</l>
               <l>Condunturque <U+017F>inu, Naturae munere <U+017F>urgunt;</l>
               <l>Et fluviis praebere ortum, quàm condere gentem</l>
               <l>Majus opus, major labor e<U+017F>t: in margine ripae</l>
               <l>Multa recens arbor, <U+017F>urgit plantata decoro</l>
               <l>Ordine, moxque umbras promittit laet a futuras:</l>
               <l>Nec melius vel Thrax fidicen cum voce canorâ,</l>
               <l>Blandu<U+017F>ue Amphyon Sylvas traxere <U+017F>equaces,</l>
               <l>Cre<U+017F>cite jàm po<U+017F>thac, tenerae jàm cre<U+017F>cite Sylvae!</l>
               <l>Tam citò tamque altùm, Domini quàm fama monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas</l>
               <l>Antevenit <U+017F>uperatque alios noti<U+017F><U+017F>ima ve<U+017F>tri!</l>
               <l>Vivat is in tantos, fatis volventibus, annos!</l>
               <l>Donec eum lar ga umbra tegat, Regalibus aequet<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
               </l>
               <l>Luxurians donec truncus fa<U+017F>tigia Tectis:</l>
               <l>O! quoties teneri po<U+017F>thac ludetis Amores,</l>
               <l>Fronde <U+017F>ub hac viridi! quoties hîc <U+017F>picula figent</l>
               <l>Cordibus, ad ripas ducentes otia Nymphae!</l>
               <l>Jàm video certare procos, blandumque favorem</l>
               <l>Officiis captare, <U+017F>uas jam fallere cur as</l>
               <l>Lu<U+017F>ibus hîc variis, dum longo errore per umbram</l>
               <l>Incerto<U+017F>ve regunt gre<U+017F><U+017F>us ducuntve choreas:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:45449:27"/>
Ae<U+017F>tivo <U+017F>ub Sole natant, brumalia fallunt</l>
               <l>Frigora, ferratâ dùm <U+017F>ulcant aequora plantâ</l>
               <l>In glaciem durata; meos an Mu<U+017F>ica <U+017F>en<U+017F>us</l>
               <l>Decipit; an potiùs parvis incerta per undas</l>
               <l>Di<U+017F>currit cymbis, <U+017F>equitur dùm mobilis Echo,</l>
               <l>Atque not as tremulâ reparat cum voce cadentes?</l>
               <l>Sic e<U+017F>t: i<U+017F>ta decent <hi>Carolinum</hi> gaudia <hi>Saeclum.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Linquit aquas, <U+017F>ur<U+017F>úmque volat, perterritus ales</l>
               <l>Incola Stagnantis Lymphae, libran<U+017F>que per auras</l>
               <l>Remigium alarum, Phoebeae lampadis ignes</l>
               <l>Inficit ob<U+017F>curis glomeratâ nube tenebris,</l>
               <l>La<U+017F>civó<U+017F>que tegit pennae velamine Nautas.</l>
               <l>Intereà liquido <U+017F>ub marmore turba natantum</l>
               <l>Ludit, &amp; auratas miratur laeta carinas;</l>
               <l>In<U+017F>idias tremulâ dùm nectit arundine virgo</l>
               <l>In medio vagabunda lacu, praedáque potita</l>
               <l>Apponit <U+017F>ubitis Neptunia fercula men<U+017F>is.</l>
               <l>Sic oculo victrixque manu, cum duplice praedâ,</l>
               <l>Inque homines pi<U+017F>ce<U+017F>que <U+017F>imul (proh! dura) triumphat.</l>
               <l>Mille <U+017F>upervolitant circúmque feruntur Amores</l>
               <l>Dor<U+017F>a lacus, illos totidem Nymphaeque <U+017F>equuntur,</l>
               <l>Huc referente <U+017F>alo fluctus, ae<U+017F>túmque tumentem;</l>
               <l>Exploratrices veluti, Miracula Terrae</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>t <hi>Briticae</hi> narrent Thetydi, quoque Aula decore</l>
               <l>Emicet, &amp; quae <U+017F>it primae illîc gloria formae.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Hîc gu<U+017F>tum quodcunque juvat, vel lumina blandè</l>
               <l>Afficit, in parvo Septi concluditur orbe.</l>
               <l>Non plùs Arca Noae coepit, non lintea Petro</l>
               <l>Plus coelo demi<U+017F><U+017F>a, <U+017F>inu tenuere capaci.</l>
               <l>Hujus mult a ferax arbos extrema coronat,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:45449:28"/>
Et gravido moles operitur <U+017F>axea ramo.</l>
               <l>Illîc tam vario pandit <U+017F>e <U+017F>emita flexu,</l>
               <l>Incerta ut dubiis retrahat ve<U+017F>tigia plantis</l>
               <l>Mu<U+017F>a nimis diver<U+017F>a <U+017F>equens: hîc algida me<U+017F><U+017F>es</l>
               <l>Horrea brumales in Regia pocula <U+017F>ervant,</l>
               <l>Intactique gelu Zephyro chry<U+017F>talla retundunt</l>
               <l>Cani <U+017F>extiles ae<U+017F>tus torpore Decembris.</l>
               <l>Ob<U+017F>curus durú<U+017F>que hyemi perfringere carcer!</l>
               <l>Vere licèt tepido velut ho<U+017F>te in<U+017F>tante fugetur.</l>
               <l>Mirum! <U+017F>ic niveas inter pugnantia me<U+017F><U+017F>es</l>
               <l>Cre<U+017F>cere <U+017F>eu <U+017F>uperent Alpes, latiten<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve Cavernis!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Buxea <U+017F>phaera illic invictos Principis armos</l>
               <l>Exercet levi in <U+017F>tadio, gaudentibus ultrò</l>
               <l>Huic circumfu<U+017F>is <hi>Briticae</hi> Magnatibus <hi>Aulae,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Cum populi plaudente manu; cre<U+017F>citque (videnti</l>
               <l>Corporis invictúmque habitum nitidúmque leporem,</l>
               <l>Et vegetos motus, ro<U+017F>eae florémque Juventae,</l>
               <l>Membrorúmque decus, j<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nctae &amp; cùm robore formae,)</l>
               <l>Spes certa, ad <U+017F>eros fore duratura Nepotes</l>
               <l>Faelicé<U+017F>que diu, <hi>Carolini</hi> tempora Sceptri.</l>
               <l>Non citiùs <U+017F>en<U+017F>it ferientis verbera dextrae</l>
               <l>Sphaer<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> fugax, <U+017F>tadii medium quàm prona peregit,</l>
               <l>Pernici<U+017F>que trahens <U+017F>ecum cita fulmina tactus,</l>
               <l>Martis <U+017F>ulphureos imitatur motibus ignes.</l>
               <l>O! tantùm no<U+017F>tros hoc fatum <U+017F>pectet ad ho<U+017F>tes!</l>
               <l>Tales ut <U+017F>ubeant iras, ictu<U+017F>ve furorem!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Non procul hinc, no<U+017F>trae delectamenta Camaenae,</l>
               <l>Porticus anno<U+017F>â <U+017F>pectabilis arbore <U+017F>urgit,</l>
               <l>Terrigenûm quae in<U+017F>tar propè vertice nubila tangens,</l>
               <l>Stelliferum rur<U+017F>ùs <U+017F>can<U+017F>ura videtur Olympum.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:45449:28"/>
Talia <hi>Primaevi</hi> coluêre palatia <hi>Reges</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Sub viridi ramo, tali duxere <U+017F>ub umbrâ</l>
               <l>Somnos Angelico inter Sylvas ho<U+017F>pite laeti.</l>
               <l>Ta<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i in Concilio Populis crevêre verendi,</l>
               <l>Et <U+017F>acrâ <U+017F>ub fronde pios tenuêre Senatus.</l>
               <l>Scilicet objicibus lucis <U+017F>trepitu<U+017F>que remotis,</l>
               <l>Mens in <U+017F>e conver<U+017F>a animos ad graudia tollit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Hîc <hi>Carolus</hi> gaudet Regni firmare <U+017F>alutem,</l>
               <l>Vicini<U+017F>que <U+017F>uis partiri fata futurae</l>
               <l>Sortis; quos vel pace beet, vel Marte lece<U+017F><U+017F>at,</l>
               <l>I<U+017F>tius umbro<U+017F>i fiunt oracula templi.</l>
               <l>Atque adèo extremis ad Gangem à Gadibus u<U+017F>que,</l>
               <l>Omnis in hunc Orbis defixa e<U+017F>t cura Rece<U+017F><U+017F>um.</l>
               <l>Mentem objecta movent, oculis allata mini<U+017F>tris,</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>ndique divinam <hi>Caroli</hi> affectu<U+017F>que <U+017F>ilenti</l>
               <l>Ex variâ rerum na<U+017F>cuntur imagine Regi.</l>
               <l>Hîc primò Imperii Sedes excel<U+017F>a <U+017F>alutat</l>
               <l>Principis Augu<U+017F>tum lumen, cui jura Coronae</l>
               <l>Sunt triplicis, cujus Populi tres ju<U+017F><U+017F>a cape<U+017F><U+017F>unt:</l>
               <l>Prae<U+017F>ulis ambitio<U+017F>a domus! cel<U+017F>ique Penates!</l>
               <l>Nunc Signati <hi>Aulae</hi> fortunâ nominis <hi>Albae,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Et qui Tarpeias fulti crevere per arces!</l>
               <l>Impare quippe <U+017F>uis Arces Authoribus ambo</l>
               <l>Sorte caput Fato<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> probante, ad nubila tollunt.</l>
               <l>Hic etiam veteris <U+017F>pectanda cacumina Fani</l>
               <l>A<U+017F><U+017F>urgunt oculis, ubi Regum more perenni,</l>
               <l>Induitur <U+017F>acrae Cervix fulgore Coronae:</l>
               <l>Regibus hîc cre<U+017F>cunt Diademata, manibus <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>rnae</l>
               <l>Hic Regum a<U+017F><U+017F>ervant Cineres po<U+017F>t fat a relictos.</l>
               <l>Ad<U+017F>cripti hîc <U+017F>uperis plus quam mortalia <U+017F>pirant,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:45449:29"/>
Deinde <U+017F>olo aequati, vulgi de more quie<U+017F>cunt.</l>
               <l>Omine faelici, dùm caetera templa ruerunt,</l>
               <l>Hoc <U+017F>tetit, ut Sceptro rabidâ de plebe triumphos</l>
               <l>Tandem promittens; <U+017F>tetit, au<U+017F>picióque <U+017F>ecundo</l>
               <l>Moles <U+017F>acra; Domo quamvis vicina, furoris</l>
               <l>Con<U+017F>cia quae Britici, civilem accendere facem</l>
               <l>Au<U+017F>a e<U+017F>t, in Patriae conver<U+017F>o vi<U+017F>cera ferro:</l>
               <l>Attamen illa <U+017F>tetit. Siculis <U+017F>ic Mulciber antris</l>
               <l>Dùm flammas ignémque vomit, cineré<U+017F>que feruntur</l>
               <l>Ad libitum Boreae, <U+017F>tat nix intacta caminis</l>
               <l>De<U+017F>uper Aetneis, <U+017F>ua lugent damna Coloni</l>
               <l>Eminùs, allap<U+017F>is <U+017F>ed parcit flamma pruinis.</l>
               <l>Non procul hinc oculos Praetoria cel<U+017F>a <U+017F>alutant</l>
               <l>Principis, Augu<U+017F>tae Themidis vi<U+017F>untur &amp; Arces,</l>
               <l>Jura ubi dat rigidis aequali lance Britannis;</l>
               <l>Arma ubi nunc ce<U+017F><U+017F>êre togae, vultú<U+017F>que <U+017F>everos</l>
               <l>Judicis exhorret timidi <U+017F>pes prona clientis.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Hîc veluti populi Pa<U+017F>tor, <U+017F>ub lumen ovile</l>
               <l>Qui tenet, &amp; tenerâ fovet hoc <U+017F>ub pectore curâ,</l>
               <l>Incedit <hi>Carolus:</hi> nullo mens <U+017F>acra laborat</l>
               <l>Ni Patris affectu, privata injuria nullo</l>
               <l>Conturbat motu <U+017F>acrae penetralia mentis.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rex pius</hi> hîc tenerae delectamenta juventae</l>
               <l>Su<U+017F>pendit, Populique vovens <U+017F>ua pen<U+017F>a <U+017F>aluti,</l>
               <l>Aulae blanditias fugat hinc, picto<U+017F>que favores,</l>
               <l>Séque u<U+017F>us <U+017F>olo ceu Con<U+017F>ultore fideli,</l>
               <l>Incedit meditans; quâ tempora cingat olivâ</l>
               <l>Re<U+017F>taurans laceras Leges, <U+017F>poliataque bello</l>
               <l>Majugenae <U+017F>tudia, aut quâ <U+017F>e fronde coronet,</l>
               <l>Clareat &amp; Lauro, po<U+017F>tquàm de Gente triumphos</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:45449:29"/>
Egerit externâ, patriá<U+017F>que refecerit arces,</l>
               <l>Tùm veterum volvens animis dictata Sophorum,</l>
               <l>Quas Fortuna vices Sceptris prae<U+017F>cribat, ut illum</l>
               <l>Erigat ex humili ceu pulvere, fulminet illum</l>
               <l>Ictu oculi, <U+017F>olidae perpendit acumine mentis:</l>
               <l>Per quas fama vigens Augu<U+017F>ti creverit artes,</l>
               <l>Quid tantùm Alcidae dederit per <U+017F>aecula nomen.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Verùm natalis moles vicina Palatî</l>
               <l>Objiciens oculis <U+017F>e <U+017F>e, majoribus implet</l>
               <l>Mentem argumentis, &amp; per <U+017F>ublimia ducit</l>
               <l>Excel<U+017F>os animos pen<U+017F>antis, qualia <hi>Sydus</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Na<U+017F>centi affulgens</hi> fecit prae<U+017F>agiaterris</l>
               <l>Attonitis, qualémque dedit <U+017F>pem Gentibus Orbis,</l>
               <l>Coelo ip<U+017F>o mon<U+017F>trante viam; <U+017F>e rumpere leges</l>
               <l>Nàm volui<U+017F><U+017F>e <U+017F>uas, lucique apta<U+017F><U+017F>e tenebras,</l>
               <l>Signarent <hi>Pueri</hi> ut cunas miracula <hi>Magni</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Vix dùm vi<U+017F>a priùs: cui tàm diver<U+017F>a reful<U+017F>it</l>
               <l>Lux na<U+017F>centi, Orbem <U+017F>acro ut <U+017F>ub foedere totum</l>
               <l>Sit natus junxi<U+017F><U+017F>e <U+017F>imul, Paci<U+017F>que jacentes</l>
               <l>Erigere, Et fe<U+017F>tis circumdare floribus aras:</l>
               <l>Nèc <U+017F>pes vana animum aut illudens fata fovebit,</l>
               <l>Quicquid enim coelum promi<U+017F>it, <U+017F>ydera quicquid</l>
               <l>Praedixêre, bonis tandem <U+017F>ucce<U+017F><U+017F>ibus haec Te</l>
               <l>Regnante evenient, &amp; <U+017F>aecula no<U+017F>tra beabunt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Collap<U+017F>ae ac veteres Gentis <U+017F>arcire ruinas,</l>
               <l>Artibus &amp; variis dùm condere <U+017F>edulus urges,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rex Pie,</hi> Tu <hi>Patriae</hi> meliori Nomine <hi>Cultor</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Dicêris, quàm quòd repara<U+017F>ti hoc nobile Septum.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:45449:30"/>
            <head>OF THE Late WAR WITH SPAINE And our VICTORY at SEA, NEAR S. LUGAR.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>NOw for <U+017F>ome ages had the Pride of <hi>Spain,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Made the Sun <U+017F>hine on half the world in vain,</l>
               <l>Whil<U+017F>t <U+017F>he bid War to all that dur<U+017F>t <U+017F>upply</l>
               <l>The place of tho<U+017F>e her cruelty made dye:</l>
               <l>Of Natures bounty men forbore to ta<U+017F>t,</l>
               <l>And the be<U+017F>t portion of the Earth lay wa<U+017F>t.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:45449:30"/>
From the new world her <U+017F>ilver and her gold,</l>
               <l>Came like a tempe<U+017F>t to confound the old;</l>
               <l>With the<U+017F>e accompli<U+017F>hing her va<U+017F>t de<U+017F>igns,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Europe</hi> was <U+017F>haken with her <hi>Indian</hi> mines.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When <hi>Britain</hi> looking with a ju<U+017F>t di<U+017F>dain,</l>
               <l>Upon his guilded Maje<U+017F>ty of <hi>Spain,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And knowing well that Empire mu<U+017F>t decline,</l>
               <l>Who<U+017F>e chief <U+017F>upport and <U+017F>inews are of coin,</l>
               <l>Her native force and virtue did oppo<U+017F>e</l>
               <l>To the rich troublers of the Worlds repo<U+017F>e.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And now <U+017F>ome months encamping on the main,</l>
               <l>Our naval Army had be<U+017F>ieged <hi>Spain,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>They that the whole Worlds Monarchy de<U+017F>ign'd</l>
               <l>Are to their ports by our bold Fleet confin'd,</l>
               <l>From whence our Red-cro<U+017F><U+017F>e they Triumphant <U+017F>ee,</l>
               <l>Riding without a rival on the Sea:</l>
               <l>Others may u<U+017F>e the Ocean as their road;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi> only make it their abode:</l>
               <l>Our Oaks <U+017F>ecure as if they there took root;</l>
               <l>We tread on billows with a <U+017F>teady foot.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Mean while the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in <hi>America,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Near to the line the Sun approaching <U+017F>aw:</l>
               <l>And hop'd their <hi>European</hi> Coa<U+017F>ts to find</l>
               <l>Clear'd from our <U+017F>hips by the <hi>Autumnal</hi> Wind:</l>
               <l>Their huge capacious <hi>Gallions</hi> <U+017F>tuft with plate,</l>
               <l>The labouring Winds drive <U+017F>lowly towards their fate:</l>
               <l>Before St. <hi>Lugar</hi> they their guns di<U+017F>charge</l>
               <l>To tell their joy or to call fotth a Barge:</l>
               <l>This heard, <U+017F>ome <U+017F>hips of ours, though out of view,</l>
               <l>As <U+017F>wift as Eagles to the quarrey flew:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:45449:31"/>
So heedle<U+017F><U+017F>e Lambs which for their mothers bleat</l>
               <l>Wake hungry Lyons and become their meat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Arriv'd, they <U+017F>oon begin that tragick play,</l>
               <l>And with their <U+017F>moaky Cannon bani<U+017F>h day;</l>
               <l>Night, horrour, <U+017F>laughter with confu<U+017F>ion meets,</l>
               <l>And in their <U+017F>able armes imbrace the Fleets;</l>
               <l>Through yielding planks the angry bullets flie,</l>
               <l>And of one wound hundreds together die,</l>
               <l>Born under different <U+017F>tars one Fate they have,</l>
               <l>The <U+017F>hip their Coffin, and the Sea their grave.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Bold were the men who on the Ocean fir<U+017F>t</l>
               <l>Spread their new <U+017F>ailes when <U+017F>hipwrack was the wor<U+017F>t</l>
               <l>More danger now from man alone we find</l>
               <l>Then from the rocks, the billows or the wind;</l>
               <l>They that had <U+017F>ayl'd from near th' Antartique pole,</l>
               <l>Their Trea<U+017F>ure <U+017F>afe and all their ve<U+017F><U+017F>els whole,</l>
               <l>In <U+017F>ight of their dear countrey ruin'd be,</l>
               <l>Without the guilt of either rock or Sea;</l>
               <l>What they would <U+017F>pare our fiercer Art de<U+017F>troys,</l>
               <l>Surpa<U+017F><U+017F>ing <U+017F>torms in terrour and in noi<U+017F>e:</l>
               <l>Once <hi>Jove</hi> from <hi>Ida</hi> did both Ho<U+017F>ts <U+017F>urvey,</l>
               <l>And when he pleas'd to Thunder part the frey;</l>
               <l>Heaven here in vain that kind retreat <U+017F>hould <U+017F>ound,</l>
               <l>The louder Canon had the thunder drown'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some we made prize, while others burnt and rent</l>
               <l>With their rich lading to the bottom went,</l>
               <l>Down <U+017F>inks at once, <U+017F>o fortune with us <U+017F>ports,</l>
               <l>The pay of Armies and the pride of Courts.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Vain man! who<U+017F>e rage buries as low that <U+017F>tore,</l>
               <l>As avarice had digg'd for it before!</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:45449:31"/>
What earth in her dark bowels could not keep</l>
               <l>From greedy hands, lies <U+017F>afer in the deep;</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Thetis</hi> kindly does from mortals hide</l>
               <l>Tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>eeds of luxu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, debate and pride:</l>
               <l>And now into her lap the riche<U+017F>t prize</l>
               <l>Fell with the noble<U+017F>t of our enemies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Marquis glad<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> to <U+017F>ee the fire de<U+017F>troy</l>
               <l>Wealth that prevailing foes were to enjoy:</l>
               <l>Out from his flaming <U+017F>hip his children <U+017F>ent</l>
               <l>To peri<U+017F>h in a milder element:</l>
               <l>Then laid him by his burning Ladies <U+017F>ide,</l>
               <l>And <U+017F>ince he could not <U+017F>ave her, with her dy'd:</l>
               <l>Spices and Gums about them melting fry,</l>
               <l>And Phoenix like in that rich ne<U+017F>t they die;</l>
               <l>Alive in flames of equal love they burn'd,</l>
               <l>And now together are to a<U+017F>hes turn'd</l>
               <l>A<U+017F>hes, more worth then all their funeral co<U+017F>t,</l>
               <l>Then the huge trea<U+017F>ure which was with them lo<U+017F>t.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The<U+017F>e dying Lovers and their floting Sons</l>
               <l>Su<U+017F>pend the Fight and <U+017F>ilence all our Guns.</l>
               <l>Beauty and youth about to peri<U+017F>h finds</l>
               <l>Such noble pity in brave Engli<U+017F>h minds,</l>
               <l>That the rich Spoil neglecting and the prize</l>
               <l>All labour now to <U+017F>ave our enemies.</l>
               <l>How frail our pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions! how <U+017F>oon changed are</l>
               <l>Our wrath and fury to a friendly care!</l>
               <l>They that but now to gain the Spani<U+017F>h plate</l>
               <l>Made the Sea blu<U+017F>h with blood, forget their hate,</l>
               <l>And their young foes while <U+017F>inking they retrive,</l>
               <l>With greater danger then they fought they dive.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:45449:32"/>
            <head>SUR La Victoire NAVALE Obtenue devant Cadis SUR L'E<U+017F>pagnol.
M.DC.LVII.</head>
            <byline>Traduit de l'Anglois de Mr. WALLER.</byline>
            <lg>
               <l>DE<U+017F>ia long temps l'orgueuil du Ca<U+017F>tillan avare,</l>
               <l>Avoit fait luire en vain <U+017F>ur ce terroir barbare</l>
               <l>Dont la Va<U+017F>te grandeur partage l' Univers,</l>
               <l>Les rayons du Soleil: long temps <U+017F>ur les deux mers</l>
               <l>Q'uil voit en <U+017F>e couchant du lieu de <U+017F>a nai<U+017F><U+017F>ance,</l>
               <l>Maint Galion avoit publié <U+017F>a pui<U+017F><U+017F>ance;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:45449:32"/>
Et l'in<U+017F>olent pouvoir de <U+017F>es commandemens;</l>
               <l>Qui privant du plus vil de tous les elemens,</l>
               <l>Ses iu<U+017F>tes po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>eurs, par une inju<U+017F>teguerre,</l>
               <l>En defendoit l'accés au re<U+017F>te de la Terre:</l>
               <l>Traittant comme un objet digne d'ho<U+017F>tilité,</l>
               <l>Quiconque s'oppo<U+017F>ant contre <U+017F>a cruauté</l>
               <l>Tentoit de reparer les bréches &amp; linjure,</l>
               <l>Que <U+017F>es meurtres fai<U+017F>oient aux loix de la Nature.</l>
               <l>Ses beaux fruits langui<U+017F><U+017F>ans, par ce jaloux de<U+017F><U+017F>ein</l>
               <l>Pourri<U+017F><U+017F>oient <U+017F>ans honneur dans <U+017F>on fertile <U+017F>ein;</l>
               <l>Et <U+017F>a main pour neant <U+017F>e montroit liberale,</l>
               <l>Des faveurs que le Ciel <U+017F>ous ces climats étalle.</l>
               <l>Ces dangerenx metaux, dont le fatal poi<U+017F>on</l>
               <l>En<U+017F>orcelle no<U+017F>tre ame &amp; ble<U+017F><U+017F>e la rai<U+017F>on,</l>
               <l>Ain<U+017F>y qu' une tempe<U+017F>te à la faveur del'onde</l>
               <l>Venoient de ce Nouveau fondre <U+017F>ur le vieil Monde,</l>
               <l>Pour troubler <U+017F>on repos; ces Princes ba<U+017F>anés</l>
               <l>Tenans des Electeurs les esprits enchainés</l>
               <l>Par des liens dorés, s'e<U+017F>toient rendus arbitres</l>
               <l>De l' Empire &amp; de Rome, &amp; di<U+017F>pen<U+017F>oient <U+017F>es titres</l>
               <l>Au gré de leur faveur, Leurs inju<U+017F>tes projets</l>
               <l>De l' Europe ébranlée attri<U+017F>toyent les <U+017F>ujets,</l>
               <l>Voians en eette main les Clefs du Capitole,</l>
               <l>Et L' Aigle des Ce<U+017F>ars trembler à leur parolle;</l>
               <l>Quand le Lion Anglois, plein d'indignation</l>
               <l>Contre le faux elcat de cette Nation</l>
               <l>Dont l'or fait la grandeur, jugea mal a<U+017F><U+017F>eurée,</l>
               <l>La Maje<U+017F>té qui croid établir <U+017F>a durée</l>
               <l>Sur le lu<U+017F>tre incertain de ce trompeur metal.</l>
               <l>Il oppo<U+017F>e au<U+017F><U+017F>i to<U+017F>t du <U+017F>oldat de <hi>Whitall</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:45449:33"/>
La <U+017F>olide valeur à vaincre accoutumée,</l>
               <l>Aux pompeux appareils de ce Roy de fumée:</l>
               <l>De<U+017F>ia les escadrons de nos fameux Vai<U+017F><U+017F>eaux</l>
               <l>Aians planté leur Camp dans le milieu des eaux,</l>
               <l>Ont a<U+017F><U+017F>iegé l'E<U+017F>pagne, et borné de leur onde</l>
               <l>Ces zelés a<U+017F><U+017F>erteurs de l'empire du Monde;</l>
               <l>Leurs navires gelés au milieu de leurs ports,</l>
               <l>Nont pour nous re<U+017F>i<U+017F>ter que de foibles efforts.</l>
               <l>Ils contemplent de loin nos mignons de Neptune,</l>
               <l>Dont la ma<U+017F>le valeur enchaine la Fortune,</l>
               <l>Po<U+017F><U+017F>eder <U+017F>ans rival les humides <U+017F>eillons,</l>
               <l>Et les faire trembler de<U+017F><U+017F>ous leurs Paveillons.</l>
               <l>D'autres <U+017F>ur l'Ocean peuvent avoir l'audace</l>
               <l>De rader, quand <U+017F>oudain Aeole les menace;</l>
               <l>L'Anglois o<U+017F>e luy <U+017F>eul y faire <U+017F>a mai<U+017F>on,</l>
               <l>L'habiter en tous vents et en toute <U+017F>ai<U+017F>on;</l>
               <l>Contre tous accidens il <U+017F>cait regir <U+017F>es voiles,</l>
               <l>Comme s'il avoit fait ligue avec les étoilles.</l>
               <l>Ses Fregates <U+017F>ur mer paroi<U+017F><U+017F>ans comme un bois</l>
               <l>Semblent y croitre encor une <U+017F>econde fois,</l>
               <l>Et comme offrir aux pieds la fermeté des villes</l>
               <l>Contre le choc des flots, en cha<U+017F>teaux immobiles.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Cependant l'E<U+017F>pagnol voiant le Dieu du jour</l>
               <l>Ses ombres raccourcir, medite <U+017F>on retour</l>
               <l>Vers <U+017F>a terre natale, e<U+017F>perant que l'Autône</l>
               <l>Qui de vents orageux cette co<U+017F>te environne,</l>
               <l>Auroit ouvert <U+017F>es ports cha<U+017F><U+017F>ant nos matelots,</l>
               <l>Qu'il craint plus mille fois que la fureur des flots,</l>
               <l>Le vent pou<U+017F><U+017F>e a regret (pre<U+017F>ageant leur fortune)</l>
               <l>Leurs p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap><U+017F>ans Galions <U+017F>ur le dos de Neptune,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:45449:33"/>
Qui trainent lentement ces lourds &amp; va<U+017F>tes corps,</l>
               <l>Ou l'Inde à renfermé pre<U+017F>que tous <U+017F>es tre<U+017F>ors.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Dés que Cadis parut, <U+017F>oit en <U+017F>igne de joye</l>
               <l>Ou bien pour advertir que du port on envoye</l>
               <l>Des alleges à bord, ils font retentir l'air</l>
               <l>D'un coup de leur canon, plus vi<U+017F>te que l'éclair,</l>
               <l>Echò le porte au loin, <U+017F>oudain de nos Ecoutes</l>
               <l>La plus prompte à ce bruit fend les humides routes</l>
               <l>Au<U+017F><U+017F>i legerement comme l'Aigle affamé</l>
               <l>Quand il double <U+017F>on vol, vers la proye animé.</l>
               <l>Des autres au<U+017F><U+017F>i to<U+017F>t la valeur <U+017F>e reveille,</l>
               <l>Le <U+017F>oldat plein d'e<U+017F>poir au combat s'appareille,</l>
               <l>Et pre<U+017F>qu'en un moment l'ombre de nos vai<U+017F><U+017F>eaux</l>
               <l>Au Ca<U+017F>tillan tremblant o<U+017F>te l'a<U+017F>pect des eaux;</l>
               <l>Ain<U+017F>y le <U+017F>imple agneau dedans <U+017F>a bergerie,</l>
               <l>Du Lion endormi réveille la furie,</l>
               <l>Beelant apres <U+017F>a mere, &amp; <U+017F>ert d'addre<U+017F><U+017F>e aux pas</l>
               <l>Du mon<U+017F>tre dont enfin il devient le repas.</l>
               <l>A l'abord leur canon d'un tragique carnage</l>
               <l>Commence le prelude, &amp; d'un ob<U+017F>cur nuage</l>
               <l>Enveloppe le jour, dont l'air <U+017F>emble attri<U+017F>té</l>
               <l>Refu<U+017F>er <U+017F>a lumiere à tant de cruauté:</l>
               <l>La nuit, l'horreur, la mort retrace de<U+017F><U+017F>us l'onde</l>
               <l>L'image du Chaos en lenfance du Monde,</l>
               <l>Et la Parque au timon de ces Châteaux mouvans</l>
               <l>Se pourmeine en triomphe à la faveur des Vents,</l>
               <l>Animant les partis, &amp; de <U+017F>es mains <U+017F>anglantes</l>
               <l>Les fait joindre en depit des vagues incon<U+017F>tantes:</l>
               <l>Maint boulet irrité <U+017F>e plonge dans le flanc</l>
               <l>Des navires bri<U+017F>és, &amp; fait pa<U+017F><U+017F>age au<U+017F>ang<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:45449:34"/>
Du <U+017F>oldat demembré, dont en foulle les ombres</l>
               <l>A chaque coup tiré pa<U+017F><U+017F>ent aux rives <U+017F>ombres.</l>
               <l>L àvoit on expirer <U+017F>ous un me<U+017F>me De<U+017F>tin,</l>
               <l>Ceux qu'un divers a<U+017F>pect divi<U+017F>oit en leur fin,</l>
               <l>Et pour les receuillir au <U+017F>ein de la Nature</l>
               <l>La nef fait leur cerceuil, l'onde leur <U+017F>epulture.</l>
               <l>Hardy fut le mortel, qui tenta des premiers</l>
               <l>D'abandonner <U+017F>a vie à l'art des Nautonniers!</l>
               <l>Quand leur danger n'alloit au delà du naufrage.</l>
               <l>Maintenant il doit plus craindre <U+017F>a propre rage,</l>
               <l>Que celle des éceuils ny des fiers Aquilons</l>
               <l>Quand ils ont irrité les humides <U+017F>eillons.</l>
               <l>Ces gens qui du climat où l'onde baigne l'Our<U+017F>e</l>
               <l>Avoyent heureusement presque achevé leur cour<U+017F>e,</l>
               <l>Et rapportoient chés eux les tre<U+017F>ors d'Occident,</l>
               <l>Sans avoir rencontré nul fa<U+017F>cheux accident,</l>
               <l>Viennent dedans le port faire un tri<U+017F>te naufrage,</l>
               <l>Dont on ne peut blamer ny les Vents ny l'orage;</l>
               <l>Ce qu'ils avoient <U+017F>auvé dela fureur des flots</l>
               <l>Tombe de<U+017F><U+017F>ous la main de nos fiers matelots,</l>
               <l>Qui dans l'art de detruire excellent les tempe<U+017F>tes</l>
               <l>Que le Ciel auroit peu ver<U+017F>er de<U+017F><U+017F>us leurs te<U+017F>tes.</l>
               <l>Jadis du haut d' Ida Iupiter regardant</l>
               <l>Les deux Camps ennemis, &amp; <U+017F>a foudre dardant,</l>
               <l>Calmoit à <U+017F>on plai<U+017F>ir les debats de leur guerre.</l>
               <l>Icy <U+017F>on bras en vain eu<U+017F>t lancé le tonnerre,</l>
               <l>Le canon <U+017F>ans re<U+017F>pect en eu<U+017F>t noyé la voix,</l>
               <l>Et deffendu d'oüir cet Heraut de <U+017F>es loix.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Le <U+017F>uccés du combat different en fortune,</l>
               <l>Partagea le butin entre nous &amp; Neptune.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:45449:34"/>
Ce qu'il prend s' abi<U+017F>mant promptement <U+017F>ous les eaux</l>
               <l>Semble en cor avoir peur du choc de nos vai<U+017F><U+017F>eaux.</l>
               <l>Ain<U+017F>y de nos grandeurs la Fortune <U+017F>e joue,</l>
               <l>Et change nos de<U+017F><U+017F>eins au plai<U+017F>ir de <U+017F>a Roüe:</l>
               <l>Ain<U+017F>y voit on perir dans ces <U+017F>tottantes tours,</l>
               <l>La Paye du <U+017F>oldat, et la pompe des Cours.</l>
               <l>Vain mortel! dont l' humeur incon<U+017F>tante et peu <U+017F>age</l>
               <l>Abi<U+017F>me rechef en <U+017F>a boüillante rage</l>
               <l>Ce metal, que Nature enfermoit à de<U+017F><U+017F>ein</l>
               <l>De l'o<U+017F>ter à nos yeux, au plus creux de <U+017F>on <U+017F>ein;</l>
               <l>Prevoiant qu'il <U+017F>eroit quelque jour le Supplice</l>
               <l>De ton ingenieu<U+017F>e et hardie avarice!</l>
               <l>Ce que la terre en vain celoit dans <U+017F>es caehots</l>
               <l>Aux mortels affamés, e<U+017F>t englouti des flots;</l>
               <l>Qui plus officieux derobent à la veüe</l>
               <l>Ce dangereux poi<U+017F>on par qui l'ame <U+017F>e tue:</l>
               <l>Ces <U+017F>emences d'orgueuil, de luxe, ambition,</l>
               <l>La pe<U+017F>te des Etats et la confu<U+017F>ion.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Mais l'onde enfin recoit dedans <U+017F>on <U+017F>ein avare,</l>
               <l>Entre tout ce butin le butin le plus rare,</l>
               <l>Un Marquis qui voiant le feu mis à <U+017F>on bord,</l>
               <l>Semble ai<U+017F>e de trouver ce chemin à la mort.</l>
               <l>Soit qu'il la creu<U+017F>t plus douce, ou tint à plus de gloire</l>
               <l>De priver l'ennemy du fruit de <U+017F>a Victoire.</l>
               <l>Lai<U+017F><U+017F>ant à la mercy d'un plus doux element,</l>
               <l>Ses Enfans retirés de <U+017F>on embra<U+017F>ement.</l>
               <l>Luy touché pour leur <U+017F>ort de <U+017F>entimens plus tendres</l>
               <l>Neglige le <U+017F>ien propre, et <U+017F>e re<U+017F>erve aux cendres</l>
               <l>De <U+017F>a chere moitie, veut mourir l'embra<U+017F><U+017F>ant</l>
               <l>Puis qu'à la <U+017F>ecourir il <U+017F>e trouve impui<U+017F><U+017F>ant.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:45449:35"/>
Et comme le Phoenix, quand il e<U+017F>t la<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> du monde,</l>
               <l>Repare <U+017F>on de<U+017F>tin <U+017F>ur <U+017F>a cendre feconde</l>
               <l>Dans un lict de parfums; tels de ces deux Amans</l>
               <l>Avant que d'expirer <U+017F>ont les embra<U+017F><U+017F>ements.</l>
               <l>Tout ce qu'ont d'odorant, les Jardins de l'Aurore,</l>
               <l>Tous ce qu'a le terroir de l'un et l'autre More</l>
               <l>De plus riches <U+017F>enteurs, comme un autel fumant</l>
               <l>S'exhale avec leurs corps, les flammes embaumant.</l>
               <l>La Mort à plus de fiel, et <U+017F>emble plus barbare,</l>
               <l>Quand des objets aimés <U+017F>a rigueur nous <U+017F>epare;</l>
               <l>Mais elle perd ce titre, alors qu'avecques nous</l>
               <l>Elle enferme au tombeau ce qui nous fut plus doux.</l>
               <l>Que fait elle au Marquis? tenoit il plus qu'a vie</l>
               <l>Son or, et la Beauté qu'elle luy à ravie?</l>
               <l>Leur caeur de leur vivant bru<U+017F>la de mesmes feux:</l>
               <l>Elle ne fait qu'un corps de la cendre des deux;</l>
               <l>Cendres, de plus haut prix qu'aucune Sepul<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ure,</l>
               <l>Qu'auroit peu lure donner ou lart ou la Nature;</l>
               <l>Que tout ce que les feux ou l'onde ont con<U+017F>umé,</l>
               <l>De tant de grands tre<U+017F>ors! Mau<U+017F>olée abismé!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ce prodige d'Amour, la famille flottante</l>
               <l>De ce couple expirant, calme et tient en attente</l>
               <l>Les E<U+017F>prits <U+017F>u<U+017F>pendus de nos fiers combattans,</l>
               <l>Puis impo<U+017F>e <U+017F>ilence aux canons eclattans.</l>
               <l>Tant à de la beauté le charme d'advantage,</l>
               <l>Quand elle e<U+017F>t en danger, pour flechir le courage</l>
               <l>Du genereux Anglois, dont la masle vertu</l>
               <l>Pardonne à l'ennemy <U+017F>ous <U+017F>es pieds abbatu.</l>
               <l>Et mépri<U+017F>ant le gain d'une avare victoire,</l>
               <l>Au <U+017F>alut des vaincus fait con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ter <U+017F>a gloire.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:45449:35"/>
Que des nos pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions l'e<U+017F>tat e<U+017F>t peu con<U+017F>tant,</l>
               <l>Que nôtre e<U+017F>prit tou<U+017F>iours en <U+017F>oy me<U+017F>me flottant</l>
               <l>Ayme le changement! et que dans nos pen<U+017F>ées;</l>
               <l>Les images qu'il peint <U+017F>ont bien to<U+017F>t effacées!</l>
               <l>La haine et l'Amitié <U+017F>e <U+017F>uivent pas à pas;</l>
               <l>Ceux qui tanto<U+017F>t portoient l'horreur et le trepas</l>
               <l>Dans leurs <U+017F>anglantes mains, de <U+017F>entimens plus calmes</l>
               <l>Maintenant animés, par de plus nobles palmes</l>
               <l>Que celles du butin <U+017F>e veullent couronner;</l>
               <l>Aimans mieux les tre<U+017F>ors de l' Inde abandonner</l>
               <l>A la mercy des flots, que de ternir le lu<U+017F>tre</l>
               <l>Par un acte cruel de leur Victoire illu<U+017F>tre.</l>
               <l>Voyans ces expo<U+017F>és dans l'extreme danger,</l>
               <l>Ces re<U+017F>tes du Marquis <U+017F>ur les ondes nager,</l>
               <l>Ils <U+017F>e jettent apres au mépris de leur vie,</l>
               <l>Pour <U+017F>uivre le chemin où l'honneur les convie</l>
               <l>Ioint avec la pitié, l'honneur de qui le prix</l>
               <l>E<U+017F>t le plus grand loyer des genereux e<U+017F>prits.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ain<U+017F>y de nos <U+017F>oldats la valeur <U+017F>e contente</l>
               <l>De <U+017F>auver du Marquis la famille flottante,</l>
               <l>Avec plus de danger qu'ils navoient combatu,</l>
               <l>Preferans au butin l'honneur et la vertu.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FIN.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:45449:36"/>
            <head>TO HIS SACRED MAIESTY, A Panegyrick ON HIS CORONATION.</head>
            <byline>By J. DREYDEN.</byline>
            <lg>
               <l>IN that wild Deluge where the World was drownd,</l>
               <l>When life and <U+017F>in one common tombe had found,</l>
               <l>The fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>mall pro<U+017F>pect of a ri<U+017F>ing hill</l>
               <l>With various notes of Joy the Ark did fill:</l>
               <l>Yet when that flood in its own depths was drown'd</l>
               <l>It left behind it fal<U+017F>e and <U+017F>lipp'ry ground;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:45449:36"/>
And the more <U+017F>olemn pomp was <U+017F>till deferr'd</l>
               <l>Till new-born Nature in fre<U+017F>h looks appear'd:</l>
               <l>Thus (Royal Sir) to <U+017F>ee you landed here</l>
               <l>Was cau<U+017F>e enough of triumph for a year:</l>
               <l>Nor would your care tho<U+017F>e glorious Joys repeat</l>
               <l>Till they at once might be <U+017F>ecure and great:</l>
               <l>Till your kind beams by their continu'd <U+017F>tay</l>
               <l>Had warm'd the ground, and call'd the Damps away<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
               </l>
               <l>Such vapours while your pow'rful influence drys</l>
               <l>Then <U+017F>oone<U+017F>t vani<U+017F>h when they highe<U+017F>t ri<U+017F>e.</l>
               <l>Had greater ha<U+017F>t the<U+017F>e <U+017F>acred rights prepar'd,</l>
               <l>Some guilty Moneth; had in your triumphs <U+017F>har'd:</l>
               <l>But this untainted year is all your own,</l>
               <l>Your glory's may without our crimes be <U+017F>hown.</l>
               <l>We had not yet exhau<U+017F>ted all our <U+017F>tore</l>
               <l>When you refre<U+017F>h'd our joy's by adding more:</l>
               <l>As Heav'n of old di<U+017F>penc'd Caele<U+017F>tial dew,</l>
               <l>You give us Manna and <U+017F>till give us new.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now our <U+017F>ad ruines are remov'd from <U+017F>ight,</l>
               <l>The Sea<U+017F>on too comes fraught with new delight;</l>
               <l>Time <U+017F>eems not now beneath his years to <U+017F>toop</l>
               <l>Nor do his wings with <U+017F>ickly feathers droop:</l>
               <l>Soft we<U+017F>tern winds waft ore the gaudy Spring,</l>
               <l>And opened Scenes of flow'rs and blo<U+017F><U+017F>oms bring</l>
               <l>To grace this happy day, while you appear</l>
               <l>Not only King of us but of the year.</l>
               <l>All eyes you draw, and with the eyes the heart,</l>
               <l>Of your own pomp your <U+017F>elf the greate<U+017F>t part:</l>
               <l>Loud <U+017F>houts the Nations happine<U+017F>s proclaim</l>
               <l>And Heav'n this day is fea<U+017F>ted with your name.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:45449:37"/>
Your Cavalcade the fair Spectators view</l>
               <l>From their high <U+017F>tandings, yet look up to you.</l>
               <l>From your brave train each <U+017F>ingles out a prey,</l>
               <l>And longs to date a Conque<U+017F>t from your day.</l>
               <l>Now charg'd with ble<U+017F><U+017F>ings while you <U+017F>eek repo<U+017F>e,</l>
               <l>Officious <U+017F>lumbers ha<U+017F>t your eyes to clo<U+017F>e:</l>
               <l>And glorious dreams <U+017F>tand ready to re<U+017F>tore</l>
               <l>The plea<U+017F>ing <U+017F>hapes of all you <U+017F>aw before.</l>
               <l>Next to the <U+017F>acred Temple you are led,</l>
               <l>Where waites a Crown for your more <U+017F>acred Head:</l>
               <l>How ju<U+017F>tly from the Church that Crown is due,</l>
               <l>Pre<U+017F>erv'd from ruin and re<U+017F>tor'd by you!</l>
               <l>The grateful quire their harmony employ</l>
               <l>Not to make greater but more <U+017F>olemn joy.</l>
               <l>Wrapt <U+017F>oft and warm your Name is <U+017F>ent on high,</l>
               <l>As flames do on the wings of Incen<U+017F>e fly:</l>
               <l>Mu<U+017F>ique her <U+017F>elf is lo<U+017F>t, in vain <U+017F>he brings</l>
               <l>Her choi<U+017F>e<U+017F>t notes to prai<U+017F>e the be<U+017F>t of Kings:</l>
               <l>Her melting <U+017F>trains in you a tombe have found,</l>
               <l>And lye like Bees in their own <U+017F>weetne<U+017F>s drown'd.</l>
               <l>He that brought peace and di<U+017F>cord could attone,</l>
               <l>His Name is Mu<U+017F>ick of it <U+017F>elf alone.</l>
               <l>Now while the <U+017F>acred Oyl anoints your head,</l>
               <l>And fragrant <U+017F>ents, begun from you, are <U+017F>pread</l>
               <l>Through the large Dome, the peoples joyful <U+017F>ound</l>
               <l>Sent back, is <U+017F>till pre<U+017F>erv'd in hallow'd ground:</l>
               <l>Which in one ble<U+017F><U+017F>ing mixt de<U+017F>cends on you,</l>
               <l>As heightned <U+017F>pirits fall in richer dew.</l>
               <l>Not that our wi<U+017F>hes do increa<U+017F>e your <U+017F>tore,</l>
               <l>Full of your <U+017F>elf you can admit no more:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:45449:37"/>
We add not to your glory, but employ</l>
               <l>Our time like Angels in expre<U+017F><U+017F>ing joy.</l>
               <l>Nor is it duty or our hopes alone</l>
               <l>Create that joy, but full fruition;</l>
               <l>We know tho<U+017F>e ble<U+017F><U+017F>ings which we mu<U+017F>t po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s,</l>
               <l>And judge of future by pa<U+017F>t happine<U+017F>s.</l>
               <l>No promi<U+017F>e can oblige a Prince <U+017F>o much</l>
               <l>Still to be good as long to have been <U+017F>uch.</l>
               <l>A noble Emulation heats your brea<U+017F>t,</l>
               <l>Ang your own fame now robbs you of your re<U+017F>t:</l>
               <l>Good actions <U+017F>till mu<U+017F>t be maintain'd with good,</l>
               <l>As bodies nouri<U+017F>h'd with re<U+017F>embling food.</l>
               <l>You have already quench'd <U+017F>editions brand;</l>
               <l>And zeal (which burnt it) only warms the Land.</l>
               <l>The jealous Sects that dare not tru<U+017F>t their cau<U+017F>e</l>
               <l>So farre from their own will as to the Laws,</l>
               <l>You for their Umpire and their Synod take,</l>
               <l>And their appeal alone to <hi>Cae<U+017F>ar</hi> make.</l>
               <l>Kind Heav'n <U+017F>o rare a temper did provide</l>
               <l>That guilt repenting might in it confide.</l>
               <l>Among our crimes oblivion may be <U+017F>et,</l>
               <l>But 'tis our Kings perfection to forget.</l>
               <l>Virtues unknown to the<U+017F>e rough Northern climes</l>
               <l>From milder heav'ns you bring, without their crimes<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
               </l>
               <l>Your calmne<U+017F><U+017F>e does no after <U+017F>torms provide,</l>
               <l>Nor <U+017F>eeming patience mortal anger hide.</l>
               <l>When Empire fir<U+017F>t from families did <U+017F>pring,</l>
               <l>Then every Father govern'd as a King;</l>
               <l>But you that are a Soveraign Prince, allay</l>
               <l>Imperial pow'r with your paternal <U+017F>way.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:45449:38"/>
From tho<U+017F>e great cares when ea<U+017F>e your <U+017F>oul unbends</l>
               <l>Your plea<U+017F>ures are de<U+017F>ign'd to noble ends:</l>
               <l>Born to command the Mi<U+017F>tre<U+017F>s of the Seas,</l>
               <l>Your thoughts them<U+017F>elves in that blue Empire plea<U+017F>e.</l>
               <l>Hither in Summer ev'nings you repair</l>
               <l>To take the frai<U+017F>cheur of the purer air:</l>
               <l>Undanted here you ride when Winter raves,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Cae<U+017F>ars</hi> heart that ro<U+017F>e above the waves.</l>
               <l>More I could <U+017F>ing but fear my Numbers <U+017F>tayes;</l>
               <l>No Loyal Subject dares that courage prai<U+017F>e.</l>
               <l>In <U+017F>tately Frigats mo<U+017F>t delight you find,</l>
               <l>Where well-drawn Battels fire your martial mind.</l>
               <l>What to your cares we owe is learnt from hence,</l>
               <l>When ev'n your plea<U+017F>ures <U+017F>erve for our defence.</l>
               <l>Beyond your Court flows in th'admitted tide,</l>
               <l>Where in new depths the wondring fi<U+017F>hes glide:</l>
               <l>Here in a Royal bed the waters <U+017F>leep,</l>
               <l>When tir'd at Sea within this bay they creep.</l>
               <l>Here the mi<U+017F>tru<U+017F>tful foul no harm <U+017F>u<U+017F>pects,</l>
               <l>So <U+017F>afe are all things which our King protects.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From your lov'd <hi>Thames</hi> a ble<U+017F><U+017F>ing yet is due,</l>
               <l>Second alone to that it brought in you;</l>
               <l>A Queen, from who<U+017F>e cha<U+017F>t womb, ordain'd by Fate,</l>
               <l>The <U+017F>ouls of Kings unborn for bodies wait.</l>
               <l>It was your Love before made di<U+017F>cord cea<U+017F>e:</l>
               <l>Your Love is de<U+017F>tin'd to your Countries peace.</l>
               <l>Both <hi>Indies</hi> (Rivalls in your bed) provide</l>
               <l>With Gold or Jewells to adorn your Bride.</l>
               <l>This to a mighty King pre<U+017F>ents rich ore,</l>
               <l>While that with Incen<U+017F>e does a God implore.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:45449:38"/>
Two Kingdoms wait your doom, and as you choo<U+017F>e,</l>
               <l>This mu<U+017F>t receive a Crown, or that mu<U+017F>t loo<U+017F>e.</l>
               <l>Thus from your Royal Oke, like <hi>Joves</hi> of old,</l>
               <l>Are an<U+017F>wers <U+017F>ought, and de<U+017F>tinies fore-told:</l>
               <l>Propitious Oracles are begg'd with vows,</l>
               <l>And Crowns that grow upon the <U+017F>acred boughs.</l>
               <l>Your Subjects, while you weigh the Nations fate,</l>
               <l>Su<U+017F>pend to both their doubtful love or hate<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
               </l>
               <l>Choo<U+017F>e only, (Sir,) that <U+017F>o they may po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s</l>
               <l>With their own peace their Childrens happine<U+017F>s.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:45449:39"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Panegyrique DU</hi> SERENISSIME ROY <hi>CHARLES II.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>Au <U+017F>uiet de <U+017F>on Couronnement.
M.DC.LXI.</head>
            <byline>Traduit de L'Anglois de Mr. DREYDEN.</byline>
            <lg>
               <l>QUand la fureur des eaux noyant le premier Monde,</l>
               <l>Etouff a le pecheur et le peché dans l'onde,</l>
               <l>Le moindre et foible a<U+017F>pect du plus proche co<U+017F>teau</l>
               <l>Sortant hors de l'abys me, au langui<U+017F><U+017F>ant Vai<U+017F><U+017F>eau</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:45449:39"/>
Fit renaitre au<U+017F><U+017F>i to<U+017F>t l'e<U+017F>perance et la joye:</l>
               <l>Mais lors que <U+017F>on reflus eut retrouvé la voye</l>
               <l>De <U+017F>es premiers Cachots, par degrés s' abbai<U+017F><U+017F>ant</l>
               <l>Le terroir demeura peu certain et gli<U+017F><U+017F>ant;</l>
               <l>Et toute la beauté qui fait cette <U+017F>tructure</l>
               <l>Differa d'éclatter, tant qu'on vi<U+017F>t la Nature,</l>
               <l>Vierge et fraiche <U+017F>ortir avec <U+017F>es ornemens</l>
               <l>Du palais tenebreux des confus élemens:</l>
               <l>Ain<U+017F>y, ROY <U+017F>ans égal, de vous voir <U+017F>ur nos rives</l>
               <l>Suffi<U+017F>oit pour tenir nos volontés captives,</l>
               <l>Et dans le premier an nous combler des plai<U+017F>irs</l>
               <l>Ou pouvoyent a<U+017F>pirer nos plus ardens de<U+017F>irs;</l>
               <l>Ce fut un de vos <U+017F>oins d'arre<U+017F>ter no<U+017F>tre joye,</l>
               <l>Tant qu'elle peu<U+017F>t parétre et plus grande et plus coye,</l>
               <l>Et que de vos rayons la bienfai<U+017F>ante ardeur</l>
               <l>Echauffant no<U+017F>tre Terre eu<U+017F>t banni <U+017F>a froideur,</l>
               <l>Et ces tri<U+017F>tes vapeurs, qui plus elles s' élevent</l>
               <l>Tant plus á vos regards <U+017F>e di<U+017F><U+017F>ipent et crévent.</l>
               <l>Trop de ha<U+017F>te auroit peu vo<U+017F>tre Pompe ternir,</l>
               <l>Et faire de nos jours les crimes rajeunir:</l>
               <l>Mais cet An e<U+017F>t tout vôtre, il e<U+017F>t <U+017F>ans tache aucune,</l>
               <l>Vôtre gloire n' a rien qui <U+017F>on lu<U+017F>tre importune:</l>
               <l>Et nos premiers plai<U+017F>irs á peine <U+017F>ont pa<U+017F><U+017F>és,</l>
               <l>Qu'en les rendant plus grands vous les recommencés:</l>
               <l>Nous donnant chaque jour, comme au Peuple rebelle</l>
               <l>Fit le Ciel autrefois, de la manne nouvelle.</l>
               <l>Tous malheurs á pre<U+017F>ent écartés de nos yeux,</l>
               <l>L' An chargé de plai<U+017F>irs <U+017F>ort des portes des cieux:</l>
               <l>Le Temps n'e<U+017F>t plus courbé <U+017F>ous le faix de <U+017F>on âge,</l>
               <l>Ou rampe langui<U+017F><U+017F>ant denué de plumage:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:45449:40"/>
Flore vient nous revoir dans le char des Zephirs,</l>
               <l>Et par<U+017F>éme les champs d' Emeraude et Sapphirs,</l>
               <l>Et de tous les tre<U+017F>ors dont elle peint l'année,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our mieuxfaire éclatter ce<U+017F>te heureu<U+017F>e journée;</l>
               <l>Cependant que vous, SIRE, en Royal appareil</l>
               <l>Semblés nous vi<U+017F>iter dans celuy du Soleil,</l>
               <l>Et <U+017F>oumettre á vos loix celles de la Nature,</l>
               <l>Fai<U+017F>ant que l' An entier <U+017F>oit vôtre Creature.</l>
               <l>De<U+017F><U+017F>us vous auiourd'huy chaque oeil e<U+017F>t arre<U+017F>té,</l>
               <l>Chaque coeur á vos pieds offre <U+017F>a liberté;</l>
               <l>Et la meilleure part de la Magnificence</l>
               <l>Dont la pompe vous <U+017F>uit, nâit de vôtre pre<U+017F>ence:</l>
               <l>L'heur de la Nation s' exprime en mille accens,</l>
               <l>Qui montent vers le Ciel comme un plai<U+017F>ant encens</l>
               <l>Chargés de vótre Nom; de vótre Cavalcade,</l>
               <l>Les Spectateurs voyans la pompeu<U+017F>e parade</l>
               <l>De leurs hauts Echaffauts, <U+017F>ont encor au de<U+017F><U+017F>ous</l>
               <l>De vótre Maje<U+017F>té; iettans les yeux <U+017F>ur vous.</l>
               <l>A l'envy chaque Brave á triompher s'appre<U+017F>te</l>
               <l>Parmi vo<U+017F>tre Cortége, et datte <U+017F>a conque<U+017F>te</l>
               <l>De ce iour glorieux: mais apres que la nuit</l>
               <l>Sous la clef du <U+017F>ilence a renfermé le bruit,</l>
               <l>De<U+017F>es moites pavots abreuvant vos paupieres,</l>
               <l>Morphée officieux, de ces belles matieres</l>
               <l>Dont vôtre oeil éveillé <U+017F>e vient d'entretenir,</l>
               <l>Fait <U+017F>ur vótre chevet l'image revenir:</l>
               <l>Puis le iour r' allumé, vous marchés droit au Temple</l>
               <l>Que <hi>Vo<U+017F>tre Maje<U+017F>té</hi> <U+017F>outient par <U+017F>on Exemple,</l>
               <l>Ou l'or d'une Couronne á Vótre Chef <U+017F>acré</l>
               <l>Du Throne Souverain vous offre le degré.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:45449:40"/>
Et c'e<U+017F>t bien la rai<U+017F>on que l' Egli<U+017F>e vous donne,</l>
               <l>Vous devant ce qu'elle e<U+017F>t, <hi>Grand Prince</hi> une Couronne.</l>
               <l>Car malgré les Complots du Tyran des Enfers,</l>
               <l>Vous l'avés rétablie, et rela<U+017F>ché <U+017F>es fers;</l>
               <l>Ses doux accords pour vous, <hi>Grand Monarque,</hi> elle em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploye</l>
               <l>Plus pour <U+017F>olennizer que pour croître <U+017F>a joye,</l>
               <l>Et vôtre Nom <U+017F>uivant <U+017F>es airs melodieux,</l>
               <l>E<U+017F>t porté comme encens vers la voute des cieux:</l>
               <l>Mais l'harmonie e<U+017F>t foible, et <U+017F>a force e<U+017F>t petite</l>
               <l>Pour du meilleur des Roys celebrer le merite:</l>
               <l>Tous <U+017F>es divins accords en<U+017F>emble recueillis,</l>
               <l>Dans un <U+017F>uiet <U+017F>i grand <U+017F>ont comme en<U+017F>evelis,</l>
               <l>Et demeurent noyés de me<U+017F>me que l' Avette</l>
               <l>S'étouffe en la liqueur qu'elle me<U+017F>me s'e<U+017F>t faite:</l>
               <l>Et puis ayant remis la Concorde et la Paix,</l>
               <l>Filles de l'Harmonie, au coe ur de vos <U+017F>uiets,</l>
               <l>Vôtre Nom doit il pas par des douceurs pareilles</l>
               <l>A <U+017F>es divins accords, enchanter nos oreilles?</l>
               <l>Cependant de<U+017F><U+017F>us vous la Sainte huile on repand,</l>
               <l>Dont depuis vôtre Chef l'odeur par tout s'e<U+017F>tend</l>
               <l>Vers le Dome du Temple, et revient <U+017F>urchargée</l>
               <l>Des cris des A<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tans, et par ces cris changée</l>
               <l>Comme e<U+017F>prits <U+017F>ublimés en benedictions,</l>
               <l>Qui r'ama<U+017F><U+017F>ent en vous l'heur de trois Nations:</l>
               <l>Et retombent ain<U+017F>i qu'une riche ro<U+017F>ée,</l>
               <l>De l'e<U+017F><U+017F>ence du Ciel<U+017F>ur les fleurs compo<U+017F>ée.</l>
               <l>Non pas que nous pui<U+017F><U+017F>ions par nos voeux repetés</l>
               <l>Ajouter quelque cho<U+017F>e á vos felicités,</l>
               <l>Vous po<U+017F><U+017F>edés a<U+017F><U+017F>és de Grandeur en vous me<U+017F>me,</l>
               <l>Plus par vôtre Vertu que vôtre Diademe</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:45449:41"/>
Digne de nos re<U+017F>pects, vous avés des Tre<U+017F>ors</l>
               <l>Au delà de nos voeux pour l'E<U+017F>prit et le Corps,</l>
               <l>Et nous n' augmentons pas par nos chants vôtre gloire,</l>
               <l>Mais de vôtre Grandeur celebrons la memoire,</l>
               <l>Comme les Anges font no<U+017F>tre joye exprimans,</l>
               <l>Et dans ce doux plai<U+017F>ir no<U+017F>tre âge con<U+017F>umans:</l>
               <l>Plai<U+017F>ir qui ne nai<U+017F>t pas de la <U+017F>eule e<U+017F>perance,</l>
               <l>Ou des loix du devoir, mais de la joüy<U+017F><U+017F>ance</l>
               <l>Des biens de<U+017F>ia pre<U+017F>ens, et qui rend l'avenir</l>
               <l>Par le pa<U+017F><U+017F>é plus cher à no<U+017F>tre <U+017F>ouvenir.</l>
               <l>Quel plege a<U+017F><U+017F>eure mieux les bontés d'un Monarque</l>
               <l>Vers la po<U+017F>terité, que cette Augu<U+017F>te marque</l>
               <l>Que vous nous en donnés par <U+017F>ix lu<U+017F>tres entiers,</l>
               <l>Suivant des Vrais Heros les immortels <U+017F>entiers;</l>
               <l>De plus d'un noble feu vôtre ame e<U+017F>t enflammée:</l>
               <l>D'un aiguillon de gloire et d'honneur animée,</l>
               <l>Et vous brûlés tonjours d'un de<U+017F>ir genereux</l>
               <l>De rendre de vos faits les Siecles amoureux;</l>
               <l>Au<U+017F><U+017F>i qui veut avoir de longues de<U+017F>tinées,</l>
               <l>Doit faire <U+017F>ucceder l'une a l'autre enchainées</l>
               <l>Les belles actions, ain<U+017F>i que dans nos corps</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>n <U+017F>uc égal <U+017F>outient de l'ame les re<U+017F><U+017F>orts.</l>
               <l>Vous avés, <hi>O Grand Prince!</hi> êteint<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> de<U+017F>ià les flames</l>
               <l>De la Rebellion, et di<U+017F><U+017F>ipe <U+017F>es trames,</l>
               <l>Vous avés corrigé ce Zele trop brûlant</l>
               <l>Qui bien loin d'échauffer, de <U+017F>on feu violant</l>
               <l>Con<U+017F>umoit la vigueur de ce<U+017F>te heureu<U+017F>e Terre,</l>
               <l>Et <U+017F>ervoit d'aliment aux fureurs de la guerre:</l>
               <l>Vous avés reforme ces e<U+017F>prits libertins,</l>
               <l>Vous e<U+017F>tes devenu de ces facheux mutins</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:45449:41"/>
Le grand Moderateur, quoy que leur humeur noire</l>
               <l>De re<U+017F>i<U+017F>ter aux Loix fi<U+017F>t <U+017F>a premiere gloire,</l>
               <l>Et n'o<U+017F>a<U+017F>ts'y fier, á pre<U+017F>ent leur devoir</l>
               <l>Du Thrône de Ce<U+017F>ar reconnoit le pouvoir.</l>
               <l>Tant égal en humeur le ciel vous a fait naitre,</l>
               <l>Qu' apprivoi<U+017F>ant le Crime il vous aime pour Maître,</l>
               <l>Ose à vous <U+017F>e fier, &amp; me<U+017F>me con<U+017F>entir</l>
               <l>A recevoir vos loix apres le repentir!</l>
               <l>L'oubli <U+017F>e doit en nous e<U+017F>timer pour un crime,</l>
               <l>Mais quand <hi>mon Roy</hi> s'en <U+017F>ert il le rend legitime,</l>
               <l>Et l'habille en vertu, dont pre<U+017F>ques á l'envy</l>
               <l>Tout un Cortege entier, Grand Roy, vous a <U+017F>uivy</l>
               <l>Des Climats étrangers <U+017F>ans mélange de vices,</l>
               <l>Des maux des Souverains les perfides complices.</l>
               <l>Vous ne degui<U+017F>és point l'état de vótre Coeur,</l>
               <l>De votre pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion il e<U+017F>t tousours vainqueur,</l>
               <l>Et <U+017F>on calme jamais ne couve de tempe<U+017F>te,</l>
               <l>Ny <U+017F>ous un ciel <U+017F>erain de tonnerre n'appre<U+017F>te.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Quand du Monde nai<U+017F><U+017F>ant la premiere Sai<U+017F>on</l>
               <l>Vit un Roy das l'enclos de chacune Mai<U+017F>on,</l>
               <l>Lors chaque Pere avoit <U+017F>on Souverain Empire;</l>
               <l>Mais vous e<U+017F>tes né tel, et tel pouvant vous dire</l>
               <l>Roy de droit ab<U+017F>olu, toujours vous imités</l>
               <l>D'vn Pere envers les <U+017F>iens les plus tendres bontés;</l>
               <l>Puis quand pour reparer ce<U+017F>te cele<U+017F>te flame</l>
               <l>De Vos e<U+017F>prits la<U+017F><U+017F>és, Vous relachés vótre ame;</l>
               <l>Elle a toujours pour but quelque noble de<U+017F><U+017F>ein,</l>
               <l>Que l' Amour ou l' Honneur vous ver<U+017F>e dans le <U+017F>ein.</l>
               <l>Né <hi>Souverain des Mers,</hi> et po<U+017F><U+017F>edant le Titre</l>
               <l>De <hi>Roy de l'Ocean,</hi> dont vous e<U+017F>tes l' Arbitre:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:45449:42"/>
Vous vous diverti<U+017F><U+017F>és <U+017F>ur ce moite Element,</l>
               <l>Qui fait de Vos Etats la force et l'ornement.</l>
               <l>Lá quand les nuits d'E<U+017F>té tendent leurs voiles <U+017F>ombres</l>
               <l>Vous y venés chercher la fraicheur dans les ombres;</l>
               <l>Puis quand l'Hyver des flots excite la fureur,</l>
               <l>Plus hardy que Ce<U+017F>ar vous domtés <U+017F>on horreur.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I'en dirois encor plus, mais ie fens mon langage</l>
               <l>Trop foible pour loüer, Sire, vo<U+017F>tre Courage;</l>
               <l>Et la peur doit <U+017F>ai<U+017F>ir tout fidelle Suiet,</l>
               <l>Qui s'approche trop prés d'vn <U+017F>i brillant objet:</l>
               <l>Vos Fregates, l'honnenr des plaines azurées,</l>
               <l>Peintes de cent combats <U+017F>ur leurs Pouppes dorées,</l>
               <l>Font tout vótre plai<U+017F>ir, et réveillent<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> en vous</l>
               <l>Parmi vos pa<U+017F><U+017F>etemps ce Martial courroux,</l>
               <l>Nourri dans vôtre <U+017F>ein dés vos ieunes années,</l>
               <l>Qui vous rend la terreur des Te<U+017F>tes couronnées:</l>
               <l>Ainsy nous éprouvons quelle e<U+017F>t l'utilité,</l>
               <l>Des diverti<U+017F><U+017F>emens de vo<U+017F>tre Maje<U+017F>té</l>
               <l>Pour l'intere<U+017F>t public, puis qu'en vos plai<U+017F>irs me<U+017F>mes</l>
               <l>Vous me<U+017F>lés prudemment les <U+017F>oins du Diadéme.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Prés de Vo<U+017F>tre Cour vient tous les iours <U+017F>e calmer</l>
               <l>Dans un nouveau Canal le reflus de la Mer:</l>
               <l>Les poi<U+017F><U+017F>ons étonnés dans leurs grottes profondes</l>
               <l>Admirent la fraicheur de ces nouvelles ondes</l>
               <l>Thetys la<U+017F><U+017F>e du bruit etmurmure des flots</l>
               <l>Dedans ce Lit Royal vient chercher <U+017F>on repos.</l>
               <l>L'oy<U+017F>eau <U+017F>auvage icy quitte <U+017F>a defiance,</l>
               <l>Tant tout <U+017F>ous vôtre Nom <U+017F>e trouve en a<U+017F><U+017F>eurance.</l>
               <l>Vôtre chere <hi>Tami<U+017F>e,</hi> aux <U+017F>oins o<U+017F><U+017F>icieux</l>
               <l>De qui ce<U+017F>te I<U+017F>le doit vôtre a<U+017F>pect gracieux,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:45449:42"/>
Nous va bien to<U+017F>p d'vn iour filló d'or et de <U+017F>oye,</l>
               <l>Encores une fois faire gou<U+017F>ter la joye:</l>
               <l>Ioye à nulle pareille, et dont l'aimable iour</l>
               <l>Ne cede qu'á celuy de vótre heureux Retour,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nous donnant une Reine,</hi> en qui la De<U+017F>tinée</l>
               <l>Garde l'ame á maint corps de Te<U+017F>te couronnée:</l>
               <l>Vótre Amour le premier fit ce<U+017F><U+017F>er nos debats,</l>
               <l>Et par luy no<U+017F>tre Paix <U+017F>e con<U+017F>erve ioy bas:</l>
               <l>Chaque Inde de vos feux devenant la Rivalle,</l>
               <l>Son or et <U+017F>es joyaux pour vôtre Reyne étalle,</l>
               <l>Celle cy vous fait voir <U+017F>es plus riches metaux,</l>
               <l>L'autre avec <U+017F>on encens tache á guarir nos maux</l>
               <l>En appai<U+017F>ant les Cieux; Deux Grands Princes attendent</l>
               <l>Quel e<U+017F>t vôtre decret, et leur joye <U+017F>u<U+017F>pendent</l>
               <l>Augré de Vótre choix, et Vótre <U+017F>eul de<U+017F>ir</l>
               <l>Leur va donner un Sceptre, ou l'o<U+017F>te á <U+017F>on plai<U+017F>ir.</l>
               <l>Ain<U+017F>i du <U+017F>acré Che<U+017F>ne on tiroit le pre<U+017F>age</l>
               <l>Des de<U+017F>tins á venir, dedans le premier age,</l>
               <l>Comme on vient avec voeux vos oracles chercher,</l>
               <l>Et hors de vos rameaux des Sceptres détacher.</l>
               <l>Vos Sujets cependant tenans leurs de<U+017F>tinées</l>
               <l>A vôtre volonté tout a fait enchainées,</l>
               <l>Su<U+017F>pendent prudemment leur haine ou leur amour,</l>
               <l>Sans les determiner qu'au gré de Vôtre Cour.</l>
               <l>Choi<U+017F>i<U+017F><U+017F>és donc, Grand Prince, afin que de nôtre Age</l>
               <l>Ee de celuy qui vient <hi>la Paix <U+017F>oit l'heritage.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FIN.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="epigram">
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:45449:43"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ANGLORUM POETARUM</hi> culti<U+017F><U+017F>imo, <hi>Sibique Amici<U+017F><U+017F>imo Dom.</hi> EDM. WALLERO.
De hâcce quorundam illius Poematum ad <U+017F>pecimen, ex Anglico Ver<U+017F>ione.</head>
            <head>
               <hi>EPIGRAMMA</hi> Authoris.</head>
            <l>ILla etiàm merita e<U+017F>t concinnae vocis honorem</l>
            <l>Quae blandos Echò <U+017F>cit dare vera <U+017F>onos.</l>
            <l>Dúm<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> tuos valeam, <hi>WALLERE,</hi> referre lepores</l>
            <l>Quae numeros auris re<U+017F>puet aequa meos?</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>P. D. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:45449:43"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> FORT<g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>NATE ISLANDS.</head>
            <head type="sub">BEING Part of a larger Poem written formerly in French, upon the Happy INAUGURATION OF CHARLES II.</head>
            <byline>
               <hi>By</hi> P. D. C. <hi>Gent. And <U+017F>ince by him Tran<U+017F>lated in Engli<U+017F>h and Latin.</hi>
            </byline>
            <bibl>Senec. Trag. Medea.</bibl>
            <q>
               <l>—Venient annis</l>
               <l>Secula <U+017F>eris, quibus Oceanus</l>
               <l>Vincula rerum laxet, &amp; ingens</l>
               <l>Pateat Tellus, Tiphy<U+017F>que novos</l>
               <l>Detegat Orbes, nec <U+017F>it terris</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>ltima Thule.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:45449:44"/>
            <p>TO THE HEROICK and ILLUSTRIOUS RUPERT, Prince Palatine of the <hi>RHINE,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>As a Monument of his devoted re<U+017F>pects, and due e<U+017F>teem of his Highne<U+017F><U+017F>es celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vertues, and great Experience in <hi>SEA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VOY AGES;</hi> and as a de<U+017F>erved acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of his H. indefatigable ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours in promoting <hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi> Plantations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P. D. C.</hi> Humbly Dedicates this Pindarick Rapture.</p>
            <p>Being part of his Poem of the <hi>Fortunate ISLANDS,</hi> formerly written in French and Addre<U+017F><U+017F>ed to The KINGS MAJESTY.</p>
            <p>Upon the Solemnity of His Au<U+017F>picious CORONATION.</p>
            <l>
               <hi>—For<U+017F>an &amp; haec memini<U+017F><U+017F>e juvabit</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Jàm pa<U+017F><U+017F>e ô graviora!</hi>
            </l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:45449:44"/>
            <head>THE <hi>FORTUNATE ISLANDS.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>Tran<U+017F>lated out of a Poem written in French, and formerly addre<U+017F><U+017F>ed to The MAJESTY of CHARLES II.
Upon the Solemn Day of HIS <hi>CORONATION.</hi>
PINDARICK ODE.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Stanza.</hi> I. An<U+017F>wering the XXIV in the French.</head>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>TOuch'd with that Flame which Poets Brea<U+017F>ts does warm,</l>
               <l>The dark Events of things to come I <U+017F>pye,</l>
               <l>Thrice Glorious KING! and dare not to deny</l>
               <l>This truth which <U+017F>hould become a crime conceal'd<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
               </l>
               <l>Po<U+017F>terity, did it lye unreveal'd,</l>
               <l>Were therein much concern'd, who<U+017F>e joy 'twill be</l>
               <l>To know with what returns our Vowes for thee</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Great Charles,</hi> came back from Heaven, but we much more</l>
               <l>Concern'd to know, thou did<U+017F>t that joy re<U+017F>tore,</l>
               <l>To prove the Greate<U+017F>t King that ever a Scepter bore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:45449:45"/>
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>Know then, of Crowned heads the worthie<U+017F>t Head!</l>
               <l>That <U+017F>ome kind Stars on us yet once <U+017F>hall <U+017F>mile,</l>
               <l>And on this I<U+017F>le</l>
               <l>A golden Age in <U+017F>pight of Fate retrive;</l>
               <l>Whil<U+017F>t thou our <hi>Pilot</hi> at the Stern <U+017F>hall <U+017F>it,</l>
               <l>A <hi>Salomon</hi> for Prudence, Fame, and Wit,</l>
               <l>Our De<U+017F>tinies to guide and happine<U+017F><U+017F>e to mind;</l>
               <l>This Globe again new <hi>Continents</hi> <U+017F>hall find,</l>
               <l>Thy conqu'ring Navy a new <hi>Ophir</hi> yield;</l>
               <l>And with new Titles fill thy Royal Shield.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>Under that part of the divided Globe</l>
               <l>Where <U+017F>lowe Bootes riding on <hi>Charles</hi> Wain,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(a)</hi> Is oft <U+017F>een in his lofty Orbe</l>
               <l>To plough the furrowes of the Main:</l>
               <l>And where the bolde<U+017F>t Ships that nearer came</l>
               <l>To make land, <note n="b" place="bottom">Therefore called <hi>Terra del fuego.</hi>
                  </note> never <U+017F>aw but flame</l>
               <l>Standing at gaze amid'<U+017F>t the Sea, there run</l>
               <l>Spread under a new Pole by the Almighty Hand,</l>
               <l>Long Tracts of va<U+017F>t and unknown Land,</l>
               <l>A larger Continent this Earthly Globe hath none. <note place="bottom">This happens in the po<U+017F>ition of the Sphere where the Line is Zenith.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:45449:45"/>
               <head>IV.</head>
               <l>As much as gue<U+017F>s by rea<U+017F>on led can find,</l>
               <l>And of dark truths inform our mind,</l>
               <l>Here <U+017F>tands in force yet Natures ancient Law,</l>
               <l>Which harmle<U+017F>s men by untaught rules do's aw;</l>
               <l>Of <U+017F>uch this happy clime has <U+017F>tore,</l>
               <l>Though a <hi>Gigantik</hi> race appear'd on <U+017F>hore</l>
               <l>Where <note n="a" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Viz.</hi> about 47. gr. South Latitude, where a <U+017F>ort of very tall men hath been feen.</note> colder aire breeds ruder wits;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="bottom">From 15. to 30. gr. S. lat. a goodly land runneth, of which the <hi>Hollanders</hi> are <U+017F>aid to have <U+017F>ome Maps, but kept by them concealed to this day.</note> But neer the Sun heat does infu<U+017F>e the <U+017F>eed</l>
               <l>Of a more vertuous race, and kinder breed,</l>
               <l>Among whom yet unwrong'd fair Virgin Nature <U+017F>its.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>V.</head>
               <l>There, next th' imbalmed groves where bright <hi>Aurora</hi> dwels,</l>
               <l>In fragrant woods old <hi>Brachmans</hi> kept their cells</l>
               <l>In the worlds birth, and on this happy <U+017F>tage</l>
               <l>Did celebrate the golden age,</l>
               <l>Teaching of Souls th' immortal fall and <U+017F>pring,</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Pythagoras</hi> thence to credulous <hi>Greece</hi> did bring.</l>
               <l>There, great <hi>Jarchas</hi> the next <hi>Magi</hi> taught</l>
               <l>The worlds <hi>Magnalia</hi> with hid knowledge fraught.</l>
               <l>For whom a <note n="*" place="bottom">Apollonius Thyanaeus.</note> curious <hi>Greek,</hi> his Seven wi<U+017F>e for<U+017F>ook,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Athens</hi> thence return'd with unknown wonders <U+017F>trook.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:45449:46"/>
               <head>VI.</head>
               <l>There, <note n="<U+263F>" place="bottom">Philo<U+017F>ophorum.</note> that kind <U+017F>teem which from <U+017F>tars drops on Earth,</l>
               <l>When <U+017F>he breeds Metals, <U+017F>wells up bulky hills,</l>
               <l>And with rich oare whole Countries fills,</l>
               <l>O're<U+017F>pread with branches which betray their birth:</l>
               <l>There in clear <U+017F>treams and cry<U+017F>tal brooks, gold torn</l>
               <l>From <U+017F>ome adjacent Mine where it was born,</l>
               <l>Runs unregarded with vile pebbles mixt,</l>
               <l>As if his juyce was yet unfixt;</l>
               <l>And Silver <U+017F>hutes by <note n="*" place="margin">Archaean.</note> <U+017F>ecret heat provokt</l>
               <l>In Ma<U+017F><U+017F>y Cry<U+017F>tal Rocks, as <hi>Alpian</hi> ridges yoakt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <l>This land in <hi>Diamonds</hi> and <hi>Rubies</hi> <U+017F>warms,</l>
               <l>As common <U+017F>tones in our fields u<U+017F>e to grow,</l>
               <l>Their lovely green there Emeralds do be<U+017F>tow,</l>
               <l>Their quarries like fair meadows <U+017F>how;</l>
               <l>There, without Fi<U+017F>hers art, or divers toil,</l>
               <l>That rich <U+017F>hoare yields the Orient <U+017F>hining Pearl</l>
               <l>Freely expos'd upon th' imbroidred <U+017F>oyl,</l>
               <l>And on each twig in woods, a worm does curl</l>
               <l>Tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>hining bowels with it's own life <U+017F>pun,</l>
               <l>Wherewith Kings hou<U+017F>es trim'd out-<U+017F>hine the Sun.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:45449:46"/>
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <l>The Saphir, Amethy<U+017F>t, and Onyx there adorne</l>
               <l>The grots of de<U+017F>arts by wi<U+017F>e Natures care,</l>
               <l>And the <U+017F>treakt Agath with it's chances born,</l>
               <l>To whom his art no Graver can compare:</l>
               <l>The changing Opall growing on the <U+017F>hore,</l>
               <l>With more fair colours charmes the eye,</l>
               <l>Then when the wond'rous Bow, or gay morn paints the skie;</l>
               <l>And mother of Pearl there breeds in <U+017F>uch a <U+017F>tore,</l>
               <l>That were it not for woods that yield a lov'lier <U+017F>hade,</l>
               <l>Each Native might thereof have unbought hou<U+017F>esmade.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="9">
               <head>IX.</head>
               <l>But the<U+017F>e tall woods who were already grown,</l>
               <l>When Time was infant yet, the world a babe,</l>
               <l>Afford <U+017F>uch plea<U+017F>ant <U+017F>hade,</l>
               <l>That ea<U+017F>e it <U+017F>elf <U+017F>eems there to fix it's la<U+017F>ting Throne:</l>
               <l>Tho<U+017F>e Palaces to whom our Art</l>
               <l>Does all the helps of wit and hand impart,</l>
               <l>Where Porphyrie vain luxe to Marble joyns,</l>
               <l>In their high pomp cannot out do</l>
               <l>The<U+017F>e rural man<U+017F>ions, who<U+017F>e <U+017F>hade entertains</l>
               <l>Freely their gue<U+017F>ts with meat and <U+017F>helter to.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="10">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:45449:47"/>
               <head>X.</head>
               <l>There <hi>Pines</hi> and <hi>Cedars</hi> reaching to the skie,</l>
               <l>Do rai<U+017F>e a roof amazing <U+017F>tanders by,</l>
               <l>Whil'<U+017F>t th' humble myrtle which embalm's the fields,</l>
               <l>Perfum'd walls next to the foundation yields.</l>
               <l>The fragrant Jels'min, and <U+017F>weet Orange-tree</l>
               <l>Common, as Fern and Broom are with us <U+017F>een,</l>
               <l>Frame a contexture of their la<U+017F>ting green;</l>
               <l>All Flora's <U+017F>tore either for <U+017F>mell or eye</l>
               <l>Makes a Mo<U+017F>aik floore mixt with <U+017F>ilky mo<U+017F>s,</l>
               <l>Who<U+017F>e gli<U+017F>tering down doves neck's in Sun <U+017F>hine does <U+017F>urpa<U+017F>s.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="11">
               <head>XI.</head>
               <l>There, the kind Earth untoucht with plough or <U+017F>pade,</l>
               <l>And without drops from careful Tillers brow,</l>
               <l>All <U+017F>orts of fruits for Sight or Palate made</l>
               <l>On happy mortalls does be<U+017F>tow.</l>
               <l>There <U+017F>weet <hi>Potatoes</hi> growing in each ground,</l>
               <l>And milky <hi>Coco</hi>'s in each forre<U+017F>t found</l>
               <l>Afford unbought and free meals in each place,</l>
               <l>Andwithout hands of cooks each common table grace,</l>
               <l>Then to <U+017F>upply for drink the want of forrain wines</l>
               <l>Her plea<U+017F>ant <U+017F>ap, to its better juice, the <U+017F>weet <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite</hi> joyns.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="12">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:45449:47"/>
               <head>XII.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bacchus and Ceres</hi> here</l>
               <l>Do always freely Crown the year,</l>
               <l>Though field for it be never torn,</l>
               <l>With fruits enough their Altars to adorn;</l>
               <l>Not that the willing earth <U+017F>hould there her crops refu<U+017F>e</l>
               <l>If Husbandmen their skill did u<U+017F>e:</l>
               <l>The Stars are there too gentle and too kind,</l>
               <l>And did care vigor add to the <U+017F>elf growing vine,</l>
               <l>Under the leaning grapes the cru<U+017F>hed props <U+017F>hould pine,</l>
               <l>And for one ventur'd corn the Sower thou<U+017F>ands find.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="13">
               <head>XIII.</head>
               <l>But where free nature with <U+017F>uch bounty fills</l>
               <l>Our trea<U+017F>ures with its own rich <U+017F>tore,</l>
               <l>What madne<U+017F><U+017F>e to repine &amp; crave for more;</l>
               <l>Or controle with our Art what her own prudence wills?</l>
               <l>O! fond attempt of humane pride!</l>
               <l>Which would through other <hi>paths</hi> our wanton <hi>actions</hi> guide</l>
               <l>Then tho<U+017F>e, which her own hand do's for us wi<U+017F>ely trace;</l>
               <l>And you, thrice happy mortals! whom that place</l>
               <l>Does entertain without ambitious care,</l>
               <l>To add to what her love appoints to be your <U+017F>hare!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="14">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:45449:48"/>
               <head>XIV.</head>
               <l>There your calm numerous years do gently <U+017F>lide<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
               </l>
               <l>O happy mortals! without pain or grief;</l>
               <l>Untill your <U+017F>tars become your guide</l>
               <l>To <U+017F>ilent du<U+017F>t, and death, which with joys pa<U+017F>t belief</l>
               <l>You do embrace; you happy while<U+017F>t alive!</l>
               <l>Who<U+017F>e well-tun'd minds were never put to <U+017F>trive</l>
               <l>Again<U+017F>t your crazy bodies tott'ring frame,</l>
               <l>But kept un<U+017F>potted your Cele<U+017F>tial flame</l>
               <l>From Tyrant pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions ever free,</l>
               <l>And from all <U+017F>pots of frail mortalitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="15">
               <head>XV.</head>
               <l>There next <hi>Aurora's Palace</hi> where the Morn</l>
               <l>Keeps con<U+017F>tant watch, <U+017F>oft <hi>Zephyrus</hi> awak't</l>
               <l>And charm'd with love of his fair Nymph each day</l>
               <l>Comes perfum'd with the Sun in <hi>Flora</hi>'s groves,</l>
               <l>And there his amber-<U+017F>ighs does <U+017F>ilently di<U+017F>play,</l>
               <l>Whi<U+017F>p'ring to chirping birds how fair a Nymph he loves;</l>
               <l>The<U+017F>e Groves then whom the Sun no <U+017F>weeter <U+017F>ees,</l>
               <l>A thou<U+017F>and dales with native flow'rs do paint,</l>
               <l>Which plea<U+017F>antly confound the gazers eyes,</l>
               <l>And in their <U+017F>miling looks through heat nor cold nere faint.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="16">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:45449:48"/>
               <head>XVI.</head>
               <l>There neither <U+017F>torm nor <U+017F>harp <hi>Chiroco</hi>'s bla<U+017F>t</l>
               <l>Does any di<U+017F>cord 'twixt the Sea<U+017F>ons ca<U+017F>t,</l>
               <l>A con<U+017F>tant Spring the gay birds entertains,</l>
               <l>And for their ne<U+017F>ts a con<U+017F>tant green maintains,</l>
               <l>Whence <U+017F>porting they as long as are the days,</l>
               <l>'Twixt harmle<U+017F><U+017F>e love and plea<U+017F>ant layes,</l>
               <l>With fear or pining care their happy lives nere <U+017F>tint;</l>
               <l>The Sun by which their lungs are tun'd</l>
               <l>Does thou<U+017F>and colours on their feathers print</l>
               <l>The Eye to entertain, whil<U+017F>t that the Ears are charm'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="17">
               <head>XVII.</head>
               <l>There the bountiful Sea by kind heat cheri<U+017F>ht <U+017F>til</l>
               <l>With rare and unknown cates her fruitful womb do's fil,</l>
               <l>Through waves of Chri<U+017F>tal bright and clear</l>
               <l>Her well <U+017F>tor'd bottome does appear:</l>
               <l>There in pure Brooks that <U+017F>wiftly run,</l>
               <l>And in their race their own <U+017F>tream <U+017F>hun,</l>
               <l>Many rare Fi<U+017F>h his <U+017F>ilver <U+017F>cales di<U+017F>playes.</l>
               <l>Edging the ta<U+017F>t by <U+017F>ight, there as a common di<U+017F>h</l>
               <l>The bright <hi>Dorado</hi> cloth'd with golden rayes</l>
               <l>Is daily <U+017F>erv'd, and there each <U+017F>en<U+017F>e enjoyes his wi<U+017F>h.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="18">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:45449:49"/>
               <head>XVIII.</head>
               <l>That braki<U+017F>h ta<U+017F>t which other Seas infe<U+017F>ts,</l>
               <l>Vexing with nau<U+017F>eous <U+017F>mells her <U+017F>queami<U+017F>h gue<U+017F>ts,</l>
               <l>Is bani<U+017F>ht thence, her perfum'd froth that breaks</l>
               <l>Each day on Shore, leaves there great amber cakes;</l>
               <l>There many branch of precious coral torn</l>
               <l>From its concealed tree, does the rich <U+017F>trand adorn;</l>
               <l>A <U+017F>trand where <U+017F>oft winds ever <U+017F>mile,</l>
               <l>And weaves do only ri<U+017F>e in <U+017F>port,</l>
               <l>Where no rocks Seamen do beguile</l>
               <l>Nor <U+017F>torms cau<U+017F>e <U+017F>hipwrack in the port.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="19">
               <head>XIX.</head>
               <l>That famous Bird which Nature made</l>
               <l>Sole Ma<U+017F>ter of his life expir'd,</l>
               <l>Which only we know in the <U+017F>hade</l>
               <l>Of dark truth in times cell retir'd;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Phoenix</hi> which his dayes alone</l>
               <l>Knows to retrive when they are gone,</l>
               <l>And of all mortal agents can</l>
               <l>Lengthen at will his own lifes <U+017F>pan,</l>
               <l>Above all others do's affect that Soyle</l>
               <l>Where for his death each wood affords a Funeral pile.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="20">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:45449:49"/>
               <head>XX.</head>
               <l>That other bird whom we may call</l>
               <l>Of other birds the true<U+017F>t gue<U+017F>t oth' sky,</l>
               <l>Which from his pitch does never fall,</l>
               <l>And takes his Name from where departed Saints do fly;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Paradice bird,</hi> who without help of wings,</l>
               <l>Su<U+017F>pended by <U+017F>ome truer <U+017F>prings</l>
               <l>Does never touch our earths defiling <U+017F>pot,</l>
               <l>Above all climes this chu<U+017F>es for his lot;</l>
               <l>Where never civil war does 'twixt the <U+017F>ea<U+017F>ons ri<U+017F>e,</l>
               <l>Nor hoary fro<U+017F>ts do check the mildne<U+017F>s of the skies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="21">
               <head>XXI.</head>
               <l>There, our eyes <U+017F>ee in truth what all tho<U+017F>e wanton</l>
               <l>Of dreaming Poets in their heated veyne,</l>
               <l>Under fal<U+017F>e prai<U+017F>es wrote of their <hi>Elizian plaine</hi> tales</l>
               <l>In time of old; There a <U+017F>treame never fayles</l>
               <l>Of harmle<U+017F>s mirth, of <U+017F>ports and youthful playes</l>
               <l>To court our <U+017F>en<U+017F>e, and <U+017F>oftly <U+017F>teal our dayes</l>
               <l>In con<U+017F>tant joy, in <U+017F>pight of envious time;</l>
               <l>And what in Fables Poets old</l>
               <l>Of happie<U+017F>t countries have us told,</l>
               <l>We find in real truth in this mo<U+017F>t happy clime.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="22">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:45449:50"/>
               <head>XXII.</head>
               <l>This is that <hi>Famous I<U+017F>le</hi> which a <note n="a" place="bottom">Plato.</note> 
                  <hi>Great Sage</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Long <U+017F>ince reveal'd the world a <note n="b" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Seneca</hi> the Tragedian.</note> Poet <U+017F>ung,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Great Atlantis</hi> which our age</l>
               <l>Hath waited for, and unknown prais'd <U+017F>o long;</l>
               <l>Th' <hi>He<U+017F>perian Grove</hi> to none but our <hi>Alcides</hi> free:</l>
               <l>There Plenty, Peace, and Mirth are long <U+017F>ince fled</l>
               <l>Frighted by di<U+017F>mal jarres, untill by Thee</l>
               <l>They be retriv'd, GREAT PRINCE, and as thy va<U+017F><U+017F>als led</l>
               <l>To <U+017F>hare the honour of this happy day,</l>
               <l>And at thy Sacred Feet their frutes for ever lay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="23">
               <head>XXIII.</head>
               <l>Go then, and pro<U+017F>per, Magnanimous King,</l>
               <l>Gather tho<U+017F>e Bays which for Thee only <U+017F>pring,</l>
               <l>Let all Advent'rers graceing Thy de<U+017F><U+017F>eine,</l>
               <l>To this ju<U+017F>t Conque<U+017F>t their be<U+017F>t <U+017F>tars re<U+017F>igne;</l>
               <l>And thou who<U+017F>e blood with <hi>Cezars blood</hi> is mixt,</l>
               <l>Who<U+017F>e bold attempts have Fortunes favour fixt,</l>
               <l>Oft to thy Sword, or through her frowns made way</l>
               <l>To reach thy <U+017F>elf and thine the long'd for Bay,</l>
               <l>Lend us, Brave <hi>RUPERT,</hi> both thy Head and Hand,</l>
               <l>All Seas by <hi>CHARLES</hi> allow'd will <U+017F>toop at thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="24">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:45449:50"/>
               <head>XXIV.</head>
               <l>Thou ha<U+017F>t enough with thy bright Name</l>
               <l>Filled the trump of Fame,</l>
               <l>Her voice and lungs by prai<U+017F>ing thee</l>
               <l>Almo<U+017F>t exhau<U+017F>ted be:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Europ</hi> enough in the<U+017F>e our parts hath <U+017F>een</l>
               <l>Of thy brave deeds the glory <U+017F>hine;</l>
               <l>Go, fill the unknown world with thy renown,</l>
               <l>And there proclaime the Briti<U+017F>h Crown,</l>
               <l>Thy Heart exceeds what with us may be done,</l>
               <l>Call for new witne<U+017F><U+017F>es under a new Sun.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="25">
               <head>XXV.</head>
               <l>Under thy Conduct and victorious armes</l>
               <l>Matcht to the <hi>Briti<U+017F>h</hi> colours, Right <U+017F>hall aw</l>
               <l>The yielding Ocean, and re<U+017F>tore that Law</l>
               <l>Which <U+017F>hips does free from greedy Pyrats harms;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Great Name of our CHARLES</hi> <U+017F>hall be</l>
               <l>A <U+017F>trong <U+017F>afegard to <U+017F>helter us and and thee,</l>
               <l>Should<U+017F>t thou meet with oppo<U+017F>ing rage.</l>
               <l>And Heav'n it <U+017F>elf with thee will joyn in <U+017F>hare,</l>
               <l>To ble<U+017F>s with Peace and Plenty this our Age,</l>
               <l>In part of tho<U+017F>e returns we expect from thy care.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:45449:51"/>
            <head>FORTUNATARUM INSULARUM DESCRIPTIO POETICA.</head>
            <head>PRO INAUGUTATIONE CAROLI II.
<hi>E GALLICO TRANSLATA: ET ILLUSTRISSIMO PRINCIPI RUPERTO PALATINO,</hi> &amp;c.
<hi>Rerum Maritimarum experti<U+017F><U+017F>imo, &amp; An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glicarum Coloniarum promovendarum <U+017F>tudio<U+017F>i<U+017F><U+017F>imo, in ob<U+017F>equii perpetui Monumentum ab ip<U+017F>o Authore,</hi> P. D. C.
Dicata.</head>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>STANZA. I.</head>
               <l>PLenus Appollineo quae <U+017F>int ventura calore</l>
               <l>Auguror, (e<U+017F>t vatum mens prae<U+017F>cia nempè futuri)</l>
               <l>Nec mea Mu<U+017F>a <U+017F>ilens audet quae fata recondunt</l>
               <l>Sub tenebris pre<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F><U+017F>e, decet quae <U+017F>cire nepotes.</l>
               <l>Illos <U+017F>cire velim no<U+017F>tris quàm Numina votis</l>
               <l>Non duras vertêre aures, quám<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> illa <U+017F>ecundis</l>
               <l>Nos ultro implerint <U+017F>ucce<U+017F><U+017F>ibus omine fau<U+017F>to:</l>
               <l>Verùm &amp; nos quoque <U+017F>cire iuvat, quàm laeta futuris</l>
               <l>Temporibus per Te na<U+017F>centur <U+017F>aecula Mundo</l>
               <l>Et Triplicis quantùm tibi cre<U+017F>cet gloria Sceptri.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:45449:51"/>
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>Di<U+017F>ce ergo, <hi>Regum Rex ô digni<U+017F><U+017F>ime!</hi> no<U+017F>tris</l>
               <l>Carminibus doctus, quantùm indulgentia coeli</l>
               <l>Te nobis Regnante dabit, quòdque illa <U+017F>erenos</l>
               <l>Quales &amp; primis Saturnia <U+017F>aecla dedêre</l>
               <l>Sponte <U+017F>uâ terris, reparabit provida <U+017F>oles,</l>
               <l>Vel Parcâ renuente tuo, <hi>Rex Maxime,</hi> ductu:</l>
               <l>Magnus Idumaeis ut quùm regnabat in oris</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Schelomo,</hi> terrarum nova Nereus adyta pandet,</l>
               <l>Alter erit tùm Typhis &amp; altera fluctibus Argos</l>
               <l>Quae <hi>Fortunatas</hi> re<U+017F>erat Te Vindice <hi>Terras.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>E<U+017F>t Locus oppo<U+017F>ito quo volvitur orbis in axe,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="bottom">Hoc contingit in po<U+017F>itione Sphaerae rectae, &amp; maxima parte Au<U+017F>tralis Hemi<U+017F>pherii.</note> Fluctibus Oceani praeceps ubi mergitur Arctos,</l>
               <l>Sedulâ ubi Naturae lu<U+017F>tranti indagine limbum</l>
               <l>Cingentem liquidae quicquid <U+017F>uperinnatat undae,</l>
               <l>Praeter aquas <note n="b" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Idcircò Continentis illius pars illa quae Hi<U+017F>panis Navigato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus primùm innotuit,</hi> Terra del fuego <hi>dicta.</hi>
                  </note> igne<U+017F>que procul vidi<U+017F><U+017F>e micantes,</l>
               <l>Nil hùc u<U+017F>que datum e<U+017F>t, jacet<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> haec incognita terra</l>
               <l>Obver<U+017F>o vicina polo; Magnique Tonantis</l>
               <l>Magnum opu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note n="c" place="bottom">Totum enim Au<U+017F>tralem Polum circumambit. ad lat. 13. gr. in aliquibus locis pertingens.</note> ip<U+017F>a dies namque in <U+017F>e condere Phoebum</l>
               <l>Et reparare videt, <U+017F>tadium pernicibus aequans</l>
               <l>Exporrecta rotis, quo non e<U+017F>t majus in orbe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:45449:52"/>
               <head>IV.</head>
               <l>Si benè conjiciunt divino lumine tactae</l>
               <l>Vatum animae, dictata vigent hîc prima recentis</l>
               <l>Naturae, legesque colit (quas <U+017F>uadet hone<U+017F>tum)</l>
               <l>Incola foelicis Terrae, qui <U+017F>implice cultu,</l>
               <l>Semper inoffen<U+017F>ae carpit <U+017F>olamina vitae;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Ad Au<U+017F>tralem lat. 57. circiter gr. gens ferox &amp; giganteae <U+017F>tatuiae a primis Navigatorib. vi<U+017F>a.</hi> Purcha<U+017F>. lin<U+017F>chot. &amp;c.</note> Sunt tamen extremâ Titanum è <U+017F>emine ripâ</l>
               <l>Vi<U+017F>i aliqui, quorum plùs denas corpora palmas</l>
               <l>Ex<U+017F>uperant oculi<U+017F>que truces, &amp; fronte minaces:</l>
               <l>Sed vicina Polo Gens haec; quae proxima Phoebo</l>
               <l>Mitior, admittit meliores pectore cultus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>V.</head>
               <l>Hîc juxtà Eôos redolentes Cynnamon Hortos,</l>
               <l>Invia <hi>Brachmanes</hi> nemorum <U+017F>ylvasque <U+017F>ecuti,</l>
               <l>Innocui <hi>Samiae</hi> coluerunt dogmata <hi>Sectae,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Aure áque emeritis celebrârunt <U+017F>aecula My<U+017F>tis;</l>
               <l>Hîc veterum fido quondam Schola vera Magorum</l>
               <l>Excepit mandata <U+017F>inu dictantis <hi>Iarbae,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ver áque na<U+017F>centis Sophiae monumenta reclu<U+017F>it;</l>
               <l>Huc <U+017F>eptem <U+017F>pretis Sapientibus impiger ar<U+017F>it</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="e" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Scil. Apollonius, qui Indiam</hi> Gymno<U+017F>ophi<U+017F>tas <hi>invi<U+017F>urus pera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravit. Sed haec Poeticè non hi<U+017F>toricè accipienda.</hi>
                  </note> Ille Thyanoeus Patriâ migrare relictâ,</l>
               <l>Unde redux doctas <note n="f" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Miraculis, de quibus fu<U+017F>è</hi> Jamblichus <hi>in Vitâ Pythagorae <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                           <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
                        </gap> <U+017F>it.</hi>
                  </note> factis <U+017F>tupefecit <hi>Athenas.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:45449:52"/>
               <head>VI.</head>
               <l>Hîc <note n="g" place="bottom">Scil. <U+263F> ille decantatus Philo<U+017F>ophorum, anima vera Univer<U+017F>i.</note> 
                  <hi>Coeli influxus,,</hi> quo de<U+017F>cendente, fera<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Parturiens <U+017F>uccos, turge<U+017F>cit vena metalli</l>
               <l>Montibus in cel<U+017F>is, varios per vi<U+017F>ceraramos</l>
               <l>Divitis effingit Terrae, <note n="h" place="bottom">Proprium apud metallarios authores vocabulum, quo ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mu<U+017F>culi venae in varias partes <U+017F>e<U+017F>e ab arbore, <U+017F>ive trunco prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipuo, diffindentis <U+017F>ignificantur.</note> virga<U+017F>que repentes;</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="i" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Aurum granulatum, quale à primis</hi> Hi<U+017F>paniolae <hi>detectoribus <U+017F>ub Columbo, in meridionali parte In<U+017F>ulae circà</hi> Cibao, <hi>affatim in rivulis reperiebatur. ab Hi<U+017F>panis Scriptorib. operari<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap><U+017F>que</hi> Oro di pepone <hi>dictum, illudque optimum.</hi>
                  </note> Multa illîc liquido <U+017F>e proluit <hi>aurea</hi> rivo.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lamina</hi> nativi fugiens de germine trunci,</l>
               <l>Inficit &amp; tremulas flaventi lumine lymphas,</l>
               <l>Qualémque auricomus volvit <hi>Pactolus</hi> arenam:</l>
               <l>Hic quoque candentes <hi>argentea fodina</hi> venas,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="k" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Talis fui<U+017F><U+017F>e refertur a Scriptoribus Indicis nobilis illa</hi> Per<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viana argentifodina in Poto<U+017F>i, <hi>quùm primùm detecta in al <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                           <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
                        </gap> <U+017F>ublimatos puri metalli ramos protrudens; argumentum cert<gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> validum adver<U+017F>ùs vegetationem &amp; vitam metallorum negantes, &amp; principiis Peripateticis mordicùs nimiùm inhaerentes.</hi>
                  </note> Trudit in excel<U+017F>um, vegetóque cacumine <U+017F>urgit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:45449:53"/>
               <head>VII.</head>
               <l>Igneus hîc <hi>Adamas</hi> faelicis cortice glebae</l>
               <l>Delitet, hîc rutilos <hi>carbunculus</hi> exerit ignes,</l>
               <l>Hîc viridis mutat campos in prata <hi>Smaragdus</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Vilis ut in no<U+017F>tris mi<U+017F>cet <U+017F>e calculus agris:</l>
               <l>Hîc fallaci hamo, hîc urinatore remoto,</l>
               <l>Gemmea Choncharum proles ad littoris oras</l>
               <l>Sponte venit no<U+017F>tros nondùm docta <hi>unio</hi> luxus;</l>
               <l>Et quas arte parant <U+017F>plendenti è vellere Seres</l>
               <l>Regum delicias, animâ &amp; <U+017F>pirante mini<U+017F>trat</l>
               <l>Bombyx fila, <U+017F>uis pendent pa<U+017F><U+017F>im obvia Sylvis.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sapphyrus</hi> hîc &amp; parvus <hi>Onyx, Amethy<U+017F>tus</hi> &amp; ardens</l>
               <l>Inter <U+017F>axa micant, pul<U+017F>is &amp; gemma tenebris</l>
               <l>Incultis Phoebi radios imitatur in antris;</l>
               <l>Hîc in marmoreo ludens Natura <hi>Gagate,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Artificis <U+017F>uperat coelum, varii<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> coloris</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Opalus</hi> agnatos coeli ignibus excitat ignes,</l>
               <l>Et rutilis <U+017F>teriles flammis accendit arenas:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gemmea choncha</hi> natat pretio<U+017F>i in littoris Orâ</l>
               <l>Multa, adeóque frequens, grato ut nî vertice Sylvae</l>
               <l>Obtegerent, qui<U+017F>que hinc <U+017F>ibi conderet incola ca<U+017F>as.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="9">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:45449:53"/>
               <head>IX.</head>
               <l>Verùm hae quas infans vidit Natura<U+017F>ub Orbe</l>
               <l>Na<U+017F>centi, rerum &amp; primaevâ ab origine <U+017F>ylvae</l>
               <l>Cre<U+017F>centes, nullâque unquam violata <U+017F>ecuri</l>
               <l>Robora, tranquillas praebent cultoribus umbras,</l>
               <l>Sub viridi <U+017F>emper <U+017F>uadentique otia ramo:</l>
               <l>Nec tantùm ho<U+017F>pitibus placeant quae tecta <U+017F>uperbo</l>
               <l>Ad coelum tollunt vicina cacumina fa<U+017F>tu,</l>
               <l>Magnatum in<U+017F>anae moles, &amp; mentis &amp; artis</l>
               <l>Difficiles partus, ubi fulcit ja<U+017F>pida marmor,</l>
               <l>Quantùm haec, Ambro<U+017F>iis <U+017F>emper reclu<U+017F>a <U+017F>ub auris.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="10">
               <head>X.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cedrus</hi> odorato coelum propè vertice tangens</l>
               <l>Summa tenet, <hi>myrtú<U+017F>que</hi> humili pavimenta coronâ</l>
               <l>Cingit, &amp; exhalat precio<U+017F>i floris odores.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jel<U+017F>eminum</hi> auratis &amp; grata <hi>aurantia</hi> pomis,</l>
               <l>Hîc <U+017F>uavi Zephyros pa<U+017F><U+017F>im <U+017F>piramine mulcent;</l>
               <l>Nec filice aut flavis plus gaudent no<U+017F>tra geni<U+017F>tis</l>
               <l>Arva; hîc mille <U+017F>olo radiant circumundique flores.</l>
               <l>Mu<U+017F>aeu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">¯</g>mque exurgit opus quo terra <U+017F>uperbit,</l>
               <l>Ver<U+017F>icolore levis contecta &amp; gramine mu<U+017F>ci,</l>
               <l>Molliùs occurrit pedibus quàm vellera Serum.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="11">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:45449:54"/>
               <head>XI.</head>
               <l>Fertilis hîc genium terrae non vomer aratri</l>
               <l>Sollicitat, nàm <U+017F>ponte <U+017F>uas dat legibus almae</l>
               <l>Provida Naturae prae<U+017F>cripto tempore me<U+017F><U+017F>es;</l>
               <l>Hîc pa<U+017F><U+017F>im dulci <U+017F>aturatus tubere campus</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Patatae, Cocoque</hi> nucis dulcedine <U+017F>ylvae</l>
               <l>Exornant laetis innoxia fercula men<U+017F>is:</l>
               <l>Hîc <hi>Palmitae</hi> arbos nativo turgida <U+017F>ucco</l>
               <l>Corticeóque penu latices effundit amaenos,</l>
               <l>Nectareó<U+017F>que refert pomis onerata racemos</l>
               <l>E longè advecti compen<U+017F>ans munera Bachi.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="12">
               <head>XII.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Liber &amp; alma Ceres</hi> hîc dextrâ <U+017F>emper amicâ</l>
               <l>Muneribus terram faecundis <U+017F>ponte coronant,</l>
               <l>Ancipiti<U+017F>que <U+017F>pei amoto <U+017F>udore coloni,</l>
               <l>Exornant proprias votivis frugibus aras;</l>
               <l>Attamen hae cultore carent, quòd <U+017F>i addita cultrix</l>
               <l>Ars Genio foret ulla loci terrae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Vigori,</l>
               <l>Hîc adeò blandos demittunt <U+017F>ydera fluxus,</l>
               <l>Obrutus ut proprii palmes <U+017F>ub mole racemi</l>
               <l>Vix jàm maturae toleraret pondera prolis,</l>
               <l>Millenóque Ceres ditaret foenore <U+017F>ulcos.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="13">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:45449:54"/>
               <head>XIII.</head>
               <l>Sed quùm tàm largâ depromat munera dextrâ</l>
               <l>Sponte <U+017F>uâ Natura parens, &amp; divite cornu</l>
               <l>Nos beet, in<U+017F>ano quid nos potiora furore</l>
               <l>Quaerimus, &amp; fuco leges violamus avitas</l>
               <l>Artifici; prudens quas olim <U+017F>implice cultu</l>
               <l>Servandas, tenero Matris prae<U+017F>crip<U+017F>it amore?</l>
               <l>O hominum vanae mentes! obductáque caecis</l>
               <l>O nimiùm <U+017F>emper mortalia corda tenebris!</l>
               <l>Túque ô faelicis faelicior incola terrae;</l>
               <l>Cui <U+017F>atis e<U+017F>t natale <U+017F>olum, ambitione remotâ!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="14">
               <head>XIV.</head>
               <l>Illîc annorum <U+017F>eries longaeva tuorum</l>
               <l>Labitur, &amp; tacito <U+017F>ua per ve<U+017F>tigia cur<U+017F>u</l>
               <l>Fatorum ad metam faelicia <U+017F>tamina ducit</l>
               <l>Morborum involata lue, vel debilis aevi</l>
               <l>Ingratis vitiis, illîc reparata vigoris</l>
               <l>Corpora flore novo, nunquàm languore fati<U+017F>cunt:</l>
               <l>Inque <U+017F>uo tranquilla manet mens laeta rece<U+017F><U+017F>u,</l>
               <l>Officiique memor, caele<U+017F>ti ab origine lap<U+017F>ae</l>
               <l>Virgineo in cultu con<U+017F>ervat <U+017F>emina flammae,</l>
               <l>Pandorae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dolos &amp; tri<U+017F>tia munera temnit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="15">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:45449:55"/>
               <head>XV.</head>
               <l>Hîc juxtà Eô<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <U+017F>pirantes cinnama tractus,</l>
               <l>Antevenit primos perfu<U+017F>us odoribus ignes</l>
               <l>Aurorae Zephyrus, blanda &amp; <U+017F>u<U+017F>piria fundens,</l>
               <l>Aera per liquidum Florae <U+017F>patiatur in hortis;</l>
               <l>Florae hortis quorum per amaenas lillia valles</l>
               <l>Mi<U+017F>centur violis, &amp; <U+017F>uadent ducere <U+017F>ommos</l>
               <l>Floribus immixti fontes, aurae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> <U+017F>u<U+017F>urrus;</l>
               <l>Tótque adeò induxit campis Natura colores,</l>
               <l>Di<U+017F>tracta ut dubitent <U+017F>e<U+017F>e quò lumina vertant,</l>
               <l>Dùm <U+017F>ulcos nec ladit hyems, nec Syrius urit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="16">
               <head>XVI.</head>
               <l>Nunquàm hîc temperies annive evertitur ordo</l>
               <l>Grandine, vel nimbis, Boreâve immane furenti;</l>
               <l>A<U+017F>t inter virides, omnîque in tempore, ramos</l>
               <l>Garrula ponit avis nidum, proli<U+017F>que futurae</l>
               <l>Pignora cara <U+017F>uae <U+017F>ecurâ <U+017F>ervat in umbrâ:</l>
               <l>Indè <U+017F>uos cantus longis cum <U+017F>olibus aequat,</l>
               <l>Cantibus &amp; teneros querulis immi<U+017F>cet amores,</l>
               <l>Sic fugiente aevo, nullâque exterrita fraude:</l>
               <l>Quique animam in<U+017F>pirat <U+017F>ol, idem mille colores</l>
               <l>Effingens pennis, antè aurem lumina pa<U+017F>cit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="17">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:45449:55"/>
               <head>XVII.</head>
               <l>Hîc <U+017F>emper <hi>faecunda Thetys</hi> numero<U+017F>a natantum</l>
               <l>Agmina deducit, findentum caerula pinnâ</l>
               <l>Marmora pernici, liquidis dùm <U+017F>ingit in undis</l>
               <l>Squama nitens varios reflexâ luce colores,</l>
               <l>Grata quibus fulvi concedat lamna metalli;</l>
               <l>Illîc in liquidi laticis <U+017F>inuante recur<U+017F>u,</l>
               <l>Multus inaurato pi<U+017F>cis <U+017F>ub cortice tutus</l>
               <l>Delitet, &amp; facilem primò per lumina gu<U+017F>tum</l>
               <l>Sollicitat<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> <U+017F>en<U+017F>ú<U+017F>que adeò plus <U+017F>implice gaudet</l>
               <l>Objecto, atque homines Divûm ceu nectare pa<U+017F>cit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="18">
               <head>XVIII.</head>
               <l>Illîc quae duros alio <U+017F>ub <U+017F>ydere nautas</l>
               <l>Offendens nares au<U+017F>tero vellit odore,</l>
               <l>Doris amara <U+017F>uam non mi<U+017F>cet fluctibus undam;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ambara</hi> <U+017F>ed ripas agitato vortice pul<U+017F>ans</l>
               <l>Spumae in<U+017F>tar grato <U+017F>uffitu littora ditat;</l>
               <l>Plurima nativo'rubet hîc avul<U+017F>a cubili</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Arbor coralii</hi> Tyrio rutilantior o<U+017F>tro,</l>
               <l>Et ramo liquidos exornat divite <U+017F>ulcos;</l>
               <l>Queis contenta Thetys <U+017F>poliis, <U+017F>ibi plura recu<U+017F>at</l>
               <l>Quaerere naufragio, Boreae aut dite<U+017F>cere damnis.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="19">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:45449:56"/>
               <head>XIX.</head>
               <l>Hîc <hi>Ales</hi> proprios cui jus conce<U+017F><U+017F>it in annos</l>
               <l>Indulgens Natura, <U+017F>ui quique arbiter aevi</l>
               <l>Illudit fatis, nec decantata Sororum</l>
               <l>Curat pen<U+017F>atrium, quem non ni<U+017F>i carmine nobis</l>
               <l>Aut tabulis uovi<U+017F><U+017F>e datum: Vitae ille magi<U+017F>ter,</l>
               <l>Qui quùm vult rapidos vel <U+017F>i<U+017F>tit temporis orbes,</l>
               <l>Vel revocat, proprióque recens è funere <U+017F>urgit,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phoebi ales Phoenix,</hi> hîc tutam figere <U+017F>edem</l>
               <l>Quae<U+017F>iit antè alias quùm <U+017F>it placidi<U+017F><U+017F>ima terras,</l>
               <l>Omnis ubi dat <U+017F>ylva rogum dùm fata re<U+017F>arcit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="20">
               <head>XX.</head>
               <l>Hîc quóque non ficto coeli quae nomine dici</l>
               <l>Incola, quaeque <U+017F>uis <U+017F>edes aptare beatas</l>
               <l>Gaudet <hi>Apis</hi> titulis, <hi>Paradi<U+017F>i nobilis ales,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Corpore librato quae <U+017F>emper pendula nubes</l>
               <l>Pervolat, &amp; no<U+017F>trae fugiens contagia terrae,</l>
               <l>Acris ad libitum liquidi per inania fertur,</l>
               <l>Radicé<U+017F>que ip<U+017F>o rur<U+017F>ùs in aethere figit,</l>
               <l>Has aliis prudens terrarum praetulit oras,</l>
               <l>Coeli ubi concordes Naturae foedera <U+017F>ervant,</l>
               <l>Nec brumae Zephyros violant, nec nubila <U+017F>oles.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="21">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:45449:56"/>
               <head>XXI.</head>
               <l>Hîc velo amoto, <U+017F>ibi quae ceu <U+017F>omnia finxit</l>
               <l>Vulgi error, vanóque vetus quae carmine Vates,</l>
               <l>Ely<U+017F>io ad<U+017F>crip<U+017F>it mendax &amp; Fabula campo,</l>
               <l>Cernere vel tetigi<U+017F><U+017F>e licet, nec ficta voluptas</l>
               <l>Deliciis animum vanâ <U+017F>ub imagine ludit,</l>
               <l>Sempérque hîc objecta movent grati<U+017F><U+017F>ima <U+017F>enfus,</l>
               <l>Credere vix alio po<U+017F><U+017F>is quae vera loquenti;</l>
               <l>Quicquid &amp; Hesperidum celebratis credula pomis</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alcinoique</hi> hortis tribuit, rurique Beato</l>
               <l>Graecia, faelici hîc potior dat gleba colono.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="22">
               <head>XXII.</head>
               <l>Denique, decantata haec e<U+017F>t illa In<U+017F>ula Magno</l>
               <l>Quae quondam detecta <note n="a" place="bottom">Platoni de <hi>Atlantide in</hi> Timaeo tractanti.</note> Sopho, &amp; celebrata <note n="b" place="bottom">Senec. Tragaedo <hi>in Medeâ.</hi>
                  </note> Poëtae,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Atlantis</hi> non Ely<U+017F>iis ce<U+017F><U+017F>ura beatis,</l>
               <l>Quaeque ni<U+017F>i <hi>Alcidae no<U+017F>tro</hi> fit pervia nulli.</l>
               <l>Hùc procul à no<U+017F>tris fugit <hi>Pax Alma</hi> querelis</l>
               <l>Et pacata quies no<U+017F>tro vexata tumultu</l>
               <l>Otia tranquilli quaerens <U+017F>ecura rece<U+017F><U+017F>us,</l>
               <l>Undè Tibi comites cupient, <hi>Rex Magne,</hi> reverti</l>
               <l>Et <U+017F>ociam praebendo manum Tua Sceptra tueri</l>
               <l>Semper, &amp; aeternas Te juxtà ponere <U+017F>edes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="23">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:45449:57"/>
               <head>XXIII.</head>
               <l>Ergò age, <hi>Magnanime</hi> ô! <hi>Princeps,</hi> Tua fortibus urge</l>
               <l>Fata animis, tantas propera decerpere palmas,</l>
               <l>Sacraque legitimâ circumdare tempora lauro,</l>
               <l>Annuat ut ju<U+017F>tis mirans <hi>Europa</hi> triumphis:</l>
               <l>Miles eat, nutúmque tuum au<U+017F>piciúmque <U+017F>equatur;</l>
               <l>Túque ô! <hi>Cae<U+017F>areos</hi> Augu<U+017F>ti <U+017F>temmatis <hi>Avos</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Qui <U+017F>equeris meritis, &amp; cujus <U+017F>plendida virtus</l>
               <l>Fortunam <U+017F>uperavit ovans, Marti<U+017F>que pericla</l>
               <l>Sprevit inoffen<U+017F>o <U+017F>ua per ve<U+017F>tigia cur<U+017F>u,</l>
               <l>Con<U+017F>ilio dextrâque juva haec incepta <hi>Roberte!</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="24">
               <head>XXIV.</head>
               <l>Jam <U+017F>at Fama tuos, <hi>Princeps genero<U+017F>e,</hi> labores</l>
               <l>Multiloquâ <U+017F>par<U+017F>it Mundi per compita linguâ,</l>
               <l>Ac tua narrando propè jàm pulmone fati<U+017F>cit,</l>
               <l>Jàm tantum detrectat onus, nec facta referre,</l>
               <l>Nec dictis aequare potens, pernicior alis</l>
               <l>Fortior aut <U+017F>i voce foret; <U+017F>at nota, per Aulas</l>
               <l>Europae tua facta volant, <U+017F>empérque potenti</l>
               <l>Decantata tubâ Famae <U+017F>ine fine vigebunt:</l>
               <l>Jàm te<U+017F>tes tibi quaere novos, aliâque <U+017F>ub Arcto</l>
               <l>Et <U+017F>ub Sole novo, tua <U+017F>plendeat inclyta virtus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="25">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:45449:57"/>
               <head>XXV.</head>
               <l>Dùm tua <hi>Vexillis</hi> fuerint <U+017F>ociata <hi>Britannis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Arma, quibus <U+017F>e<U+017F>e <U+017F>emper Fortuna faventem</l>
               <l>Praebet, &amp; aeternas nectit Victoria palmas,</l>
               <l>Oceano rediet tandem reverentia legum</l>
               <l>Pri<U+017F>ca rena<U+017F>centum; <hi>Carolino Nomine</hi> tutus</l>
               <l>Ceu clypeo incedes, tempe<U+017F>tatúmque periclis</l>
               <l>Eripiêre, furens <U+017F>i quando minabitur Au<U+017F>ter:</l>
               <l>A<U+017F>tra tuis etiam ridebunt pro<U+017F>pera ceptis,</l>
               <l>Et tecum <hi>Pax alma redux &amp; Copia</hi> <U+017F>edes</l>
               <l>Hîc figent <U+017F>ibi perpetuas, illo orbe relicto.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:45449:58"/>
            <head>OCC<g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>RS<g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>S <hi>REGIS In TAMESI.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>Julio obeunte A. 1661.
Carmine extemporaneo con<U+017F>criptus hortatu Magnatis Anglici meriti<U+017F><U+017F>imi.
<hi>Et Illu<U+017F>tri<U+017F><U+017F>imo</hi> G<g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>ILLELMO <hi>C.</hi> DEVONIAE, <hi>Poë<U+017F>eos omni<U+017F>que politioris literaturae digni<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>imo Mecaenati optimóque judici, In ob<U+017F>ervantiae &amp; gratitudinis te<U+017F>timonium DICATUS.</hi>
               <hi>A Nunquám dignè <U+017F>atis amica in <U+017F>e collata officia &amp; beneficia per<U+017F>oluturo.</hi> P. D. C.</head>
            <l>VE<U+017F>pere <U+017F>ub tacito, liquidis in <hi>Tame<U+017F>is</hi> undis,</l>
            <l>Phoebus ad occiduas dùm properaret aquas;</l>
            <l>Commodiora viae fe<U+017F><U+017F>us compendia longae</l>
            <l>Quaerebam, &amp; <note n="*" place="bottom">Anglis proprio vocabulo <hi>a Skullor</hi> dictâ.</note> cymbâ paupere vectus eram:</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:45449:58"/>
Quùm <U+017F>ubitò Fluvium motos componere fluctus,</l>
            <l>Et virides ro<U+017F>eâ tingere luce comas</l>
            <l>Adverti, Nymphá<U+017F>que loci circumundique fu<U+017F>as</l>
            <l>Intrepido vultu carpere <U+017F>umma lacus:</l>
            <l>Ri<U+017F>erunt croceo <U+017F>plendentes lumine ripae,</l>
            <l>Flavit &amp; in<U+017F>olitò blandiùs aura <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>epens;</l>
            <l>Mille <U+017F>upervolitant cri<U+017F>patum flumen Amores,</l>
            <l>Auláque Nereïdum gemmea tota fuit.</l>
            <l>Attonitus reputo quâ vi, quo Numine, tales</l>
            <l>Extemplò <U+017F>ubeant aër &amp; unda vices;</l>
            <l>Quùm vox crebre<U+017F>cens ripae ad convexa, <U+017F>onoram</l>
            <l>Officio<U+017F>a Echôn <U+017F>ollicitando ferit.</l>
            <l>CAROLE viue diù, no<U+017F>trae, REX, gloria ripae,</l>
            <l>Vive diù Britici gloria magna <U+017F>oli!</l>
            <l>Per Te, moe<U+017F>ta olim, taciturna <U+017F>ilentia rumpens</l>
            <l>Jàm rediviva loquor <hi>CAROLE vive diù.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Undarum ingeminant Nymphae, plau<U+017F>ú<U+017F><expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> <U+017F>ecundos</l>
            <l>Ip<U+017F>a dedit Doris Nereidúmque cohors;</l>
            <l>CAROLE vive diù, no<U+017F>tri ipes <U+017F>ola Tridentis!</l>
            <l>Et Ro<U+017F>eae <hi>aeternus <U+017F>it tibi</hi> frondis <hi>honos!</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Nympha Tagi <hi>no<U+017F>tris aderit mox laeta choraeis,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Et Tua gaudebit nectere <U+017F>erta <U+017F>ibi.</l>
            <l>Protinùs obvertor: dùm CAROLUS, ecce, <U+017F>ecundo</l>
            <l>Findebat placidas flumine vectus aquas,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Fraterno</hi> <U+017F>olùm <hi>comitatu</hi> cinctus, apertâ</l>
            <l>Nabat &amp; in cymba <hi>dans <U+017F>ua jura Salo.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Ponè <U+017F>equebantur deauratâ puppe Mini<U+017F>tri,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Rex</hi> autem ligno <U+017F>implice vectus erat.</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:45449:59"/>
Tunc, pro more <U+017F>uo, <U+017F>ubridens fronte <U+017F>erenâ,</l>
            <l>In nos, ut tran<U+017F>it, lumina <U+017F>acra jacit.</l>
            <l>Cymba velox ae<U+017F>tum autevenit Magno Ho<U+017F>pite laeta,</l>
            <l>Remorúmque citô verbere pul<U+017F>a fugit.</l>
            <l>Non pernix Aquilae citiori penna volatu,</l>
            <l>Dùm praedam <U+017F>equitur, nubila cel<U+017F>a <U+017F>ecat:</l>
            <l>Non per caeruleos cur<U+017F>u tàm praepete <U+017F>ulcos</l>
            <l>Pinnarum remos Navita Pry<U+017F>tis agit;</l>
            <l>Non rapidos Delphin vincens conatibus Au<U+017F>tros,</l>
            <l>Non <U+017F>ubitam accelarans vi<U+017F>a colubra fugam;</l>
            <l>Signat longa viam gli<U+017F>centis linea cymbae,</l>
            <l>CAROLUS &amp; radians fulminis in<U+017F>tar abit:</l>
            <l>Vixque avido Illîus potuit Ve<U+017F>tigia ni<U+017F>u,</l>
            <l>Nereïdúmque cohors Doris &amp; ip<U+017F>a <U+017F>equi.</l>
            <l>En Deus ille, inquàm, prae<U+017F>ens en Numinis aura,</l>
            <l>Cujus am ant nutus aer &amp; unda <U+017F>acros.</l>
            <l>Verùm acies adeò celeri par luminis e<U+017F><U+017F>e</l>
            <l>No<U+017F>tra fugae nequiit, ce<U+017F><U+017F>it &amp; ip<U+017F>a dolens.</l>
            <l>Vocibus auditis ergò mea carmina mi<U+017F>cens</l>
            <l>Voce <U+017F>equor repetens, <hi>CAROLE vive diù:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Vivant jura Ro<U+017F>ae, rutilos dùm Cynthius ignes</l>
            <l>Condet, &amp; in <U+017F>al<U+017F>is exorietur aquis.</l>
            <l>Te modò <U+017F>ic videam (<U+017F>i plus mihi fata negârint)</l>
            <l>Saepiùs ô! cymbâ paupere vectus eam.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="note">
            <pb facs="tcp:45449:59"/>
            <head>Quicunque no<U+017F>tra Latinè dignabitur legere,.</head>
            <p>HIS paucis etiàm quae praefamur, pro <U+017F>olita Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>arum comitate, Mu<U+017F>as colentium humanitate, ne tanti<U+017F>per immorari dedignetur. Admonitum quippè illum cupimus, nos diù à Poetices (Latinae praecipuè, inter varios ob<U+017F>ervationum apices po<U+017F>itae) <U+017F>tudiis, per <U+017F>ortis iniquitatem avocatos (contrà votum carmina <U+017F>cribentium, quae <hi><U+017F>ece<U+017F><U+017F>um &amp; otia quaerunt)</hi> <U+017F>olo animi ardorè, <U+017F>olâ aemulatione inter Vota publica <hi>OPTIMO PRINCIPI,</hi> cum caeteris fidorum <U+017F>ubditorum, bono die bona verba dicendi, ad de<U+017F>ueta Parna<U+017F><U+017F>i munia revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catos, hoc quantulumcumque operis, oratione ver<U+017F>â, ut <U+017F>olennitatibus accommodatiori, è vernaculo no<U+017F>tro Gallico exara<U+017F><U+017F>e: I<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>circò Lectoris amici &amp; faventis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgentiam ambire, non doctorum <U+017F>everitatem criticam (<U+017F>ub quâ proculdubiò nobis laborandum foret) invitare. Illam obte<U+017F>tamur, amplectimur; hanc deprecamur. Non inficias euntes, praeter <U+017F>phalmata multa quae huic opu<U+017F>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo ex incuriâ Typographi irrep<U+017F>erunt, aliqua etiàm no<U+017F>tra Pro<U+017F>odiae leges violantia inventura iri. Sed quae <U+017F>peramus inventioni Poematis &amp; Carminis venu<U+017F>tati nihil <U+017F>ui precii detractura: quaedam <U+017F>i citiùs innotui<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ent, nec adeò tumultuariè, ac totum penè ip<U+017F>um opus prodire cogitur, effu<U+017F>a fui<U+017F><U+017F>ent, in meliùs (fateor) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutari poterant; quaedam verò ad propo<U+017F>itum adeò appo<U+017F>itè cadere vi<U+017F>a <U+017F>unt, ut verborum Empha<U+017F>im &amp; concinnitatem in Pro<U+017F>odiae gratiam inflectere, carmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<U+017F>que meliùs <U+017F>ic fluentis harmoniam pe<U+017F><U+017F>undare, quid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam immutando, nos poenitui<U+017F><U+017F>et. Condonet ergò, Lector <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc><1… pages missing></desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:45449:60"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>In the</hi> Fortunate I<U+017F>lands. <hi>Engli<U+017F>h.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 51. <hi>St.</hi> 1. Touch'd. <hi>l.</hi> Touch t. <hi>v.</hi> 6. were therein much concern'd, <U+017F>hould therein be concern'd. <hi>p.</hi> 57. <hi>St.</hi> XIII. or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trole with our art. <hi>l.</hi> or to controle with art.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Latin.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 65. <hi>Sl.</hi> II. <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>Terrarum nova Nereus adyta. l. loca Nereus abdita pandet. St.</hi> III. <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>Naturae, in quibu<U+017F>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">¯</g> Exempl. l. Nautae. p.</hi> 67. <hi>St.</hi> VI. <hi>v.</hi> 4. <hi>virga<U+017F>que repentes. l. tepentes. v.</hi> 9. <hi>argentea fodina venas. l. argentea vena fodinas. p</hi> 98. <hi>l.</hi> 68. <hi>St.</hi> VIII. <hi>v.</hi> 6. <hi>choncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. l. concharum. p.</hi> 69. <hi>St.</hi> X. <hi>v.</hi> 2. <hi>Myrtu<U+017F>que humili pavimenta. l. Myrthu<U+017F>que <U+017F>olum <U+017F>ub<U+017F>trata coronans. p.</hi> 17. <hi>l.</hi> 71. <hi>St.</hi> XIV. <hi>v.</hi> 4. <hi>Morborum involata lue. l. inviolata. p.</hi> 72. <hi>St.</hi> XV. <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>amaenas. l. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moenas. v.</hi> 10. <hi>Syrius. l. Sirius. p.</hi> 73. <hi>St.</hi> XVII. <hi>v. faecunda. l. foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunda. p.</hi> 74. <hi>St.</hi> XIX. <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>uovi<U+017F><U+017F>e. l. novi<U+017F><U+017F>e. St.</hi> XX. <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>l. Radice<U+017F><expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ip<U+017F><gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> rur<U+017F>us. l. quae rur<U+017F>ùs in aethere figit. p.</hi> 75. <hi>St.</hi> XXI. <hi>v.</hi> 6. <hi>grati<U+017F><U+017F>ima <U+017F>en<U+017F>us. l. grati<U+017F><U+017F>ima. p.</hi> 80. <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>Pry<U+017F>tis. l. pri<U+017F>tis.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:45449:60"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>

