<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A modern essay on the tenth satyr of Juvenal by Henry Higden, Esquire.</title>
            <title>Satura 10. English &amp; Latin</title>
            <author>Juvenal.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2007-01">2007-01 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46422</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J1278</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22431</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12743088</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12743088</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93159</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A46422)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93159)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 694:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A modern essay on the tenth satyr of Juvenal by Henry Higden, Esquire.</title>
                  <title>Satura 10. English &amp; Latin</title>
                  <author>Juvenal.</author>
                  <author>Dryden, John, 1631-1700.</author>
                  <author>Behn, Aphra, 1640-1689.</author>
                  <author>Settle, Elkanah, 1648-1724.</author>
                  <author>Higden, Henry.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 58, [10] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.M., and are to be sold by Randal Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>English text at upper part of pages; Latin text and notes at lower part of pages.</note>
                  <note>English annotations printed separately: p. [1-9] at end.</note>
                  <note>Preliminary material contains complimentary verses by Dryden, Mrs. Behn and E. Settle.</note>
                  <note>"Cato his answer to Labienus when he requested him to consult the oracle of Jupiter Ammon : being a translation of part of the 9th Book of Lucan ..": p. [9-10] at end.</note>
                  <note>A variant edition of this work, produced in 1687 with imprint: London : Printed by T.M. for the author, and sold by R. Bentley, Joseph Hindmarsh, John Newton, and by R. Taylor may be found on Reel 1486:2.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2005-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2005-10</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2006-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93159:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93159:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A
<hi>Modern E<U+017F><U+017F>ay</hi>
On the Tenth
SATYR
OF
JUVENAL.</p>
            <p>By HENRY HIGDEN, E<U+017F>quire.</p>
            <p>Licen<U+017F>ed June 2d. 1686. Ro. L'E<U+017F>trange.</p>
            <p>Ridendo Monet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi>
Printed by <hi>T. M.</hi> and are to be Sold by <hi>Randal Taylor</hi> near
<hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:93159:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93159:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable
RICHARD,
LORD
LUMLEY,
Baron of L<g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>MLEY,
AND
Vi<U+017F>count L<g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>MLET in Ireland, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THE Knowledge I have of Your Lord<U+017F>hips
Great Worth and Honour, is the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
that pu<U+017F>hes me to Publi<U+017F>h this
Piece under Your Lord<U+017F>hips Patronage,
who<U+017F>e Name and Character is <U+017F>o Illu<U+017F>trious, that it
was impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible for me to Re<U+017F>i<U+017F>t <U+017F>uch a Powerful
Attraction: But when I reflect on the <hi>Poorne<U+017F>s</hi> of the
<hi>Pre<U+017F>ent</hi> and <hi>Pre<U+017F>enter,</hi> and from thence advance my
Thoughts, to con<U+017F>ider the Grandeur of my Patron,
I di<U+017F>cover my Want of Ability to render You the
Ju<U+017F>t Attributes of your Merit: Who be<U+017F>ides Your
Lord<U+017F>hips Hereditary Vertues, po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s <U+017F>o many Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
acquired Ones, the Contemplation whereof
<pb facs="tcp:93159:3"/>
fills me with Raptures and Tran<U+017F>ports too Exqui<U+017F>ite
for a De<U+017F>cription. With this Impotence I wholly
de<U+017F>i<U+017F>t from a <hi>Panegyrick</hi> in this <hi>Epi<U+017F>tle,</hi> the general
Topick of Dedications, having <U+017F>o Ju<U+017F>t an Excu<U+017F>e for
the Want of Mine, which would be wholly unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F><U+017F>ary,
<U+017F>ince Your Lord<U+017F>hips Vertues are <U+017F>o Eminent
and Con<U+017F>picuous, they want neither a Herauld nor
an Hi<U+017F>torian.</p>
            <p>I was con<U+017F>cious to my Self (<hi>My Lord</hi>) of an unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable
piece of Confidence in this Addre<U+017F>s, in lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<U+017F>o <hi>Poor</hi> a <hi>Trifle</hi> at Your Lord<U+017F>hips Feet. But,
alas! What boots the Sen<U+017F>e of a Fault, without being
able to Re<U+017F>i<U+017F>t the Temptation of Committing it?
Be<U+017F>ides, the Con<U+017F>ideration that I was already Li<U+017F>ted
in the Gang of Scriblers, and commenced a Brother
of the Quill, who of all Mankind are the lea<U+017F>t apt
to have their Mode<U+017F>ty or Con<U+017F>cience fly into their
Faces: The Mu<U+017F>es them<U+017F>elves (under favour) being
thought but a <U+017F>ort of light Rambling Gyp<U+017F>ies; and
of <U+017F>o deep an <hi>Affrican</hi> Complexion, that they were never
ob<U+017F>erved to Redden, for all their daily Pre<U+017F>umptions
and Extravagancies; and Whipping (as Experience
has Taught us) does but rai<U+017F>e and provoke their
Mettle to more Waggi<U+017F>h Pranks. Do not we daily
<U+017F>ee, that the Lowe<U+017F>t Fluttering Dogrell <U+017F>hall with as
great an a<U+017F><U+017F>urance perch under a Noble Umbrage,
as the Highe<U+017F>t Soarer in Heroick Flights? The Carrion
Crow <U+017F>hall a<U+017F>pire to Build in the Cedar's Top, and
the Noble Eagle can pretend to no more. This
Hereditary Liberty allowed; as al<U+017F>o, That all Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<U+017F>ty
<pb facs="tcp:93159:3"/>
is directly again<U+017F>t the Rules of our Order,
and the Charter of our Company; And that the<U+017F>e
Cogent Poetical Rea<U+017F>ons being maturely weighed, may,
I hope, Warrant my Obedience to <hi>Custome,</hi> and
Apologize for a Trouble<U+017F>ome and Impertinent De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication;
to <U+017F>uffer in which Ca<U+017F>e will be for me
much more tolerable, than by my omitting <U+017F>o Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F><U+017F>ary
a Ceremony, provoke a Revengeful and Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
Brotherhood, that will a<U+017F><U+017F>uredly <hi>Damn me</hi> by a
Univer<U+017F>al Con<U+017F>ent, for pre<U+017F>uming to hope for Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
and to Stand and Fall by my own Merits,
without praying the A<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance of an able Patron,
according to the <hi>Laudable Custome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for this <hi>Tenth Satyr of Juvenal,</hi> by All approved
for the Grave<U+017F>t, and mo<U+017F>t <hi>Phylo<U+017F>ophical,</hi> both for Argument
and Matter, of all our Authors, (if his Sen<U+017F>e have
not lo<U+017F>t too much of the Spirit by Transfu<U+017F>ion from
one Language to another) I <U+017F>hould e<U+017F>teem a Suita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
Pre<U+017F>ent to Your Lord<U+017F>hip, who has Ju<U+017F>tly e<U+017F>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bli<U+017F>hed
a Noble and Spotle<U+017F>s Reputation from Worthy
and Hone<U+017F>t Actions: yet have Wi<U+017F>ely learnt betimes
to take up from a too eager and precipitate Cha<U+017F>e of
Fame, which Hurries many intemperately through
Thick and Thin, violently breaking through the Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
to pur<U+017F>ue and ma<U+017F>ter their Game; who often
(according to the many Examples in this <hi>Satyr</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>cribed)
do meet with a Di<U+017F>a<U+017F>terous Conclu<U+017F>ion,
which in them is the Effect of an Immoderate
Thir<U+017F>t and De<U+017F>ire of a Name; and does not proceed
from the Principles of Steddy Virtue. Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>hips
<pb facs="tcp:93159:4"/>
Wi<U+017F>er Con<U+017F>ideration having denyed Your Self to
the Court<U+017F>hip and Blandi<U+017F>hments of the World, rather
than to give the lea<U+017F>t Violence to your Mind and
Repo<U+017F>e; chu<U+017F>ing rather a Noble Retirement within
the Bounds of a Plentiful Fortune; of which few
Noble Men can boa<U+017F>t a Greater, or have given <U+017F>o
Early a <hi>Proof</hi> of their Knowledge and Skill to u<U+017F>e
and manage it to Improvement. Which that Your
Lord<U+017F>hip may live Long to enjoy with all Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s
and Honour, is the Con<U+017F>tant Wi<U+017F>h of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
               <signed>Your Lord<U+017F>hips Mo<U+017F>t Devoted,
Humble Servant,
HENRY HIGDEN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:93159:4"/>
            <head>To my Ingenious Friend,
M<hi rend="sup">R.</hi> Henry Higden, E<U+017F>q;
On his Tran<U+017F>lation of the
Tenth SATYR
OF
JUVENAL</head>
            <l>
               <hi>THe</hi> Grecian <hi>Wits, who</hi> Satyr <hi>fir<U+017F>t began,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Were Plea<U+017F>ant</hi> Pa<U+017F>quins <hi>on the Life of Man:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>At Mighty Villains, who the State oppre<U+017F>t,</l>
            <l>They dur<U+017F>t not Rail; perhaps, they Laugh'd at lea<U+017F>t,</l>
            <l>And turn'd 'em out of Office with a Jest.</l>
            <l>No Fool could peep abroad, but ready stand</l>
            <l>
               <hi>The</hi> Drolls, <hi>to clap a</hi> Bauble <hi>in his Hand:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Wi<U+017F>e</hi> Legi<U+017F>lators <hi>never yet could draw</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>A</hi> Fopp <hi>within the Reach of</hi> Common-Law;</l>
            <l>For Po<U+017F>ture, Dre<U+017F>s, Grimace, and Affectation,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Tho'</hi> Foes <hi>to</hi> Sence, <hi>are Harmle<U+017F>s to the</hi> Nation.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Our la<U+017F>t Redre<U+017F>s is Dint of</hi> Ver<U+017F>e <hi>to try;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>And</hi> Satyr <hi>is our</hi> Court <hi>of</hi> Chancery.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>This Way took</hi> Horace <hi>to reform an Age</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Not Bad enough to need an Author's Rage:</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:93159:5"/>
But Yours,<note n="*" place="margin">Juvenal.</note> who liv'd in more degen'rate Times,</l>
            <l>Was forc'd to fa<U+017F>ten Deep, and woorry Crimes:</l>
            <l>Yet You, my Friend, have temper'd him <U+017F>o well,</l>
            <l>You make him Smile in <U+017F>pight of all his Zeal:</l>
            <l>An Art peculiar to your Self alone,</l>
            <l>To joyn the Vertues of Two Stiles in One.</l>
            <l>Oh! were your Author's Principle receiv'd,</l>
            <l>Half of the lab'ring World wou'd be reliev'd;</l>
            <l>For not to Wi<U+017F>h, is not to be Deceiv'd!</l>
            <l>Revenge <hi>wou'd into</hi> Charity <hi>be chang'd,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Becau<U+017F>e it co<U+017F>ts too Dear to be</hi> Reveng'd:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>It co<U+017F>ts our</hi> Quiet <hi>and</hi> Content of Mind;</l>
            <l>And when 'tis compa<U+017F>s'd, leaves a Sting behind.</l>
            <l>Suppo<U+017F>e I had the better End o'th' Staff,</l>
            <l>Why <U+017F>hou'd I help th' ill-natur'd World to laugh?</l>
            <l>'Tis all alike to them, who gets the Day;</l>
            <l>
               <hi>They Love the Spight and Mi<U+017F>chief of the</hi> Fray.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>No; I have Cur'd my Self of that</hi> Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e;</l>
            <l>Nor will I be provok'd, but when I plea<U+017F>e:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>But let me half that</hi> Cure <hi>to You re<U+017F>tore;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>You gave the</hi> Salve, <hi>I laid it to the</hi> Sore.</l>
            <l>Our kind Relief again<U+017F>t a Rainy Day,</l>
            <l>Beyond a Tavern, or a tedious Play;</l>
            <l>We take your Book, and laugh our Spleen away.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>If all Your</hi> Tribe, (<hi>too studious of</hi> Debate)</l>
            <l>Wou'd cea<U+017F>e fal<U+017F>e Hopes and Titles to create,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Led by the</hi> Rare Example <hi>you begun,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Clyents <hi>wou'd fail, and</hi> Lawyers <hi>be undone.</hi>
            </l>
            <closer>
               <signed>JOHN DRYDEN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:93159:5"/>
            <head>TO Henry Higden, E<U+017F>q; On his Tran<U+017F>lation of the Tenth SATYR OF JUVENAL.</head>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>I Know You, and I mu<U+017F>t Confe<U+017F>s,</l>
               <l>From Sence <U+017F>o Celebrated, and <U+017F>o True,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wit</hi> <U+017F>o Uncommon, and <U+017F>o New,</l>
               <l>As that which alwaies <U+017F>hines in You;</l>
               <l>I cou'd expect no le<U+017F>s.</l>
               <l>'Tis <hi>Great,</hi> 'tis <hi>Ju<U+017F>t,</hi> 'tis <hi>Noble</hi> all!</l>
               <l>Right Spirit of the <hi>Original;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No <U+017F>catter'd Spark, no glimmering Beams,</l>
               <l>As in <U+017F>ome Pieces here, and there,</l>
               <l>Through a dark Glade of <hi>Duller Numbers</hi> gleams.</l>
               <l>But 'tis all <hi>Fire!</hi> all Glittering every where</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Grateful In<U+017F>truction</hi> that can never fail,</l>
               <l>To Plea<U+017F>e and Charm, even while you Rail.</l>
               <l>By <hi>Arts</hi> thus Gentle and Severe</l>
               <l>The <hi>Powers Divine</hi> fir<U+017F>t made their Mortals Wi<U+017F>e;</l>
               <l>The <U+017F>oft Reproach they did with Reverence bear;</l>
               <l>Whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e they Ador'd the <hi>GOD</hi> that did Cha<U+017F>tize.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>Perhaps there may be found <U+017F>ome <hi>Carping Wit,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>May blame the Mea<U+017F>ures of thy <hi>Lines,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And cry,—Not <U+017F>o the <hi>Roman</hi> Poet writ;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:93159:6"/>
Who dre<U+017F>t his <hi>Satyr</hi> in more lofty Rhimes.</l>
               <l>But thou for thy In<U+017F>tructer <hi>Nature</hi> cho<U+017F>e,</l>
               <l>That <hi>fir<U+017F>t</hi> be<U+017F>t Principle of <hi>Poetry;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And to thy Subject did<U+017F>t thy <hi>Ver<U+017F>e</hi> di<U+017F>po<U+017F>e,</l>
               <l>While in Harmonious Union both agree.</l>
               <l>Had the <hi>Great Bard</hi> thy <hi>Properer Numbers</hi> view'd,</l>
               <l>He wou'd have lay'd his <U+017F>tiff Heroicks by,</l>
               <l>And this more <hi>Gay,</hi> more <hi>Airy</hi> Path pur<U+017F>u'd,</l>
               <l>That <U+017F>o much better leads to <hi>Ralliery.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wit</hi> is no more than <hi>Nature</hi> well expre<U+017F>t;</l>
               <l>And He fatigues and toyles in vain</l>
               <l>With <hi>Rigid Labours,</hi> breaks his Brain,</l>
               <l>That has <hi>Familiar Thought</hi> in lofty Numbers dre<U+017F>t.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>True to his <hi>Sen<U+017F>e</hi> and to his <hi>Charming Wit,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou every where ha<U+017F>t kept an equal Pace:</l>
               <l>All his Brisk Turns exactly hit,</l>
               <l>Ju<U+017F>tly maintain'd his Humour and his Grace:</l>
               <l>And with the <hi>Language</hi> ha<U+017F>t not chang'd the Face:</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Juvenal</hi> in every Line,</l>
               <l>True <hi>Roman</hi> <U+017F>till o're all does <U+017F>hine;</l>
               <l>But in the <hi>Britti<U+017F>h</hi> Garb appears mo<U+017F>t fine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <l>Long did the <hi>Learned Author</hi> <U+017F>earch to find</l>
               <l>The Vice and Vanity of Humane-kind:</l>
               <l>Long he ob<U+017F>erv'd, nor did ob<U+017F>erve in vain;</l>
               <l>In every differing Humour found</l>
               <l>Even there where <hi>Virtue</hi> did abound,</l>
               <l>Some mortal Frailties reign.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Philo<U+017F>ophers</hi> he <U+017F>aw were Proud</l>
               <l>Of dull-affected Poverty.</l>
               <l>Senators cringing to the Crowd</l>
               <l>For trifling Popularity.</l>
               <l>The Judge Reviles the Criminal at <hi>Bar.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And now becau<U+017F>e old Ages Ice</l>
               <l>Has chill'd the Ardour of his willing Vice<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
               </l>
               <l>Snarles at tho<U+017F>e <hi>Youthful Follies</hi> which he cannot <U+017F>hare.</l>
               <l>From the vain-keeping <hi>'Squire<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
                  </hi> and Cully'd <hi>Lord;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The fawning <hi>Courtier, States-man</hi>'s Broken Word:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:93159:6"/>
Down to the flattering, Jilting <hi>Curtizan;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And the more faithle<U+017F>s couzening <hi>Citizen.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Tricks of <hi>Court</hi> and <hi>State</hi> to him were known;</l>
               <l>And all the Vices veil'd beneath the <hi>Gown:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From the Sharp <hi>Pulpit</hi> to the Blunted <hi>Stall,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He knew, and gently did reproach them all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>V.</head>
               <l>If <hi>Rome,</hi> that kept the le<U+017F><U+017F>er World in awe,</l>
               <l>Wanted a <hi>Juvenal</hi> to give them Law,</l>
               <l>How much more we, who <U+017F>tockt with <hi>Knave</hi> and <hi>Fool,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Have turn'd the Nation into <hi>Ridicule.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The dire Contagion <U+017F>preads to each degree</l>
               <l>Of Wild <hi>Debauchery.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The mad Infected Youth make ha<U+017F>te</l>
               <l>To lay their <hi>Fortunes, Health,</hi> and <hi>Rea<U+017F>on</hi> wa<U+017F>te:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Fop,</hi> a tamer <U+017F>ort of <hi>Tool,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who dre<U+017F><U+017F>es, talks, and loves, by Rule;</l>
               <l>Has long for a <hi>Fine Per<U+017F>on</hi> pa<U+017F>t.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Block-heads</hi> will pa<U+017F>s for <hi>Wits,</hi> and Write,</l>
               <l>And <U+017F>ome for <hi>Brave,</hi> who ne'r could Fight.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Women</hi> for <hi>Cha<U+017F>te,</hi> who<U+017F>e knack of <hi>Cant</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Boa<U+017F>ts of the <hi>Virtues</hi> that they want:</l>
               <l>Cry <hi>Faugh</hi>—at Words and Actions Innocent,</l>
               <l>And make that naughty that was never meant:</l>
               <l>That vain-affected <hi>Hypocrite</hi> <U+017F>hall be</l>
               <l>In <hi>Satyr</hi> <U+017F>ham'd to <hi>Hone<U+017F>t Sen<U+017F>e</hi> by Thee.</l>
               <l>'Tis Thou, our <hi>Engli<U+017F>h Juvenal,</hi> alone,</l>
               <l>To whom all <hi>Vice,</hi> and every <hi>Vertue</hi>'s known:</l>
               <l>Thou that like <hi>Judah</hi>'s King through all ha<U+017F>t pa<U+017F>t,</l>
               <l>And found that all's but <hi>Vanity</hi> at la<U+017F>t;</l>
               <l>'Tis you alone the <hi>Di<U+017F>cipline</hi> can u<U+017F>e,</l>
               <l>Who dare at once be <hi>bold, <U+017F>evere,</hi> and <hi>kind;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Soften rough <hi>Satyr</hi> with thy gentler <hi>Mu<U+017F>e,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And force a <hi>Blu<U+017F>h</hi> at lea<U+017F>t, where you can't change the Mind.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. Behn.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:93159:7"/>
            <head>TO
H. HIGDEN, E<U+017F>q;
On his Modern Way of Tran<U+017F>lating
JUVENAL'S
Tenth SATYR.</head>
            <l>IF <hi>Poets</hi> without Fiction in Applau<U+017F>e</l>
            <l>Of their lov'd <hi>Mu<U+017F>e</hi> <U+017F>peak Truth in their own Cau<U+017F>e;</l>
            <l>And Wit to <hi>Favourites</hi> gives a Lawful Claim,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>To be Inroll'd in Deathle<U+017F>s Books of</hi> Fame.</l>
            <l>Howe'er the Rest of the fam'd Si<U+017F>ters thrive,</l>
            <l>And happily to Time's la<U+017F>t Sand <U+017F>urvive,</l>
            <l>Satyr <hi>alone finds a Hard Task to live.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Even half a Key in th' highe<U+017F>t Flights of Glory,</l>
            <l>
               <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>nlocks whole Volumes of Heroick Story.</l>
            <l>Vertue <hi>in Robes of</hi> La<U+017F>ting <hi>Dye array'd,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Is down even to Remote<U+017F>t</hi> Time <hi>convey'd.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Great Deeds are Read <U+017F>o Plain, and <U+017F>poke <U+017F>o loud,</l>
            <l>Ca<U+017F>ting a Lu<U+017F>tre which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o Age can <U+017F>hroud;</l>
            <l>Her bright Divinity breaks through the Cloud.</l>
            <l>No Antique Garb can again<U+017F>t Worth prevail;</l>
            <l>Alcides <hi><U+017F>truts with Club and Lyons Tayl;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>And</hi> Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <hi>looks Great in Ruff and Farthingale.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Thus whil<U+017F>t</hi> Heroicks <hi>their Great</hi> Theams <hi>di<U+017F>play,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Stalking abroad in Fields and open Day:</l>
            <l>Remarking Satyr mu<U+017F>t to Coverts creep,</l>
            <l>Pry in clo<U+017F>e Grot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, and ob<U+017F>cure Clo<U+017F>ets peep.</l>
            <l>They Copy by <U+017F>o weak and faint a Light;</l>
            <l>Vice <hi>is their</hi> Theam, <hi>in</hi> Ma<U+017F>querade <hi>they Write,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And <U+017F>lyly walk in gloomy Scenes of Night;</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:93159:7"/>
Thus whil<U+017F>t the warm Intrigue is ju<U+017F>t found out</l>
            <l>And the fre<U+017F>h Calumny is dealt about,</l>
            <l>Murmur'd and buz'd through all the Tickled Rout:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Oh! with what Lawrel Wreaths is</hi> Satyr <hi>Crown'd!</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>How ravi<U+017F>hing the <U+017F>mart</hi> Iambicks <hi><U+017F>ound!</hi>
            </l>
            <l>But when the Grin, the Sneer, and Jest is pa<U+017F>t,</l>
            <l>(Malice <hi>that runs <U+017F>o <U+017F>wift, and tires as fa<U+017F>t)</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Poor</hi> Satyr <hi>then, the Nine Days Wonder done,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Strait lies Neglected, and Forgot as <U+017F>oon:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>With its own Parent,</hi> Scandal, <hi>does expire;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The generous <U+017F>on of an Ignoble Sire.</l>
            <l>The Poinant Gall that holds Authentick Text</l>
            <l>
               <hi>This Age, is damn'd t'</hi> Apocrypha <hi>the next.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>The Flowry Banks our plea<U+017F>ed</hi> Forefathers <hi>knew,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>O'regrown by Time, we a Rude Labyrinth view,</l>
            <l>Where Commentators groap without a Clue.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Whil<U+017F>t</hi> Satyr <hi>de<U+017F>tined to <U+017F>o Har<U+017F>h a Doom,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Must undergo <U+017F>uch</hi> Hard<U+017F>hip <hi>ev'n at Home;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Alas! what mu<U+017F>t it <U+017F>uffer when it walks</l>
            <l>Abroad, and in a Forreign Language talks!</l>
            <l>Where Loads of Dro<U+017F>s the precious Oar enfold,</l>
            <l>Skilful mu<U+017F>t th' Artist be t' Extract the Gold;</l>
            <l>
               <hi>One practi<U+017F>ed to the</hi> World <hi>and</hi> Mu<U+017F>es Laws,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>And well acquainted with the</hi> Face <hi>he draws.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Satyr <hi>to Trace at Heels, and poorly Line</hi>
            </l>
            <l>For Line Tran<U+017F>late, is <U+017F>uch a weak De<U+017F>ign,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Does even the</hi> Marks <hi>of</hi> Life, <hi>and</hi> Spirit <hi>want,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>A</hi> Jargon <hi>wor<U+017F>e than a</hi> Fanatick Cant:</l>
            <l>A Wi<U+017F>e Attempt, <hi>and Ju<U+017F>tify'd by none</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>But <U+017F>ome</hi> Enthu<U+017F>ia<U+017F>t Prophet <hi>of their own.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Thy</hi> Pencil <hi><U+017F>corns a Portraicture <U+017F>o faint:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Thou animate'<U+017F>t what <U+017F>uch dead Colours paint:</l>
            <l>You Naturalize the Author you Tran<U+017F>late,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>And</hi> Cla<U+017F><U+017F>ick Roman <hi>dre<U+017F>s in</hi> Modern State.</l>
            <l>Sprightly and Gay he makes his Vi<U+017F>it here;</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Dre<U+017F>t</hi> Al-a-mode, <hi>and <U+017F>peaks</hi> en Cavalier.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Great</hi> Juvenal's <hi>Wit, who in an</hi> Engli<U+017F>h <hi>Scene,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>By</hi> Time's <hi>long Ru<U+017F>t at be<U+017F>t had pointle<U+017F>s been,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Thou grind'<U+017F>t to a New Edge, to out more keen.</l>
            <l>From Letts and Rubbi<U+017F>h clear'<U+017F>t the craggy Shore,</l>
            <l>And driv'st thy own Triumphant Chariot o're.</l>
            <l>His di<U+017F>tant Heat does by thy Labour burn,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>And Rear thy</hi> Phenix <hi>from his Spicey <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>rne.</hi>
            </l>
            <closer>
               <signed>E. SETTLE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:93159:8"/>
            <head>THE
PREFACE
TO THE
READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I Did not think to have given you or my <U+017F>elf this Trouble, re<U+017F>olving what
I had <U+017F>aid before my</hi> Thirteenth Satyr <hi><U+017F>hould have <U+017F>erved the
Turn: But <U+017F>ince my Friend Mr.</hi> Shadwell, <hi>before his late Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious
Tran<U+017F>lation, has taken <U+017F>ome notice of this E<U+017F><U+017F>ay of mine, I
could not in good Manners, but make his Civility a Return in Print.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This</hi> Engli<U+017F>h <hi>E<U+017F><U+017F>ay of mine was Perfect, and Licen<U+017F>ed above a Year
<U+017F>ince, as intended to have been Printed in la<U+017F>t</hi> Trinity <hi>Term was Twelve-month,
but was by <U+017F>ome Accident prevented. In the following</hi> Vacation
<hi>Mr.</hi> Shadwell <hi>did me the Favour to peru<U+017F>e it, keeping it for a con<U+017F>idera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
Time by him: At the Return he told me, He had a mind to Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>late
it for his Diver<U+017F>ion, as liking the Author and Subject; which has
taken <U+017F>o good Effect, that I perceive the</hi> Younger Brother <hi>has by the</hi>
Common-Mother <hi>the</hi> Pre<U+017F>s <hi>out<U+017F>tript the</hi> Elder, <hi>and lurch'd him of the</hi>
Ble<U+017F><U+017F>ing: <hi>Which I <U+017F>hall not much bewail, <U+017F>ince I had not <U+017F>et my Heart
upon it: Nor will I blame his Ha<U+017F>te to Chri<U+017F>ten his Own Child fir<U+017F>t,
which is but the way of the World. But I thought it very hard, that
his Fondne<U+017F>s to his own way, <U+017F>hould make him (in crying up his own) fall
<U+017F>o <U+017F>everely upon all others; proclaiming his own for an Exact and Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard
Tran<U+017F>lation,</hi> clo<U+017F>e <hi>to the</hi> Words <hi>and</hi> Sence <hi>of the</hi> Author, <hi>which
mu<U+017F>t be <U+017F>o, le<U+017F>t it <U+017F>hould happen, (as he <U+017F>ays it does in all Paraphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>es)</hi>
That the Sen<U+017F>e and Spirit of the Author be quite deaded and
lo<U+017F>t; <hi>Adding further, that</hi> When any pre<U+017F>ume to Rank and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mix
their <U+017F>en<U+017F>e and thoughts with tho<U+017F>e of the Noble <hi>Roman</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors,
they look like Patches of homely Woollen on the Riche<U+017F>t
Silks; this Modern Age producing no <hi>Genius</hi> like theirs, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
their Imaginations mu<U+017F>t be Unequal, and <U+017F>hort of the Author's.
<pb facs="tcp:93159:8"/>
               <hi>A very fine Complement put upon this</hi> Age <hi>and</hi> Nation, <hi>which without
Vanity have produced</hi> Men <hi>Eminent and Learned in all</hi> Arts <hi>and</hi> Sciences,
<hi>and all manner of</hi> Learning, <hi><U+017F>urpa<U+017F><U+017F>ing the last preceding Ages, and
beyond the pitch of other Nations. And as for</hi> Poetry, <hi>being the matter
in Que<U+017F>tion, I will only in<U+017F>tance Mr.</hi> Cowley, <hi>who perhaps had as great
a</hi> Genius <hi>in all <U+017F>orts of</hi> Poetry, <hi>both</hi> Latin <hi>and</hi> Engli<U+017F>h, <hi>as any one of
the Ancients: But, it <U+017F>eems, he would Monopolize and Confine the</hi> Wit
<hi>of this Age (like the Caballi<U+017F>tical Learning of the</hi> Jews) to a Club
of his Acquaintance, who (<hi>it <U+017F>eems</hi>) are no profe<U+017F><U+017F>ed Poets, <hi>but choice
Spirits,</hi> and by much the greate<U+017F>t Wits in <hi>England, and <U+017F>o tran<U+017F>cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
others,</hi> that he thinks <hi>England</hi> never produced the like in any
Age.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This frank way of dealing with the</hi> World, <hi>and impo<U+017F>ing his own
Fancy for Laws on others, led me to con<U+017F>ider how my Friend had gone
through with the</hi> Irk<U+017F>ome drudgery <hi>of his Tran<U+017F>lation; and how his</hi>
Genius <hi>had comported with <U+017F>o mean an</hi> Imployment, <hi>not doubting but he
had nicely ob<U+017F>erved tho<U+017F>e Rules he had <U+017F>o Magi<U+017F>terially laid down for
others, and in Mode<U+017F>ty had forborn to mingle any Thought of his own
with his</hi> Noble Roman Author, <hi>which might po<U+017F><U+017F>ibly nau<U+017F>eate our
stomachs</hi> like Wine of two ta<U+017F>ts; <hi>pre<U+017F>uming he had <U+017F>urpa<U+017F><U+017F>ed the
Elaborate Tran<U+017F>lations of</hi> Stapleton <hi>and</hi> Holliday; <hi>of which I will not
pretend to judge: When upon Peru<U+017F>al, I found he had not <U+017F>trictly followed
his Author, but made bold to</hi> Paraphra<U+017F>e <hi>and Embroider his Author's</hi>
Rich Silken <hi>Garment with</hi> homely Woollen Patches <hi>of his own, I <U+017F>hall
in<U+017F>tance only in four Ver<U+017F>es, being the fir<U+017F>t that came to Hand, the two
fir<U+017F>t taken out of his Son's Tran<U+017F>lation of</hi> Cato's <hi>Speech, printed before
his Tran<U+017F>lation; the later two Ver<U+017F>es being in the Fir<U+017F>t Page of his</hi> Satyr,
<hi>and printed with a different Character, to denote <U+017F>omething extraordinary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In</hi> Cato's <hi>Speech:</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Haeremus Cuncti <U+017F>uperis:</l>
               </q> 
               <hi>which he renders thus:</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>We all on God, as parts of him, depend;</l>
                  <l>There does the Mighty Chain begin and end.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now I would have our nice Tran<U+017F>lator point out where the Author <U+017F>o
much as hints any thing of this</hi> Mighty Chain; <hi>or in<U+017F>truct his tolerable</hi>
Grammarian <hi>where to find it: which</hi> Chain <hi>mu<U+017F>t (like</hi> Jacob's <hi>Ladder</hi>)
<hi>be</hi> Mighty <hi>enough to reach from Earth to Heaven: Of which I can find
no more in our Author, than of a</hi> Cable <hi>or</hi> Sheet-Anchor. <hi>Be<U+017F>ides, it will
allow of a Di<U+017F>pute, whether God has any Parts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other In<U+017F>tance is in the Fir<U+017F>t Page of his Satyr:
<q>
                  <l>Cantabit vacuus coram latrone viator.</l>
               </q>
Which he Tran<U+017F>lates thus:
<q>
                  <l>While the Poor man void of all Precious things,</l>
                  <l>In company of Thieves, joggs on and <U+017F>ings.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which Mr.</hi> Holliday <hi>has more truly and comprehen<U+017F>ively tran<U+017F>lated in
One Ver<U+017F>e, thus:</hi>
               <q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:93159:9"/>
Before the Thief, who travels empty, Sings.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There was no nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity the Authors Traveller <U+017F>hould be a</hi> Poor Man;
<hi>for if he had nothing of Value about him, he might <U+017F>ing without Fear,
though he were Wealthy at home: And if we allow him a</hi> Poor Man
<hi>we might gue<U+017F>s he was</hi> Void of all Precious things. <hi>Which word</hi> Void
<hi>is very <U+017F>eldome u<U+017F>ed in the <U+017F>ence there intended: May be the</hi> Poor Man
voided his precious <hi>Stones long before he came into the Thieves Company,
that the Capon might <U+017F>ing the <U+017F>weeter in his Journey. Be<U+017F>ides, I can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
nothing in the Author that warrants that Heroick Phra<U+017F>e,</hi> (joggs on.)
<hi>The Author's meaning is, that the empty Traveller having no cau<U+017F>e of
fear, might <U+017F>ing before the</hi> Thief: <hi>Yet there is no nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity he <U+017F>hould</hi>
Jog on in Company of Thieves, <hi>who perhaps had other De<U+017F>igns on foot,
than to li<U+017F>ten to his Melody. But I <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e, the next time he will mend
his Hand, and not brew and da<U+017F>h his Ver<U+017F>e, till 'tis like</hi> Wine of two
la<U+017F>ts, <hi>that when we have pallated the New, we <U+017F>hall have no rea<U+017F>on to <U+017F>ay
the Old is better. Let</hi> Milo <hi>in the Satyr be an Example to him, not
to pre<U+017F>ume too much on his own <U+017F>trength, de<U+017F>pi<U+017F>ing others, le<U+017F>t being wedged
in a trap of his own making, he become a Prey to the mercile<U+017F>s Criticks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And thus much I thought my <U+017F>elf obliged to <U+017F>ay upon this occa<U+017F>ion, <U+017F>ince
the</hi> Tran<U+017F>lator <hi>was not only content <U+017F>tyly to top his Tran<U+017F>lation upon his</hi>
Friend; <hi>but by way of Anticipation, would arrogantly cry down all but his
own Tran<U+017F>lation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I <U+017F>hould now <U+017F>ay <U+017F>omething for this</hi> E<U+017F><U+017F>ay <hi>of mine, which I never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>igned
for a just Tran<U+017F>lation, though I have alwaies kept the Author in
my Eye, and not willingly rambled too far from him, (except in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>cription
of the Praetor and his Equipage) which was too <U+017F>tubborn to work
into my Ver<U+017F>e, endeavouring to make his <U+017F>ence,</hi> Engli<U+017F>h, <hi>and <U+017F>uch as is
now currant; All</hi> Satyr <hi>having a <U+017F>trong ta<U+017F>te of the Humour and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
Hints of the Times wherein they were writ, which is indeed the Life
and Beauty of</hi> Satyr. <hi>And I am the more confirmed in the Opinion of my
way, <U+017F>ince I have read a Verbal Tran<U+017F>lation, done by <U+017F>o able a hand as
Mr.</hi> Shadwell's. <hi>In mine I have rather imitated that Admirable Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>lation
of</hi> Quevedo, <hi>that gives Life and Spirit to his</hi> Author, <hi>by making
him</hi> Engli<U+017F>h, <hi>in a Modi<U+017F>h and Familiar way, which I hope you will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove
of, and excu<U+017F>e</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. HIGDEN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="authors_note">
            <p>I have in the End of the Book Printed a New Tran<U+017F>lation
of <hi>Cato</hi>'s Speech in <hi>Lucan,</hi> done, and <U+017F>ent me by an unknown
Hand, though in the Printing it has met with <U+017F>ome alterations:
For which, I beg the Author's Pardon; <U+017F>ubmitting his <hi>Poem</hi> and
my <hi>Satyr</hi> as Foyls to Mr. <hi>Shadwell</hi>'s; being de<U+017F>irous to Play
one Fragment again<U+017F>t another.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="satire">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93159:9"/>
            <head>JUVENAL's
TENTH
SATYR,
Made Engli<U+017F>h.</head>
            <l>SUrvey Mankind, (1) mu<U+017F>ter the Herd</l>
            <l>From <U+017F>moothe<U+017F>t Chin to deepe<U+017F>t Beard;</l>
            <l>Search every Climate, view each Nation,</l>
            <l>from lowe<U+017F>t to the highe<U+017F>t Station;</l>
            <l>From Ea<U+017F>tern to the We<U+017F>tern <hi>Indies,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>From frozen <hi>Poles</hi> to'th <hi>Lyne</hi> that <U+017F>indges:</l>
            <l>Scarce will you find one Mortal Wight</l>
            <l>Knows <hi>Good</hi> from <hi>Ill,</hi> or <hi>Wrong</hi> from <hi>Right,</hi>
            </l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="bottom">OMNIBUS. Tanta e<U+017F>t humanae mentis coecitas, ut in toto orbe vix ab ortu Solis u<U+017F>que ad occa<U+017F>um, pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci<U+017F><U+017F>imi inveniantur, qui vera bona, a malis po<U+017F><U+017F>int di<U+017F>cernere, vel quid <U+017F>it <U+017F>ecundum rationem fugiendum quid petendum.</note> Omnibus in terris quae <U+017F>unt a<note n="b" place="bottom">GADIEUS. In<U+017F>ula nunc Cadiz vocata, in <U+017F>itore Hi panico <U+017F>ita, ultra fretum olim Herculeum dic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, hodie angu<U+017F>tiae de Gibralter; hic Poetae Herculem duas Columnas <U+017F>tatui<U+017F><U+017F>e volunt: Extremum occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentem credebant antiqui unde Elogium Herculis Columnis in<U+017F>eriptum. NE PLUS ULTRA.</note> Gadibus u<U+017F>que</l>
               <l>Auroram<note n="c" place="bottom">GANGEM. Nobili<U+017F><U+017F>imum Indiae orientalis Fluvium.</note> &amp; Gangem, pauci digno<U+017F>cere po<U+017F><U+017F>unt</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="bottom">VERA BONA. Quae animi tantum <U+017F>unt, uti Virtus, Ju<U+017F>titia, &amp; vitae integritas, quae fracta Nave cum nudo Po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>ore enatare po<U+017F><U+017F>int.</note> Vera bona,</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:93159:10"/>
'Cau<U+017F>e clouds of Lu<U+017F>t and Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion blind</l>
            <l>And bri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e with Intere<U+017F>ts our Mind;</l>
            <l>And while they Combat in our heart,</l>
            <l>Our Fondne<U+017F>s crowns the conqu'ring part.</l>
            <l>What is the thing under the Sun,</l>
            <l>That we with Rea<U+017F>on <U+017F>eek or <U+017F>hun?</l>
            <l>Or Ju<U+017F>tly by our Judgment weigh'd,</l>
            <l>Should make us fond of, or afraid?</l>
            <l>What 'ere is luckily begun</l>
            <l>Brings <U+017F>ure Repentance at long-run.</l>
            <l>The di<U+017F>tant Object loomeing great,<note place="margin">A term of Art at Sea, <U+017F>ignifying the appearance of a Ve<U+017F><U+017F>el at a di<U+017F>tance</note>
            </l>
            <l>Po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>t, proves oft an empty Cheat;</l>
            <l>And he who wins the wi<U+017F>h't for prize</l>
            <l>A trouble often dearly buyes.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>—a'que illis multum diver<U+017F>a, remota</l>
               <l>Erroris nebulâ, quid enim ratione timemus</l>
               <l>Aut cupimus? Quid tam<note n="a" place="bottom">DEXTRO PEDE: Quid tam dextro vel pro<U+017F>pero au<U+017F>picio a Dijs petis, concupis &amp; precaris, ut non olim tuae petitionis &amp; voti te poeniteat. Dextra cum erant numina favere credebantur, Laeva contra</note> dextro pede concipis, ut te</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="bottom">CONATUS: Contentionis, appetiis, de<U+017F>iderij.</note> 
                  <hi>Conatus non poeniteat, votique peracti?</hi>
               </l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93159:10"/>
Some for their Family importune</l>
            <l>And beg their ruin for a Fortune.</l>
            <l>The Courteous Gods granting their Prayers,</l>
            <l>Have intayl'd Cur<U+017F>es on their Heirs.</l>
            <l>Of Wizards <U+017F>ome inquire their doom</l>
            <l>Greedy to know Events to come</l>
            <l>And by their over Caution run</l>
            <l>On the <U+017F>ame Fate they <U+017F>trove to <U+017F>hun:</l>
            <l>Some have petition'd to be great</l>
            <l>And eminent in Church and State;</l>
            <l>This in the Warrs a famous Leader,</l>
            <l>T'other at Bar a cunning Pleader,</l>
            <l>The Cau<U+017F>e on either <U+017F>ide en<U+017F>ure yee,</l>
            <l>By dint of noy<U+017F>e <U+017F>tun Judge and Jury:</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>Evertere domus totas opt antibus ip<U+017F>is</l>
               <l>Dij faciles: nocitura Toga, nocitura a petuntur</l>
               <l>Militia.<note n="a" place="bottom">EVERTERE: Dij prompti ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis &amp; faciles ad largiendum, &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>equendum votis hominum impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunis, dum dant hominibus mala &amp; noxia petentibus totas domus &amp; familias fuas perdiderunt, etiam optan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus ip<U+017F>is dominis.</note> torrens<note n="b" place="bottom">TORRENS: Eloquentia abundans, &amp; Torrentis in<U+017F>tar fluens, multis exitium tulit, ut Ciceroni &amp; Demo<U+017F>theni: ut infra v. 1140.</note> dicendi copia multis,</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:93159:11"/>
And if the bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s won't bear water</l>
            <l>Then banter and perplex the matter.</l>
            <l>But their ob<U+017F>trep'rous Eloquence</l>
            <l>Has fail'd ev'n in their own defence;</l>
            <l>And <U+017F>aving others by Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>anguing</l>
            <l>Have brought them<U+017F>elves at la<U+017F>t to hanging.</l>
            <l>(2) <hi>Milo</hi> pre<U+017F>uming on his <U+017F>trength</l>
            <l>Caus'd his own de<U+017F>tiny at length.</l>
            <l>The greedy care of heaping Wealth</l>
            <l>Damns many a Soul and ruins Health,</l>
            <l>And in an Apoplectick Fitt</l>
            <l>Sinks them down right into the pitt.</l>
            <l>How many Up<U+017F>tarts crept from low</l>
            <l>Condition, va<U+017F>t po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>ions <U+017F>how?</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>Et <U+017F>ua mortifera e<U+017F>t Facundia. Viribus ille</l>
               <l>Confi<U+017F>us periit admirandi<U+017F>que lacertis.</l>
               <l>Sed plures<note n="a" place="bottom">NIMIA: Cura in divitiis accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulandis <U+017F>trangulat, opri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it <U+017F>uffo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat, dum omni ratione laborant, ut <U+017F>uus cen<U+017F>us tanto excedat aliorum cen<U+017F>us, quanto balaena Britanica ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>uperat delphinam mole.</note> nimia conge<U+017F>t a pccunia cura</l>
               <l>Strangulat, &amp; cuncta exuperans patrimonia cen<U+017F>us</l>
               <l>Quanto delphinis balaena Britanica major.</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:93159:11"/>
Who<U+017F>e E<U+017F>tate's audit <U+017F>o immen<U+017F>e</l>
            <l>Exceeds all Prodigal Expence.</l>
            <l>With which compare that Spot of Earth,</l>
            <l>To which the<U+017F>e Mu<U+017F>hroms owe their Birth:</l>
            <l>Their Mannours to Dads Cottage <U+017F>how,</l>
            <l>As Greenland Whales to Dolphins do.</l>
            <l>In (3) <hi>Neroe</hi>'s Plotting di<U+017F>mal times</l>
            <l>Riches were judg'd <U+017F>ufficient Crimes.</l>
            <l>Fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>wear them Traytors to the State,</l>
            <l>Then for their pains <U+017F>hare their E<U+017F>tate.</l>
            <l>Fat forfeitures their Toyles reward:</l>
            <l>Poor Rogues may pa<U+017F>s without regard.</l>
            <l>Some are hook'd in for Sen<U+017F>e and Wit,</l>
            <l>And <U+017F>ome Condemn'd for want of it.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>Temporibus diris igitur, ju<U+017F><U+017F>uque<note n="a" place="bottom">
                     <p>NERONIS: Nero undique oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca<U+017F>ione quae<U+017F>ita, divitum opibus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>idiabatur &amp; diris illis &amp; Tyrani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis temporibus Imperatore jubente, tota Cohors militum percu<U+017F><U+017F>orum clau<U+017F>it Longinum &amp; Senecae praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitis hortos, et aedes divitum Lateranorum ut divitias <U+017F>uas cum vita adimeret. Exempla illa fune<U+017F>ta demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>trant, divitias multis exitiales fai<U+017F><U+017F>e.</p>
                     <p>LATERANORUM. Plautii Laterani quem inter<U+017F>ici etiam ju<U+017F><U+017F>it Nero.</p>
                  </note> Neronis,</l>
               <l>Longinum, et magnos Senecae praedivitis hortos</l>
               <l>Clau<U+017F>it, et Egregias Lateranorum ob<U+017F>idet aedes</l>
               <l>Tota cohors.</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:93159:12"/>
The over-rich <hi>Longinus</hi> (4) dyes:</l>
            <l>His bright heaps daz'led Envious eyes.</l>
            <l>Neither could deep Philo<U+017F>ophy,</l>
            <l>Wi<U+017F>dome, de<U+017F>ert, or Piety</l>
            <l>Rich <hi>Seneca</hi> (5) from his Pupil <U+017F>ave,</l>
            <l>'Tis fit he <U+017F>end him to a Grave,</l>
            <l>And then re<U+017F>ume the wealth he gave.</l>
            <l>The Guards the Pallaces be<U+017F>et,</l>
            <l>For Noble Game they pitch their net:</l>
            <l>While from Alarms and Pangs of fear,</l>
            <l>Securely <U+017F>leeps the Cottager.</l>
            <l>If you by night <U+017F>hall happen late,</l>
            <l>To Travail with a Charge of Plate;</l>
            <l>With watchful eyes and panting heart,</l>
            <l>Surpriz'd, each Object makes you Start:</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="bottom">RARUS. Miles vel perou<U+017F><U+017F>or ju<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>u Neronis Ratus in pauperuin ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ulas &amp; caenacula venit, ut eos <U+017F>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liet vel trucidet.</note> Rarus venit in canacula miles.</l>
               <l>Panca licet portes argenti va<U+017F>cula puri,</l>
               <l>Nocte iter ingre<U+017F><U+017F>us, gladium contum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tiniebis:</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:93159:12"/>
While Rack'd with doubts, oppre<U+017F>t with fear,</l>
            <l>Each Bu<U+017F>h does an arm'd Thief appear:</l>
            <l>A <U+017F>haken reed will Terrour Strike,</l>
            <l>Mi<U+017F>taken for a brandi<U+017F>h'd Pike.</l>
            <l>Before the Thief, the empty Clown</l>
            <l>Sings unconcern'd and Travailes on.</l>
            <l>With warm Petitions mo<U+017F>t men ply</l>
            <l>The Gods, their Baggs may multiply;</l>
            <l>That riches may grow high and ranck</l>
            <l>Out <U+017F>welling others in the Bank.</l>
            <l>But from plain wood and earthen Cupps,</l>
            <l>No poy<U+017F>on'd draught the Pea<U+017F>ant <U+017F>upps.</l>
            <l>Of the Gold Goblet take thou care,</l>
            <l>When <U+017F>parkling wine's <U+017F>pic'd by thy heir:</l>
            <l>Et motae ad Lunam trepidabis arundinis umbram.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="bottom">CANTABIT: Securo animo e<U+017F>t, cui nihil e<U+017F>t, nihil au<U+017F>erri po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<U+017F>t; illis autem Maxime timendum quibus Maximae divitiae.</note> Gantabit vacuus coram latrone viator.</l>
               <l>Prima fere vota, &amp; cunctis noti<U+017F><U+017F>ima Templis</l>
               <l>Divitiae, cre<U+017F>cant ut cpes, ut maxima toto</l>
               <l>No<U+017F>tra <U+017F>it arca<note n="b" place="bottom">FORO: Trajano <U+017F>cil ubi Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores et ditiores arcas habebant, in quibus argentum &amp; pecuniam tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius di<U+017F>ponebant.</note> foro. Sed nulla aconita bibuntur</l>
               <l>Fictilibus: tunc illa time, cum pocula <U+017F>umes</l>
               <l>Gemmata &amp; lato<note n="c" place="bottom">SENTINUM vinum <U+017F>entinum flammei erat coloris in auratis po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis.</note> <U+017F>entinum ardebit in auro.</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:93159:13"/>
Then who can blame that brace of <hi>Wi<U+017F>emen</hi>
            </l>
            <l>That did in diffring moods de<U+017F>pi<U+017F>e men:</l>
            <l>Th' old merry Lad <U+017F>aunters the Streets,</l>
            <l>And laughs, and drolls at all he meets:</l>
            <l>For Pa<U+017F>time rallys, flouts, and fools 'em,</l>
            <l>Shamms, banters, mimicks, ridicules 'em.</l>
            <l>The other Sage in maudling wi<U+017F>e,</l>
            <l>Their Errors mourns with weeping Eyes.</l>
            <l>Dull Fools with ea<U+017F>e can grin and <U+017F>neere,</l>
            <l>And Buffoons flout with <U+017F>awcy jeere.</l>
            <l>What <U+017F>owrce could con<U+017F>tant Tears <U+017F>upply,</l>
            <l>To feed the <U+017F>luces of each Eye!</l>
            <l>Or t'others merry humour make,</l>
            <l>His <U+017F>pleen continually to <U+017F>hake?</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>Jamne igitur laudas quod de <U+017F>apientibus<note n="a" place="bottom">ALTER. Democritum Abde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critam philo<U+017F>ophum intellige qui <U+017F>emper <U+017F>tultitias &amp; Ineptias ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum ridebat.</note> alter</l>
               <l>Ridebat, quoties de limite moverat unum</l>
               <l>Pretulerat que <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>edem; Flebat contrarius<note n="b" place="bottom">ALTER. Heraclitus Ephe<U+017F>ius notatur qui <U+017F>emper hominum dementiam et mi<U+017F>erias deflebat.</note> alter:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="c" place="bottom">SED. Jam ho<U+017F>ce: duos contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rios Adfectus inter <U+017F>e comparat demon<U+017F>trans in promptu e<U+017F>t ride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re: <U+017F>ed mirum unde Heraclito <U+017F>uppeteret tanta Lachrymarum co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia.</note> <U+017F>ed facilis cuivis rigidi cen<U+017F>ura cachinni.</l>
               <l>Mirandum e<U+017F>t unde ille oculis <U+017F>uffecerit Humor.</l>
               <l>Perpetuo ri<U+017F>u pulmenem agitare <U+017F>olebat</l>
               <l>Democritus—</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:93159:13"/>
Since the rude <hi>Thracian</hi> in his City</l>
            <l>Ne're <U+017F>aw proce<U+017F><U+017F>ion half<U+017F>o pretty,</l>
            <l>As modern Pageantry and State</l>
            <l>Does on our City-Triumphs wait;</l>
            <l>Than which no Interlude is gayer,</l>
            <l>Whil<U+017F>t Sword and Cap u<U+017F>her the Mayor;</l>
            <l>A Cap that does with Heads di<U+017F>pen<U+017F>e</l>
            <l>Without regard of Brains or Sen<U+017F>e:</l>
            <l>And who<U+017F>e my<U+017F>terious Power tran<U+017F>lates</l>
            <l>Mechanick Furs to Potentates,</l>
            <l>From weighing Plumbs, to ballance States.</l>
            <l>So Mayor and Aldermen from Stalls</l>
            <l>Wi<U+017F>er than Pope<note n="*" place="margin">L. Ch. J. <hi>Scroggs</hi> at Je<U+017F>uits Tryal.</note> and Cardinals,</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>—quanquam non e<U+017F><U+017F>ent <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>rbibus illis</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="bottom">PRAETEXTA, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Poeta hic e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerat Ornamenta Regalia &amp; cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tera in<U+017F>ignia Romani Praetoris.</note> Praetexta, &amp; trabeae, fa<U+017F>ces, lectica, Tribunal.</l>
               <l>Quid <U+017F>i vidi<U+017F><U+017F>et Praetorem Curribus altis</l>
               <l>Extantem et medio <U+017F>ublimem in Pulvere Circi</l>
               <l>In Tunica Jovis,</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:93159:14"/>
From Shop to Bench with in<U+017F>pired Noddle</l>
            <l>The Body Politick does waddle;</l>
            <l>Where Pre<U+017F>ident mute Judge hears Cau<U+017F>e</l>
            <l>That Statute never read nor Laws.</l>
            <l>So <hi>Rablais</hi> Gown conveys his <U+017F>pirit</l>
            <l>To all <U+017F>ucceeding Quacks that wear it.</l>
            <l>Thus Furs, more proud than Ermyn, mu<U+017F>ter,</l>
            <l>Gilt Jack-Chains give the Faction Lu<U+017F>ter;</l>
            <l>Whil<U+017F>t the whole Livery attend,</l>
            <l>Banners and Trophies without end:</l>
            <l>Of honour'd Gue<U+017F>ts a Cavalcade</l>
            <l>Who<U+017F>e Friend<U+017F>hip by the Treat is made;</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>—&amp;<note n="a" place="bottom">PICTAE: in palmata trabea, id e<U+017F>t in picta &amp; triumphali toga quam ex templo Jovis fumptam indue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant.</note> pictae Sarrana ferentem</l>
               <l>Ex humeris<note n="b" place="bottom">AULAEA Sarrana, <U+017F>atyrice <U+017F>io Dictum, <U+017F>araiana qua<U+017F>i purpurea &amp; Aulaea Regia.</note> Aulaea Togae, magnaeque coronae.</l>
               <l>Tantum orbem, quanto cervix non <U+017F>ufficit ulla?</l>
               <l>Quippe tenet <U+017F>udans banc<note n="c" place="bottom">PUBLICUS. Servus qui trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantibus à tergo in eodem curru ad<U+017F>tabat ut coronam illam aure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am immen<U+017F>i ponderis &amp; amplitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dmis <U+017F>uftneret.</note> publicus, &amp; <U+017F>ibi con<U+017F>ul</l>
               <l>Ne placeat, curru <U+017F>ervus portatur eodem.</l>
               <l>Da nunc &amp; volucrem, <U+017F>ceptro quae <U+017F>urgit eburno,</l>
               <l>Illinc cornicines, hinc praecedentia longi</l>
               <l>Agminis officia, &amp; niveos ad frena Quirites,</l>
               <l>De<U+017F>o<U+017F><U+017F>a in loculis quos <U+017F>portula fecit amicos.</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:93159:14"/>
By flowing Bowls and City Cu<U+017F>tard</l>
            <l>T'huzzahs and <hi>Io Paeans</hi> flu<U+017F>ter'd.</l>
            <l>Thus haughty Mayor without a Charter</l>
            <l>Looks big, as if in<U+017F>tall'd 'oth' Garter:</l>
            <l>Their Leaden Sword and Mace may <U+017F>wagger;</l>
            <l>But the wi<U+017F>e State <U+017F>ecur'd their Dagger.</l>
            <l>For Children and unskilful fools</l>
            <l>Cut their own fingers with edg'd-tools.</l>
            <l>Could he in <U+017F>ober hone<U+017F>t times</l>
            <l>With <U+017F>harp conceit tax petty crimes!</l>
            <l>And every where among<U+017F>t the rout</l>
            <l>Find follyes for his Wit to flout:</l>
            <l>Which, proves that <hi>Goatham</hi> and gro<U+017F>e Clymes</l>
            <l>Produce prodigious Wits <U+017F>ometimes.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="bottom">TUNC. Emphatice dictum, quum <U+017F>cilicet homines (vivente De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>to) prudenter &amp; longe rectius vitas <U+017F>uas con<U+017F>tituebant; quanto magis no<U+017F>tro tempore hominum vanitates rideret.</note> Tunc qucque materiam ri<U+017F>us invenit ad omneis</l>
               <l>Occur<U+017F>us hominum—</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:93159:15"/>
The Joys and fears of the vain crowd,</l>
            <l>And whimp'ring tears hee'd jeer aloud;</l>
            <l>Wi<U+017F>ely <U+017F>ecure, Fortune deride</l>
            <l>By Foppi<U+017F>h Mortals Deify'd;</l>
            <l>Bid her behang'd, and laugh at Fate</l>
            <l>When threatned at the highe<U+017F>t rate;</l>
            <l>Whil<U+017F>t Fools for vain and harmful things</l>
            <l>Pour out their Prayers and Off'rings,</l>
            <l>Fa<U+017F>ting Petitions on the <hi>(7) Knees</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Of their regardle<U+017F>s Deityes.</l>
            <l>For place and power how many men vy</l>
            <l>Procuring mortal Hate and Envy;</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>—cujus prudentia mon<U+017F>trat</l>
               <l>Summos po<U+017F><U+017F>e viros, &amp; magna exempla daturos</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="bottom">VERVECUM PATRIA: vervex e<U+017F>t convitium hominis <U+017F>implicis &amp; rudis, <U+017F>ic Plautus, <hi>Ain' vero Verve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum Caput,</hi> anglice <hi>Sheeps-Head.</hi> Vervex e<U+017F>t aries ca<U+017F>tratus.</note> Vervecum in patria, cra<U+017F><U+017F>oque <U+017F>ub aere na<U+017F>ci.</l>
               <l>Ridebat curas, nec non &amp; gaudia vulgi:</l>
               <l>Interdum &amp; lachrymas, cum<note n="b" place="bottom">FORTUNAE: nam cum For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuna minitaretur mali al quod De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocrito, ille in contemptu manda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret fortunae laqueum, in ip<U+017F>ius <U+017F>u<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendium, protendens medium in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famem digitum, reliquis digitis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractis, quae contumelia indicabat
ignominio<U+017F>um Cinaedum vel Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</note> fortunae ip<U+017F>e minaci</l>
               <l>Mandaret laqueum, mediumque o<U+017F>tenderet unguem.</l>
               <l>Ergo <U+017F>upervacua aut <U+017F>ibi pernitio<U+017F>a petuntur,</l>
               <l>Propter quae fas e<U+017F>t<note n="c" place="bottom">GENUA: Olim concepta vota in tabulis con<U+017F>cripta Deorum genibus cera ob<U+017F>ignata affixerunt.</note> genua incerare Deorum.</l>
               <l>Quo<U+017F>dam praecipitat <U+017F>ubjecta potentia magnae—Invidiae,</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:93159:15"/>
Heralds long winded Titles <U+017F>ound</l>
            <l>Which the vain owners oft confound.</l>
            <l>Down go their Statues in di<U+017F>grace;</l>
            <l>The Party hangs up in the place.</l>
            <l>In rage they break Chariot triumphant,</l>
            <l>Becau<U+017F>e a Knave fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>et his rump ont:</l>
            <l>Poor Hor<U+017F>es <U+017F>uffer for no fau't</l>
            <l>Unle<U+017F>s by bungling work-men wrought.</l>
            <l>The Founders Fournace grows red hot,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Sejanus</hi> (8) Statue goes to pot:</l>
            <l>That Head lately ador'd, and reckond</l>
            <l>In all the Univer<U+017F>e the Second,</l>
            <l>Melted new forms and <U+017F>hapes a<U+017F><U+017F>umes,</l>
            <l>Of Pi<U+017F>pots, Frying-pans, and Spoons:</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>—mergit longa at que in<U+017F>ignis honorum</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="bottom">PAGINA: Tabula aenaea ima. ginibus affixa quae honorum gradus continebat.</note> Pagina;<note n="b" place="bottom">DESCENDUNT: Statuae dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natorum tyranidis, laefae Maje<U+017F>tatis, vel gravis alicujus criminis, nomina eorum eradibantur fa<U+017F>tis, Statuae frangebantur idque decreto Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tratus, vel furore populi, laqueos altioribus Statuis <U+017F>olebant injicere atque ita detrahere.</note> de<U+017F>cendunt Statuae re<U+017F>temque <U+017F>equuntur.</l>
               <l>Ip<U+017F>as deinde<note n="c" place="bottom">ROTAS: Currus Triumphale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Statuas eque<U+017F>tres, equos aenaeos.</note> rot as bigarum impacta <U+017F>ecuris</l>
               <l>Caedit, &amp; immeritis franguntur crura Caballis.</l>
               <l>Jam strident<note n="d" place="bottom">IGNES: quibus <U+017F>unduntur &amp; li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuntur Statuae, &amp; ardet, &amp; lique<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit caput Statuae Sejani, nuper in tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to honore habitum, fuerat enim perpetuus Collega Tibe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ii Imperatoris eique <U+017F>ecundi honores habebantur.</note> ignes, jam follibus at que caminis</l>
               <l>Ardet adoratum populo caput, &amp; crepat ingens</l>
               <l>Sejanus: deinde ex <U+017F>acie toto orbe <U+017F>ecunda</l>
               <l>Fiunt urceoli, pelves, <U+017F>artago, patellae.</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:93159:16"/>
The Crowd o'rejoy'd that <hi>Cae<U+017F>ar</hi>'s living</l>
            <l>Petition for a new thank<U+017F>giving.</l>
            <l>How the ba<U+017F>e Rout in<U+017F>ult to <U+017F>ee</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Sejanus</hi> dragg'd to De<U+017F>tiny!</l>
            <l>Cryes one, that fellow I ne're brook'd,</l>
            <l>How down and hangingly he look'd!</l>
            <l>What blobber lips the ra<U+017F>cal <U+017F>hew'd?</l>
            <l>I told you hee'd ne're come to good.</l>
            <l>But what's his Crime, or how detected?</l>
            <l>That Que<U+017F>tion wholly is neglected:</l>
            <l>What Evidence or Judges <U+017F>it?</l>
            <l>P<U+017F>haw, waw, that matters not a whit?</l>
            <l>When <U+017F>o apparent was his Crime,</l>
            <l>A formal proce<U+017F>s would lo<U+017F>e time.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="bottom">PONE: quod fieri <U+017F>olitum in laetitia Publica, in qua frondibus domus ornabantur.</note> Pone domi laures<note n="b" place="bottom">DUC: Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatum (i. e.) candidum bovem quem Jovi Capitolino ex triumphantium more immoles; in gratiarum actio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem; Superis enim candidas victi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas immolabant, Inferis nigras.</note> duc in Capitolia magnum</l>
               <l>Creta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mque bovem:<note n="c" place="bottom">SEJANUS: qui paulo ante alios in Triumphum ducebat, jam ip<U+017F>e unco trahitur ad <U+017F>upplicium ad <U+017F>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Gemonias juxta Tybrim al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is <U+017F>pectaculum exhibiturus.</note> 
                  <hi>Sejanus</hi> ducitur unco</l>
               <l>Specta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dus:<note n="d" place="bottom">GAUDENT OMNES ejus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teritu, ne quis illi amicus videretur.</note> gaudent omnes.<note n="e" place="bottom">QUAE LABRA haec inter <U+017F>e po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulus in horas mobilis, a <U+017F>pectacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo tam tri<U+017F>ti rever<U+017F>us; occi<U+017F>o <hi>Sejano</hi> in<U+017F>ultans.</note> quae labra? quis illi</l>
               <l>Vultus crat?<note n="f" place="bottom">NUNQUAM: Hic dialogus brevis incipiens cum occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patione, qua<U+017F>i dicat, ego quidem nunquam amavi <hi>Sejanum,</hi> <U+017F>ed ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men libenter <U+017F>cirem, <U+017F>ub quo cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine ceciderit, aut quo te<U+017F>te Imperator probat <hi>Sejanum</hi> <U+017F>ibi <U+017F>truxi<U+017F><U+017F>e in<U+017F>idias.</note> nunquam (<U+017F>i quid mihi credis) amavi</l>
               <l>Hunc hominem. <U+017F>ed quocecidit <U+017F>ub crimine? qui<U+017F>nam</l>
               <l>Delator? quibus Indicibus, quo te<U+017F>te probavit?</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="g" place="bottom">NIL HORUM re<U+017F>pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens alter, fatetur <U+017F>e nil horum <U+017F>cire quae in judicio Capitali fieri <U+017F>olebant, <U+017F>ed verbo<U+017F>a &amp; grandis epi<U+017F>tola <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enit à Capreis qua Imperator <hi>Sejanum</hi> e<U+017F><U+017F>e reum demon<U+017F>travit.</note> Nil horum—</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:93159:16"/>
Long letters were from (9) <hi>Capra</hi> <U+017F>ent</l>
            <l>By <hi>Cae<U+017F>ar</hi> to the Parliament,</l>
            <l>With orders not to be di<U+017F>puted,</l>
            <l>The Traytor <U+017F>hould be executed.</l>
            <l>'Tis very well, th'other reply'd</l>
            <l>Your <U+017F>ervant Sir, I'me <U+017F>atisfy'd.</l>
            <l>What thought the <hi>Mobile</hi> the while?</l>
            <l>Nothing; tame animals they <U+017F>mile:</l>
            <l>Contentedly drive with the Tyde</l>
            <l>And alwayes hate the <U+017F>uffering <U+017F>ide.</l>
            <l>Had Fortune own'd <hi>Sejanus</hi> part,</l>
            <l>And with <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s had crown'd his art:</l>
            <l>And our young States-man had the hap</l>
            <l>To've ta'ne the old (10) Fox in his trap:</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>—verbo<U+017F>a &amp; grandis epistola venit</l>
               <l>A Capreis:<note n="a" place="bottom">BENE: re<U+017F>pondet primus inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogator, <U+017F>e jam omnem rem tenere &amp; intelligere.</note> bene habet, nil plus interrogo; <U+017F>ed quid</l>
               <l>Turbaremi? <U+017F>equitur fortunam, ut <U+017F>emper, &amp; odit</l>
               <l>Damnatos. idem populus, <U+017F>i<note n="b" place="bottom">NURTIA: fortuna Dea Thu<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum. <U+017F>en<U+017F>us e<U+017F>t, <U+017F>i Sejanus Thu<U+017F>cus fortuna Dea patriae <U+017F>avente Tiberi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um oppre<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F><U+017F>et, Populus Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Sejanum in Tiberii locum a<U+017F><U+017F>ump<U+017F>i<U+017F><U+017F>et, eumque imperatorem Augu<U+017F>tum faluta<U+017F><U+017F>et.</note> Nurtia Tu<U+017F>co</l>
               <l>Favi<U+017F><U+017F>et, <U+017F>i oppre<U+017F><U+017F>a foret <U+017F>ecura <U+017F>enectus—Principis,</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:93159:17"/>
Then our <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>sful Favorite</l>
            <l>The World had own'd to've been i'th' right:</l>
            <l>The fawning Rabble had that hour</l>
            <l>Saluted him their Emperour.</l>
            <l>Poor Roman fools <U+017F>ince ancient date</l>
            <l>Can Sell no voices in the State;</l>
            <l>Now freed from Care, and living idle</l>
            <l>Are taught to bite upon the Bridle.</l>
            <l>Who once Dictators, Con<U+017F>uls, cho<U+017F>e,</l>
            <l>And did all Offices di<U+017F>po<U+017F>e,</l>
            <l>Pa<U+017F>s now ingloriou<U+017F>ly their dayes,</l>
            <l>And meanly beg for Bread and Playes.</l>
            <l>'Tis <U+017F>aid Warrants are out to <U+017F>ei<U+017F>e</l>
            <l>Many and great Accomplices.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>—hac ip<U+017F>a Scjanum diceret hora</l>
               <l>Augu<U+017F>tum, jam pridem<note n="a" place="bottom">EXQUO: A tempore Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiae Julii Cae<U+017F>aris, ex quo impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores e<U+017F><U+017F>e ceperunt; nos Romani per <U+017F>uffragia quae plerunque vena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia fuerunt non eligimus Magi<U+017F>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, nec vendimus diver<U+017F>is candida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis competitoribus.</note> ex quo <U+017F>uffragia nulli</l>
               <l>Vendimus<note n="b" place="bottom">EFFUGIT Populus Romanus curas Electionis &amp; Comitiorum, quippe Imperatores Con<U+017F>ulum comitia ad <U+017F>e transtulere, exemplo Julii Cae<U+017F>aris.</note> effugit curas.<note n="c" place="bottom">NAM <hi>P. R.</hi> Qui per <U+017F>uffragia dabat Imperium, dictaturam, Con<U+017F>ulatum, Praeturam, Legiones, Belli praefecturam omnia officia &amp; honores nunc optant cum anxietate</note> nam qui dabat olim</l>
               <l>Imperium, fa<U+017F>ces, legiones, omnia, nunc <U+017F>e</l>
               <l>Continet, at que duas tantum res anxius optat</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="bottom">Panem ad victum, &amp; voluptatem è lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis Circen<U+017F>ibus.</note> Panem, &amp; Circen<U+017F>es.<note n="e" place="bottom">PERITUROS: Alter Populi paventis introducitur dialogi<U+017F>mus.</note> perituros audio multos.</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:93159:17"/>
Likely; the Prince his Rage does burn as</l>
            <l>Outragiou<U+017F>ly as fire in Furnace.</l>
            <l>At <hi>Mars</hi> his Shrine I met <hi>Brutidius</hi>
            </l>
            <l>With gha<U+017F>tly looks, all pale, and hideous,</l>
            <l>Since the ill-manag'd Plot took vent</l>
            <l>His looks declare his di<U+017F>content,</l>
            <l>As if for game ill play'd he meant,</l>
            <l>Like <hi>Ajax</hi> to anticipate</l>
            <l>With his own hands his ling'ring Fate.</l>
            <l>But to wipe off <U+017F>u<U+017F>pition</l>
            <l>On our part, let's to <hi>Tyber</hi> run;</l>
            <l>While on the Banck the Corps does ly</l>
            <l>Trample on <hi>Cae<U+017F>ars</hi> Enemy.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>Nil dubium: magna e<U+017F>t<note n="a" place="bottom">FORNACULA: Ira in Pectore Tiberii ae<U+017F>tuante. vel Fornacula ad exurendos malos &amp; proditores.</note> fornacula: pallidulus mi</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="bottom">BRUTIDIUS: Vereor ne <hi>Bruti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius</hi> amicus meus, quem modo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veni pallentem ad <hi>Martis</hi> aram; ex male con<U+017F>cio animo, vel metu prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipis, quod Amicus &amp; Con<U+017F>pirator cum <hi>Sejano</hi> <U+017F>e interficiat <U+017F>icut <hi>Ajax.</hi>
                  </note> Brutidius mens ad Martis fuit obvius aram.</l>
               <l>Quem timeo, victus ne paenas exigat Ajax,</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>t male defen<U+017F>us! curramus praecipites, et,</l>
               <l>Dum jacet in ripa calcemus Cae<U+017F>aris<note n="c" place="bottom">HOSTEM: <hi>Sejani</hi> Cadaver.</note> ho<U+017F>tem.</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:93159:18"/>
But 'twill do wi<U+017F>ely our whole Crew</l>
            <l>Of Servants <U+017F>hould the action veiw;</l>
            <l>That Friends, and Foes may te<U+017F>tify</l>
            <l>How we abhor di<U+017F>loyalty.</l>
            <l>The murm'ring vulgar at this rate</l>
            <l>Did of the fal'n <hi>Sejanus</hi> prate:</l>
            <l>Would you on the<U+017F>e Conditions, Sir,</l>
            <l>Be Favourite and Prime-Mini<U+017F>ter,</l>
            <l>As was <hi>Sejanus?</hi> Stand Po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>t</l>
            <l>Of Honours, Power and Intere<U+017F>t;</l>
            <l>Di<U+017F>po<U+017F>e <U+017F>upream Commands at will,</l>
            <l>Promote, di<U+017F>grace, pre<U+017F>erve, or kill:</l>
            <l>Be guardian to a carele<U+017F>s King</l>
            <l>Who in all plea<U+017F>ures takes his <U+017F>wing:</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>Sed<note n="a" place="bottom">VIDEANT SERVI ne quis eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum tanquam Sejano <U+017F>aventes accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>et.</note> videant <U+017F>ervi, ne quis neget, &amp; pavidum in jus</l>
               <l>Cervice ob<U+017F>tricta dominum trahat: hi <U+017F>ermones</l>
               <l>Tunc de Sejano, <U+017F>eoreta haec murmura vulgi.</l>
               <l>Vis ne <U+017F>alutari <U+017F>icut Sejanus? habere</l>
               <l>Tantundom? atque illi <U+017F>ummas donoere<note n="b" place="bottom">CURULES: Magi<U+017F>tratus urbanos, <U+017F>ellis Curulibus in Curiam ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi &amp; ex iis jura dare <U+017F>olebant Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tratus.</note> Curuleis?</l>
               <l>Illum exercitibus praeponere?<note n="c" place="bottom">TUTOR: Vicarius Imperato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris e<U+017F><U+017F>e dum in angu<U+017F>ta Caprearum In<U+017F>ula in <U+017F>ece<U+017F><U+017F>u otium &amp; vitam li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidino<U+017F>am agit, cum Chaldeis Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematicis &amp; Fatidicis quibus mire deditus erat Tiberius.</note> tutor haberi</l>
               <l>Principis Augu<U+017F>ta Caprearum in rupe <U+017F>edentis</l>
               <l>Cum grege Chaldeo?—</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:93159:18"/>
Cloy<U+017F>t'red in Bawdy Grots and Cellers,</l>
            <l>With Pimps, Buffoones, and Fortune-Tellers.</l>
            <l>Have Foot and Hor<U+017F>e-Guards, the Command</l>
            <l>Of Armys both by Sea and Land.</l>
            <l>Why not? Though Good-men would not kill,</l>
            <l>Yet in their pow'r they'd have it <U+017F>till:</l>
            <l>What Plea<U+017F>ure can <U+017F>o tickle <U+017F>en<U+017F>e;</l>
            <l>Sharp pains and Grief to recompen<U+017F>e,</l>
            <l>What happy or exalted State,</l>
            <l>But is o're ballanc'd by Ill Fate?</l>
            <l>Would not you rather ask in Prayer,</l>
            <l>To be <U+017F>ome Petty Country Mayor:</l>
            <l>There domineer, and when your Plea<U+017F>ur's,</l>
            <l>Condemn light weights, &amp; break fal<U+017F>e mea<U+017F>ures.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>—<note n="a" place="bottom">VIS CERTE: <U+017F>cio te velle primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilatum vel legionis praefecturam Pila ponitur pro peditibus pilis mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitis.</note> vis certe pila, Cohortes,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="bottom">EGREGIOS EQUITES equitum dome<U+017F>ticorum Magi<U+017F>terium.</note> Egregios equites, et<note n="c" place="bottom">CASTRA DOMESTICA: Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriana quae primus ad muros Romae po<U+017F><U+017F>uit Sejanus.</note> ca<U+017F>tra dome<U+017F>tica, quid ni</l>
               <l>Haec cupias? et qui nolunt occidere quenquam</l>
               <l>Po<U+017F><U+017F>e volunt. Sed quae praeclara et pro<U+017F>pera tanti,</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>t rebus laetis par <U+017F>it men<U+017F>ura malorum?</l>
               <l>Hujus qui trahitur<note n="d" place="bottom">PRAETEXTAM fummum imperium cum Sejaui periculo et <U+017F>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicio.</note> praetextam <U+017F>umere mavis,</l>
               <l>An Fidenarum Gabiorum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> e<U+017F><U+017F>e<note n="e" place="bottom">POTESTAS an in ob<U+017F>cura Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la Aelilem vel Magi<U+017F>tratum cum <U+017F>ecura tranquillitate.</note> Pote<U+017F>tas?</l>
               <l>Et de men<U+017F>uris jus dicere, va<U+017F>a minora</l>
               <l>Frangere panno<U+017F>us vacuis aedilis<note n="f" place="bottom">ULUBRIS: vel Aedilis in vacuo et de <U+017F>erto Vol<U+017F>corum oppido.</note> 
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>lubris.</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:93159:19"/>
Though meanly clad in <U+017F>afe e<U+017F>tate</l>
            <l>Then choo<U+017F>e <hi>Sejanus</hi> Robes and Fate.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Sejanus</hi> then we mu<U+017F>t conclude</l>
            <l>Courting his Bane, mi<U+017F>took the Good.</l>
            <l>For he who from a mean e<U+017F>tate</l>
            <l>Va<U+017F>t Honours did accumulate,</l>
            <l>And endle<U+017F>s Riches, which enable</l>
            <l>To build his Fortune high as <hi>Babel,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And brav'd the World; by weight too large</l>
            <l>Did th' high pil'd Storyes overcharge:</l>
            <l>Whence <U+017F>hockt with <U+017F>torms the reeling weight</l>
            <l>The owner did precipitate,</l>
            <l>And Signaliz'd Ambitions Fate.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="bottom">ERGO: Repetit propo<U+017F>itionem &amp; concludit ip<U+017F>um <hi>Sejanum</hi> vera bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na ignora<U+017F><U+017F>e, qua<U+017F>i dicat, con<U+017F>tater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go <hi>Sejanum</hi> dum honores <hi>&amp;c.</hi> appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiit nihil boni petii<U+017F><U+017F>e, <U+017F>ed in altum &amp; <U+017F>ummum honorum cacumen a<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendi<U+017F><U+017F>e, ut altius &amp; profundius rueret. Claudianus.</note> Ergo quid optandum foret ignora<U+017F><U+017F>e fateris</l>
               <l>Sejanum. <hi>nam qui nimios optabat honores,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Et nimias po<U+017F>cebat opes,<note n="b" place="bottom">NUMEROSA: Sibi ip<U+017F>i numero<U+017F>as &amp; multiplices contignationes &amp; tabulata in excel<U+017F>o honorum fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tigio exaedificabat, unde po<U+017F>tea deturbatus per ingens atque immane praecipitium violenta ruina decideret.</note> numero<U+017F> a parab at</l>
               <l>Excel<U+017F>ae turris tabulata, unde altior e<U+017F><U+017F><gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t</l>
               <l>Ca<U+017F>us, &amp; impul<U+017F>ae praeceps immane ruinae.</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lap<U+017F>u graviore ruant, tolluntur in altum.</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:93159:19"/>
               <hi>Cra<U+017F><U+017F>us</hi> and <hi>Pompeys</hi> fate of old</l>
            <l>The truth of this <U+017F>ure Maxime told:</l>
            <l>And his who fir<U+017F>t bow'd <hi>Romes</hi> Stiff neck,</l>
            <l>And made the World obey his beck,</l>
            <l>By Subtil ways and arts a<U+017F>pir'd</l>
            <l>And Sov'reign <U+017F>way at length accquir'd;</l>
            <l>While the Malignant Heavens decreed,</l>
            <l>His own de<U+017F>ires <U+017F>hould make him bleed;</l>
            <l>Tyrants with <U+017F>ome untimely end</l>
            <l>To <hi>Pro<U+017F>erpines</hi> black Court de<U+017F>cend.</l>
            <l>The Novice in his Accidence,</l>
            <l>Dares pray his Wit and Eloquence</l>
            <l>May Rival Roman <hi>Cicero</hi>'s (11) fame</l>
            <l>And Greek <hi>Demo<U+017F>thenes</hi> (12) high name.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>Quid<note n="a" place="bottom">CRASSOS: Marcum Cra<U+017F><U+017F>um patrem a Surena Legato Parthorum rege devictum; eju<U+017F>que filios a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>this &amp; Cae<U+017F>arianis occi<U+017F>os.</note> Cra<U+017F><U+017F>os, quid<note n="b" place="bottom">POMPEIOS: Pompeium mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num cum duobus filiis a Cae<U+017F>arianis trucidatos.</note> Pompeios evertit?<note n="c" place="bottom">ET ILLUM: Julium Cae<U+017F>arem perpetuum Dictatorem intelligit, qui Quirites (i. e.) cives Romanos domitos deduxit ad <U+017F>ua flagra (i. e.) imperium ab<U+017F>olutum; imminuta imo ami<U+017F><U+017F>a libertate, ille a Bruto, Ca<U+017F><U+017F>io, &amp; reliquis conjuratoribus in Senatu, 23. vulneribus confo<U+017F><U+017F>us periit.</note> &amp; illum,</l>
               <l>Ad <U+017F>ua qui domitos deduxit flagra Quirites?</l>
               <l>Summus nempe locus nulla non arte petitus,</l>
               <l>Magnaque numinibus vota exandita malignis.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="bottom">AD GENERUM CERERIS: (i. e.) ad Plutonem Pro<U+017F>erpinae filiae Cereris maritum, pauci Tyranni de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>cendunt morte non cruenta.</note> Ad generum Cereris <U+017F>ine caede, &amp; vulnere pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i</l>
               <l>De<U+017F>cendunt Reges, &amp; <U+017F>icca morte Tyranni.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="e" place="bottom">ELOQUIUM: Puer elementa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius qui literis initiatur, quem <U+017F>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus Cap<U+017F>arius deducit ad <U+017F>cholam &amp; reducit pauculos <U+017F>erens libros.</note> Eloquium &amp; famam Demo<U+017F>thenis &amp; Ciccronis</l>
               <l>Incipit optare, &amp; totis<note n="f" place="bottom">QUINQUATRIEUS: (i. e.) in <U+017F>e<U+017F>tis Minervae <U+017F>apientiae prae<U+017F>idis quae quinque diebus celebrantu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; exoptat eloquentiam Demo<U+017F>thenis &amp; Ciceronis. alii putant hoc de Paedagogo non de Di<U+017F>cipulo dictum.</note> Quinquatribus optat,</l>
               <l>Quisquis adhuc uno partam colit a<U+017F><U+017F>e Minervam,</l>
               <l>Quem <U+017F>equitur cu<U+017F>tos angu<U+017F>tae vernula cap<U+017F>ae.</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:93159:20"/>
Yet to both the<U+017F>e, their <U+017F>welling vein</l>
            <l>Of wit and fancy prov'd their bane;</l>
            <l>The Fatal cau<U+017F>e that Forfeited,</l>
            <l>The <hi>Ciceronian</hi> hands and head.</l>
            <l>No pleading dunce's jobber noule,</l>
            <l>Revenge e're doom'd <U+017F>hould grace a Pole.</l>
            <l>O happy Romes <U+017F>ecure E<U+017F>tate,</l>
            <l>Where I was fortunate innate;<note place="margin">Wherein the Tran<U+017F>lator imitates the gingle of <hi>Cicero</hi>'s own Ver<U+017F>e.</note>
            </l>
            <l>Had happily his Genius cho<U+017F>e</l>
            <l>To've writ <U+017F>uch inoffen<U+017F>ive pro<U+017F>e;</l>
            <l>His harmle<U+017F>s blunt <U+017F>tupidity</l>
            <l>Might <hi>Antonys</hi> Revenge defy;</l>
            <l>'Tis <U+017F>afer <U+017F>en<U+017F>ele<U+017F>s ver<U+017F>e to write,</l>
            <l>Than in <hi>Philippicks</hi> keenly bite.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>Eloquio <U+017F>ed uterque perit orator, utrumque</l>
               <l>Largus, et exundans letho dedit ingenii fons,</l>
               <l>Ingenio<note n="a" place="bottom">MANUS: et Caput Ciceronis ab<U+017F>ci<U+017F><U+017F>a affigebantur ro<U+017F>tris e qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus in Antonium dixerat.</note> manus e<U+017F>t, et cervix cae<U+017F>a, nec unquam</l>
               <l>Sanguine Cau<U+017F>idici maduerunt ro<U+017F>tra pu<U+017F>illi.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="bottom">O FORTUNATAM: ver<U+017F>um hinc Ciceronis de oppre<U+017F><U+017F>u Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talina in <U+017F>uo Con<U+017F>ulatu irridet, propter vocem natam natam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>epte iteratam, unde Author in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuit: <U+017F>i talia inepta carmina Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero <U+017F>emper <U+017F>crip<U+017F>i<U+017F><U+017F>et, et tam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>epte omnia dixi<U+017F><U+017F>et ab Antonii gladiis tutus et <U+017F>ecurus eva<U+017F>i<U+017F><U+017F>et.</note> O fortunatam natam me Con<U+017F>ule Romam.</l>
               <l>Antonii gladios potuit contemnere <U+017F>i <U+017F>ic</l>
               <l>Omnia dixi<U+017F><U+017F>et: ridenda P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emata malo,</l>
               <l>Quam te con<U+017F>picuae divina<note n="c" place="bottom">PHILIPPICA orationes Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceronis in Antonium quas malo omine Philippicas in<U+017F>crip<U+017F>it ab iis quas in Philippum regem Macedonia habuit Demo<U+017F>thenes. Quae ambobus oratoribus aeque exitiales fuerunt.</note> Philippica famae,</l>
               <l>Volveris a prima quae proxima.—</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:93159:20"/>
A violent and <U+017F>ullen fate</l>
            <l>Did on th' admir'd Athenian wait;</l>
            <l>Who<U+017F>e manage <hi>Mobile</hi>'s had guided</l>
            <l>As with a rein where e're he <U+017F>ided.</l>
            <l>Yet born under unlucky Stars</l>
            <l>Sqinting untoward and perver<U+017F>e,</l>
            <l>Was <U+017F>ent by's <U+017F>warthy blear-ey'd Sire</l>
            <l>Betimes from <U+017F>ooty forge and fire,</l>
            <l>From making <U+017F>words and martial tools,</l>
            <l>To hammer Arguments in Schools.</l>
            <l>The Trophies which the vanqui<U+017F>h'd field</l>
            <l>Do to the glorious Victors yield,</l>
            <l>Triumphant Conquerours can ble<U+017F>s</l>
            <l>With more than humane happine<U+017F>s.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>—<U+017F>aevus &amp;<note n="a" place="bottom">ILLUM: Demo<U+017F>thenem cujus eloquentia in modum torrentis fluens, regebat &amp; gubernabat to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Theatrum &amp; auditorium ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num civibus Athenien<U+017F>ibus: in quo orationes recitare <U+017F>olitus: qui accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to nuntio de Antipatri &amp; Crateri adventu, in Calabriam Thraciae ad a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram Neptuni profugit, a cujus ara cum Archias <U+017F>atelles cum ab<U+017F>trahe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re conaretur, Demo<U+017F>thenes veneno quod in calamo habuit hau<U+017F>to inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riit.</note> illum</l>
               <l>Exitus eripuit, quem mirabantur Athenae</l>
               <l>Torrentem &amp; pleni moderantem frena Theatri.</l>
               <l>Diis ille adver<U+017F>us genitus, fatoque <U+017F>inistro,</l>
               <l>Quem pater ardentis ma<U+017F><U+017F>ae fuligine lippus</l>
               <l>A carbone, &amp; forcipibus, gladio<U+017F>que parante</l>
               <l>Incude, &amp; luteo Vulcano ad rhetora mi<U+017F>it.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="bottom">BELLORUM: tran<U+017F>it jam elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentia ad glorias laudes ac victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as bellicas, quae tantopere a pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis appetuntur, &amp; reputantur <U+017F>um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma bona &amp; pror<U+017F>us divina e<U+017F><U+017F>e licet multis exitio fui<U+017F><U+017F>e demon<U+017F>trat ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplis Annibalis, Alexandri magni, &amp; Xerxis.</note> Bellorum<note n="c" place="bottom">EXUVIAE Triumphi; Trophaea, Spolia, omnis generis quae victis ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tibus
in bello exuuntur.</note> exuviae, truncis affixa trophaeis</l>
               <l>Lorica, &amp; fracta de ca<U+017F><U+017F>ide buccula pendens.</l>
               <l>Et currum temone jugum, victaeque triremis</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="bottom">APLUSTRE: Ornamenta navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um: Victoriae Navalis ornamenta: <hi>Flaggs, Pendants, Streamers, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> Aplustre, &amp; <U+017F>ummo tri<U+017F>tis Captivus in arcu.</l>
               <l>Humanis major a bonis creduntur:—</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:93159:21"/>
This <hi>Roman, Grecian,</hi> and <hi>Barbarian,</hi> (13)</l>
            <l>Spurr'd to acts hazardous and daring,</l>
            <l>In <U+017F>weat and blood, <U+017F>pending their dayes</l>
            <l>For empty Fame, and fadeing Bayes.</l>
            <l>'Tis the immoderate thir<U+017F>t of Fame</l>
            <l>Much more than Vertue does inflame:</l>
            <l>Which none for wor<U+017F>e or better take</l>
            <l>But for her dower and trappings <U+017F>ake.</l>
            <l>The fond Ambition of a few</l>
            <l>Many va<U+017F>t Empires overthrew;</l>
            <l>While their Archievements with their du<U+017F>t</l>
            <l>They vainly to their Tomb<U+017F>tones tru<U+017F>t.</l>
            <l>For <U+017F>epulchres like bodyes ly</l>
            <l>Swallow'd in Deaths ob<U+017F>curity.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>—<note n="a" place="bottom">AD HAEC Trophea quae cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt <U+017F>umma bona erexerunt <U+017F>e Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus ut <hi>Sylla, Marius, Pompeius magnus, Julius Cae<U+017F>ar,</hi> Graius, <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exander magnus,</hi> Barbarus, <hi>Annibal, Xerxes, Darius.</hi>
                  </note> ad hac <U+017F>e</l>
               <l>Romanus, Graius, ac Barbarus Induperator</l>
               <l>Erexit: cau<U+017F>as di<U+017F>criminis, at que laboris</l>
               <l>Inde habuit:<note n="b" place="bottom">INDE HABUIT: Ex hac am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitione &amp; bellicae laudis gloria, hi tot di<U+017F>crimina, pericula, aerumnas &amp; labores in <U+017F>e <U+017F>u<U+017F>ceperunt.</note> tanto major famae <U+017F>itis e<U+017F>t quam</l>
               <l>Virtutis, quis enim virtutem amplectitur ip<U+017F>am<note n="c" place="bottom">TANTO MAJOR: nam om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes virtute relicta, <U+017F>amam &amp; glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am bellicam quae<U+017F>iverunt</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="bottom">PRAEMIA: ld e<U+017F>t, <U+017F>i honorem, <U+017F>amam, &amp; gloriam, quae virtutis praemia putantur, tollas: nemo virtutem nudam curabit.</note> Praemia <U+017F>i tollas? patriam tamen obruit olim</l>
               <l>Gloria paucorum, &amp; laudis titulique cupido</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="e" place="bottom">HAESURI SAXIS: in<U+017F>cribendi faxeis <U+017F>epulcris in quibus Urnae &amp; Cineres conduntur.</note> Hae<U+017F>uri <U+017F>axis cinerum cu<U+017F>todibus: ad quae</l>
               <l>Di<U+017F>cutienda valent <U+017F>terilis mala robora<note n="f" place="bottom">FICUS Caprificus <U+017F>teriles in nulla re pro<U+017F>unt, quae ex muris erumpentes <U+017F>eindunt validi<U+017F><U+017F>imos muros &amp; <U+017F>axa in quibus na<U+017F>cuntur.</note> ficus:</l>
               <l>Quandoquidem data <U+017F>unt ip<U+017F>is quoque fata <U+017F>epulcris.</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:93159:21"/>
Behold how <U+017F>mall an Urn contains</l>
            <l>The mighty <hi>Hannibals</hi> (14) Remains.</l>
            <l>Yet this was he who<U+017F>e <U+017F>welling mind</l>
            <l>To <hi>Affrick</hi> (15) could not be confin'd;</l>
            <l>Though meas'ring that large tract of Land</l>
            <l>From <hi>Tangier</hi> to <hi>Niles</hi> reaking <U+017F>and:</l>
            <l>Thence <U+017F>outhwards to <hi>Cape Bon 'Sperance</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Negroes</hi> and lofty Elephants:</l>
            <l>Whence wafting o're the <hi>Mid-land</hi> Main,</l>
            <l>He conquers and po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>es <hi>Spain:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Re<U+017F>tle<U+017F>s in his ambitious mind,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Italian</hi> Conque<U+017F>ts are de<U+017F>ign'd.</l>
            <l>Strong Bars wi<U+017F>e Nature did oppo<U+017F>e</l>
            <l>The <hi>Alps</hi> (16) thatcht with eternal Snows:</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="bottom">EXPENDE Hannibalis cineres velgloriam bellicam</note> Expende Hannibalem, quot libras in duce <U+017F>ummo</l>
               <l>Invenies?<note n="b" place="bottom">HIC EST Hannibal ille quem vivum tota Africa, tunc tertia pars terrarum orbis exi<U+017F>timata, non cepit.</note> hic e<U+017F>t quem non capit Africa<note n="c" place="bottom">MAURO a mari Atlantico ab Occidente patens ad Nilum, Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti flumen ob <U+017F>ole verticali tepentem, ab Oriente.</note> Mauro</l>
               <l>Perfu<U+017F>a Oceano, Niloque remota a tepenti.</l>
               <l>Rur<U+017F>us ad Aethiopum populos alto<U+017F>que Elephantes:</l>
               <l>Additur Imperiis Hi<U+017F>pania:<note n="d" place="bottom">PYRENAEUM: alti montes qni Hi<U+017F>paniam a Gallia dividunt.</note> Pyrenaeum</l>
               <l>Tran<U+017F>ilit.<note n="e" place="bottom">OPPOSUIT: Natura Alpes alti<U+017F><U+017F>imos &amp; nivo<U+017F>os Montes, quibus Galliam &amp; Germaniam ab Italia di<U+017F>terminavit.</note> oppo<U+017F>uit natura a Alpemque, nivemque:</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:93159:22"/>
His way not craggy Mountain blocks,</l>
            <l>With <hi>Vinegar</hi> (17) he eats through rocks:</l>
            <l>Impediments by Nature ca<U+017F>t</l>
            <l>By art or labour are o're pa<U+017F>t,</l>
            <l>To <hi>Italy</hi> he comes at la<U+017F>t;</l>
            <l>Where after Towns and Battles won</l>
            <l>He crys, <hi>Comrades,</hi> there's nothing done,</l>
            <l>Unle<U+017F>s our Conqu'ring Punick Powers</l>
            <l>Brake down <hi>Romes</hi> Gates, level her Towers,</l>
            <l>Root up her Po<U+017F>ts, and brake her chains,</l>
            <l>And knock out all Oppo<U+017F>ers Brains:</l>
            <l>Whil<U+017F>t our Troops <U+017F>cowr the City thorough</l>
            <l>And fix our Standard in<note n="*" place="margin">A high Street in the City, like <hi>Cheap-<U+017F>ide.</hi>
               </note> Saburra.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="bottom">DIDUXIT di<U+017F>traxit, divi<U+017F>it, viam per Alpes apperiens adhibito incendio, &amp; infusò aceto <U+017F>copulos fregit, ut fabulosè <U+017F>cribit Livius.</note> Diduxit <U+017F>copulos, &amp; montem rupit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Jam tenet Italiam: tamen ultra <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc><…></desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="bottom">ACTUM verba Hannibalis mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram regnandi libidinem exprimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, quibus milites <U+017F>uos hortat Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam ip<U+017F>am perdere, innuens vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torias adhinc acqui<U+017F>itas nullius momenti e<U+017F><U+017F>e, ni<U+017F>i Punico milite Romae portas frangeret, ac urbe devicta, vexillum <U+017F>ummum Triumphantem<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> in Saburra nobili<U+017F><U+017F>ima &amp; alti<U+017F><U+017F>ima urbi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> collocaret.</note> Actum, inqu't, nihil est, ni<U+017F>i <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc><…></desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Frangimus, &amp; media vexillum pono <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:93159:22"/>
Oh had you then his Figure <U+017F>een,</l>
            <l>With what a rueful <hi>Phis</hi> and <hi>meine,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The Rhod'montado Captain <U+017F>poke,</l>
            <l>Doubtle<U+017F>s your laughter 'twould provoke!</l>
            <l>Some pencil now to paint the form</l>
            <l>Of this grum bulk of Huff and Storm;</l>
            <l>While Swarthy, meager, and one-ey'd,</l>
            <l>He does his <hi>Africk</hi> Mon<U+017F>ter ride.</l>
            <l>But what Cata<U+017F>trophy of Fate,</l>
            <l>Does on our famous Leader wait!</l>
            <l>His Conduct's baffled, Army's broke,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Carthage</hi> puts on the <hi>Roman</hi> Yoak:</l>
            <l>Whil<U+017F>t Flight and Bani<U+017F>hment's his Fate,</l>
            <l>His ruin'd Countryes Scorn and Hate:</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="bottom">O QUALIS FACIES: irridet Poeta vanitatem &amp; deformitatem Annibalis, qui tamen tot &amp; tanta in mente agitabat, quam ridicula facies &amp; <U+017F>igura <U+017F>it, <U+017F>i unoculus dux Getulo alicui Elephanti in<U+017F>idens, in pictura pingueretur.</note> O qualis facies, &amp; quali digna tabella,</l>
               <l>Cum Getula Ducem portaret bellua<note n="b" place="bottom">LUSCUM: unoculum alterum ami<U+017F>erat vigiliis &amp; palu<U+017F>tri caelo dum in Etruriam de<U+017F>cenderet.</note> lu<U+017F>cum!</l>
               <l>Exitus ergo quis e<U+017F>t? O gloria! vincitur idem</l>
               <l>Nempe, &amp; in exilium praeceps fugit,</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:93159:23"/>
At the <hi>Bythinian</hi> (18) Tyrants Gate,</l>
            <l>The reform'd Fugitive mu<U+017F>t wait:</l>
            <l>And there for audience <U+017F>uppliant <U+017F>it,</l>
            <l>Till the Kings <hi>Levè</hi> will admit.</l>
            <l>Neither the <U+017F>word, nor <U+017F>pear, nor dart,</l>
            <l>Could reach that wi<U+017F>e undaunted heart,</l>
            <l>And decently di<U+017F>patch that Soul</l>
            <l>That did the Univer<U+017F>e controul:</l>
            <l>With awful Reverence his Fate</l>
            <l>Did none but his own Orders wait:</l>
            <l>As if decreed by Powers Divine,</l>
            <l>His Ring <U+017F>hould his own Pa<U+017F>port <U+017F>ign;</l>
            <l>That Ring that mu<U+017F>t avenge the guilt</l>
            <l>Of Seas of Blood at <hi>Canna</hi> (19) <U+017F>pilt.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>—atque ibi magnus</l>
               <l>Mirandu<U+017F>que Cliens <U+017F>edet ad praetoriaregis,</l>
               <l>Donec Bithino libeat vigilare Tyranno.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="bottom">FINEM ANIMAE laethum An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibali qui omnia inturbabat non gladii, nec bellica in<U+017F>trumenta da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant! nam Italia relicta, in Africam rever<U+017F>us Annibal, Zama in praelio à Scipione devictus, &amp; exilio mulcta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, ad Antiochum Syriae Regem profugit, quem po<U+017F>tquam de pace cum Romanis <U+017F>u<U+017F>pectum de<U+017F>eruit, &amp; ad Pru<U+017F>iam Bythiniae regem <U+017F>e contulit, pro quo adver<U+017F>us Eume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem victor bellum gerit; quo cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nito; Romani mittunt ad Pru<U+017F>iam, Quintum Flaminium Legatum u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, ut <U+017F>ibi Annibal daretur ad Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam perducendus, quo Annibali olfacto, hau<U+017F>to veneno, quod <U+017F>em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <U+017F>ub annuli gemma habuerat Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manam malitiam illu<U+017F>it.</note> Finem animae quae res humanas mi<U+017F>cuit olim,</l>
               <l>Non glad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i, non <U+017F>axa dabunt, nec tela: <U+017F>ed ille</l>
               <l>Cannarum vindex, &amp; tanti <U+017F>anguinis ultor</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="bottom">ANNULUS: <U+017F>ub cujus palea in hunc u<U+017F>um Annibal venenum in omni tempore paratum habuit, annu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Cannarum vindex, &amp; ultor modii annulorum, quos Senatorum &amp; Equitum Gannis cae<U+017F>orum digitis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractos Carthaginem mi<U+017F>it.</note> Annulus.</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:93159:23"/>
No other means was found for <hi>Rome</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To be <U+017F>ecure from fears to come,</l>
            <l>But poor abandon'd <hi>Annibal</hi>
            </l>
            <l>A weak old Sacrifice mu<U+017F>t fall.</l>
            <l>Go Mad-man, act thy frantick part,</l>
            <l>Climb horrid <hi>Alps,</hi> with pains and art,</l>
            <l>To be with mighty reputation</l>
            <l>The <U+017F>ubject of a Declamation.</l>
            <l>One World's too mean a trifling thing</l>
            <l>For the Young (20) <hi>Macedonian</hi> King,</l>
            <l>He raves like one in Bani<U+017F>hment</l>
            <l>In narrow craggy <hi>I<U+017F>land</hi> pent:</l>
            <l>In one poor Globe does <U+017F>weat and <U+017F>queeze,</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>Wedg'd in and crampt in <hi>Little-Ea<U+017F>e.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>—<note n="a" place="bottom">I DEMENS: Poeta Sarca<U+017F>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus in<U+017F>ultat jam Annibali, qui jam mortu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ex tot laboribus, tot tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multibus, bellis, cladibus, nihil reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui habeat, quam ut <U+017F>chola<U+017F>ticis pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eris in <U+017F>cholis, materiam declaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di praebeat.</note> i demens, &amp; <U+017F>avas curre per Alpes</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>t pueris placeas, &amp; declamatio fias.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="bottom">UNUS PELLEO JUVENI: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exandro magno in Pella Macedoniae urbe nato, qui cum adhuc juvenis Anaxarchum Philo<U+017F>ophum de infinitis mundis audi<U+017F><U+017F>et differentem, fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi<U+017F><U+017F>e dicitur, &amp; dixi<U+017F><U+017F>e me mi<U+017F>erum qui unius mundi Dominus nondum factus <U+017F>um.</note> 
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>nus Pellaeo Juveni non <U+017F>ufficit orbis:</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="c" place="bottom">AESTUAT: Qua<U+017F>i in angu<U+017F>to conclavi clau<U+017F>us, in quo vix <U+017F>piritum po<U+017F><U+017F>it ducere.</note> Ae<U+017F>tuat infelix angu<U+017F>to limite mundi</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>t Gyarae<note n="d" place="bottom">CLAUSUS: Gyara vel Seripho angu<U+017F>ti<U+017F><U+017F>imis In<U+017F>ulis ad quas maxime <U+017F>teriles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>acinero<U+017F>i mittebantur, gravi<U+017F><U+017F>imi exilii locus.</note> clau<U+017F>us <U+017F>copulis, parvaque Seripho.</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:93159:24"/>
But he who humane race once <U+017F>corn'd,</l>
            <l>Gave out high <hi>Jove</hi> (21) King <hi>Phillip</hi> horn'd,</l>
            <l>While manag'd Oracles declare</l>
            <l>The Spark, great <hi>Ammons</hi> Son and Heir;</l>
            <l>At <hi>Babylon</hi> (22) for all his huffing,</l>
            <l>Finds ample room in narrow Coffin.</l>
            <l>Man <U+017F>wells with bomba<U+017F>t of inventions:</l>
            <l>When <U+017F>trip'd Death <U+017F>hews his true dimen<U+017F>ions.</l>
            <l>We will believe wild <hi>Xerxes</hi> rent</l>
            <l>Mount <hi>Athos</hi> (23) from the Continent,</l>
            <l>And in a frolick made a <U+017F>hift</l>
            <l>To <U+017F>et it in the <U+017F>ea a drift:</l>
            <l>What e're Romancing <hi>Greek</hi> dares tell,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Greece,</hi> that for Cracking bears the Bell:</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>Cum tamen a figulis munit am intraverit<note n="a" place="bottom">URBEM: Babylonem quam Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miramis cocto à figulis latere mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris cinxit &amp; circumdedit.</note> urbem,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="bottom">SARCOPHAGO quem vivum mundus non caeperat mortuus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentus &amp; inclu<U+017F>us e<U+017F>t exigua urna vel capulo ex Lapide A<U+017F><U+017F>io dicto quod cadaver con<U+017F>umat, Lapis Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cophagus intra quadraginta dies totum Corpus ab<U+017F>umit exceptis dentibus: Greci corpora defunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum non cremabant.</note> Sarcophago contentus erit,<note n="c" place="bottom">MORS: cum moriuntur homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes apparet, qui &amp; qual<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s fuerunt, &amp; quam exiguo illi loco includi &amp; contineri po<U+017F><U+017F>int.</note> Mors <U+017F>ola fatetur,</l>
               <l>Quantula <U+017F>int hominum Corpu<U+017F>cula.<note n="d" place="bottom">CREDITUR: Transit ad Xerxem Per<U+017F>arum regem, qui immen<U+017F>o <U+017F>uo imperio non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ontentus Graeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am bello petjit immen<U+017F>o Exercitu, quo Athonem Montem alti<U+017F><U+017F>imum Macedoniae à continenti ab<U+017F>cindi ju<U+017F><U+017F>it illumque navium velis circum dedit &amp; circum navigavit.</note> Creditur olim</l>
               <l>Velificatus Athos, &amp; quicquid Graecia mendax</l>
               <l>Audet in<note n="e" place="bottom">HISTORIA: Hi<U+017F>torici Greci vani &amp; mendaces, hi<U+017F>toriis <U+017F>uis incredibiles fabulas admi<U+017F>cent ut <U+017F>uam gloriam amplificarent.</note> hi<U+017F>toria—</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:93159:24"/>
With <U+017F>hips pav'd o're the <hi>Helle<U+017F>pont,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And built a floating bridge upon't:</l>
            <l>Drove Chariots o're by this device,</l>
            <l>As lately Coaches on the Ice.</l>
            <l>He led <U+017F>o numberle<U+017F>s a Rout,</l>
            <l>As at one Meal drank Rivers out.</l>
            <l>The Kings-Health <U+017F>carce could go about:</l>
            <l>With many like amazing Feats</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Sostratus</hi> Giddy Mu<U+017F>e repeats,</l>
            <l>With damp wing in her drunken heats.</l>
            <l>This Tyrant we in <U+017F>torys find</l>
            <l>was us'd to whip and Flogge the winde,</l>
            <l>Their Jayler <hi>Aeolus</hi> (24) in Pri<U+017F>on,</l>
            <l>Ne're firk'd them with <U+017F>o little rea<U+017F>on:</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>—Con<U+017F>tratum Cla<U+017F><U+017F>ibus<note n="a" place="bottom">IISDEM: Navibus quibus A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thos velificatus et circum naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Xerxes fretum Hele<U+017F>ponticum pontibus <U+017F>ternebat, et Abidum in A<U+017F>ia Se<U+017F>to in Europa junxit ubi nunc Turcorum munimenta hodie vocata <hi>the Dardanello'es</hi> po<U+017F>ita <U+017F>unt, Rotas ergo Curruum intelligit quae per pontem Tran<U+017F>ibant.</note> ii<U+017F>dem</l>
               <l>Suppo<U+017F>itumque rotis <U+017F>olidum mare. credimus altos</l>
               <l>Defeci<U+017F><U+017F>e amneis, epotaque flumina Medo<note n="b" place="bottom">MEDO: Xerxe et exercitu ex Medo et Perfis.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Prand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, &amp; madidis cantat quae So<U+017F>tratus alis.<note n="c" place="bottom">SOSTRATUS Graecus Poeta qui de expeditione Xerxis in Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia <U+017F>crip<U+017F>it, qui potu vel Poetico furore ebrius veritatem et <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>lem Hi<U+017F>toriae excedit et tran<U+017F>volat.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Ille tamen, qualis rediit Salamine relicta,<note n="d" place="bottom">SALAMINE relicta: in<U+017F>ula in <U+017F>inu Attico, ubi Xerxes navali praelio a Themi<U+017F>tocle Graecorum duce <U+017F>uperatus, cum magna clade Per<U+017F>arum; Unde fugiens ad Pontem Helle<U+017F>pontiacum, quem cum liberius tempe<U+017F>tatibus fractum invenit pi<U+017F>catoria <U+017F>capha trepidans turpiffime trajecit; qui paulo ante ventis impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare, et in Corum atque Eurum flagris <U+017F>uis dementer <U+017F>aevire <U+017F>olebat.</note> 
               </l>
               <l>In Corum, atque Eurum <U+017F>olitus <U+017F>aevire flageliis</l>
               <l>Barbarus, Aeolio nunquam hoc in carcere pa<U+017F><U+017F>os,</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:93159:25"/>
Nor could blew <hi>Neptunes</hi> (25) Godhead <U+017F>ave him,</l>
            <l>But he with Fetters mu<U+017F>t en<U+017F>lave him.</l>
            <l>'Twas well he <U+017F>cap'd his fury <U+017F>o,</l>
            <l>And was not whip'd and branded too.</l>
            <l>He mu<U+017F>t be a Complai<U+017F>ant God,</l>
            <l>Will budg at <U+017F>uch a Bedlam's nodd.</l>
            <l>But after all the<U+017F>e Roaring freaks,</l>
            <l>Routed and broak he homewards <U+017F>neaks;</l>
            <l>Abandons all to'th <hi>Conqu'ring</hi> Greeks,</l>
            <l>And Ferry's (26) o're in Fi<U+017F>her-boat,</l>
            <l>Through Shoals of Carca<U+017F><U+017F>es afloat;</l>
            <l>His hopes all Vani<U+017F>ht, bilk'd of all</l>
            <l>His gaudy dreams, <U+017F>ee Prides ju<U+017F>t fall.</l>
            <l>The frequent Subject of our prayers,</l>
            <l>Is length of life, and many years.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>Ip<U+017F>um compedibus qui vinxer at<note n="a" place="bottom">ENNOSIGAEUM Neptunum a Graecis <U+017F>ic dictum quia fluctibus concutit terram.</note> Enno<U+017F>igaeum</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="bottom">MITIUS: Ironia mitius et cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentius egit Xerxes cum Neptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no quod illi <U+017F>tigma non inu<U+017F><U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ut mos erat vernis fugitivis.</note> Mitius id <U+017F>ane, quod non et <U+017F>tigmate dignum</l>
               <l>Credidit<note n="c" place="bottom">HUIC verba Poetae huic tam <U+017F>tulto et ve<U+017F>ano regi, aliquis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum vellet in<U+017F>ervire?</note> huic qui<U+017F>quam vellet <U+017F>ervire Deorum?</l>
               <l>Sed qualis rediit? nempe una nave cruentis</l>
               <l>Fluctibus, ac tardo per den<U+017F>a cadavera prora,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="bottom">HAS Conclu<U+017F>io hujus mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bri de Gloria bellica. Haec et con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>imilia mala at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> pericula paenae loco exegit Gloria, ab Hanibale Alexandro et Xerxe et aliis, Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria inquam quam ip<U+017F>i toties exop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taverant.</note> Has toties optata exegit gloria poenas.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="e" place="bottom">DA SPATIUM: pergit jam ad votum longae vitae et <U+017F>enectutis cujus mi<U+017F>erias accurate de<U+017F>cribit et depingit.</note> Da <U+017F>patium vitae, multos da Jupiter anmos:</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:93159:25"/>
We boldly urge the<U+017F>e fair Petitions</l>
            <l>In health &amp; <U+017F>ickne<U+017F>s; all conditions:</l>
            <l>But what ince<U+017F><U+017F>ant plagues and ills</l>
            <l>The Gulf of Age with mi<U+017F>chief fills?</l>
            <l>Where meeting tides of <U+017F>orrows flow</l>
            <l>As Rivers in the Ocean do.</l>
            <l>Ugly deform'd the frightful Elves</l>
            <l>Dete<U+017F>ted grow, unlike them<U+017F>elves.</l>
            <l>In<U+017F>tead of skin, on their out-<U+017F>ide</l>
            <l>A wither'd and di<U+017F>colour'd hide;</l>
            <l>They with long Nayles, like tallons claw</l>
            <l>Their rivell'd toothle<U+017F>s lanthorn jaw:</l>
            <l>As a lean mumping Grandam Ape</l>
            <l>Her hollow wrinkled chops doth <U+017F>crape,</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="bottom">HOC: non demi<U+017F><U+017F>o vultu &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ut caetera vota petunt omni vitae tempore laetus aut tri<U+017F>tis <U+017F>anus vel egrotus.</note> Hoc recto vultu <U+017F>olum, hoc &amp;<note n="b" place="bottom">PALLIDUS: anxius, <U+017F>ollicitus, pallens ex metu vel ex morbo.</note> pallidus optas;</l>
               <l>Sed quam continuis, &amp; quantis longa <U+017F>enectus</l>
               <l>Plena malis: deformem, &amp; tetrum ante omnia vultum</l>
               <l>Di<U+017F><U+017F>imilemque<note n="c" place="bottom">SUI: olim juvenis di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>imilem.</note> <U+017F>ui, deformem pro cute<note n="d" place="bottom">PELLEM: <U+017F>ic pellem acute di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tingunt, ut cutis haereat vivis pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis mortuis.</note> pellem,</l>
               <l>Pendente<U+017F>que genas<note n="e" place="bottom">ET TALES:. Ordo e<U+017F>t: tales in <U+017F>enibus rugas a<U+017F>pice, quales <U+017F>imia jam mater <U+017F>ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pit in vetula bucca (in illa regione) ubi Tabarcha pandit <U+017F>altus umbriferos.</note> &amp; tales a<U+017F>pice rugas,</l>
               <l>Quales, umbriferos ubi pandit<note n="f" place="bottom">TABARCHA: in <U+017F>ilvis juxta Tabarcham in Africa minori <U+017F>imiarum plenis.</note> Tabraca <U+017F>alius,</l>
               <l>In vetula <U+017F>calpit jam<note n="g" place="bottom">I MATER SIMIA: anno<U+017F>a &amp; ob id deformior.</note> mater <U+017F>imia bucca.</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:93159:26"/>
Bright glorious Youth inchants our <U+017F>ight</l>
            <l>With various objects of delight;</l>
            <l>This a more hand<U+017F>ome face can <U+017F>how</l>
            <l>Than that call graceful well-<U+017F>hap'd <hi>Beau:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>In <U+017F>ong and dance this <U+017F>park is rare,</l>
            <l>He Fences, Rides, Vaults, flings the Bar.</l>
            <l>No diffr'ing forms our fancy <U+017F>trike,</l>
            <l>In extream age, they're all alike;</l>
            <l>Weak trembling voice, their hair all <U+017F>hed</l>
            <l>Off from their paralitick head.</l>
            <l>Th'old Dotard to new Childhood comes,</l>
            <l>A dripping No<U+017F>e, and toothle<U+017F>s Gums:</l>
            <l>While his loath'd painful Dreggs of Life</l>
            <l>Nau<U+017F>eat his Children and his Wife;</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>Plurima <U+017F>unt juvenum di<U+017F>crimina, pulchrior ille</l>
               <l>Hoc, atque ille alio: multum hic robu<U+017F>tior illo.</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>na <U+017F>enum facies, cum voce trementia membra,</l>
               <l>Et jam<note n="a" place="bottom">LEVE: Calvum.</note> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve caput, madidique<note n="b" place="bottom">INFANTIA in<U+017F>tar in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>antium. vel jam in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ecunda infantia.</note> infantia na<U+017F>i,</l>
               <l>Frangerdus mi<U+017F>ero gingiva panis<note n="c" place="bottom">INERMI: Edentula</note> inermi.</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g><U+017F>que adeo gravis uxori, nati<U+017F>que <U+017F>ibique,</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:93159:26"/>
So loath'd, makes ev'n the Stomack ri<U+017F>e</l>
            <l>Of Rogues, who fawn for Legacies.</l>
            <l>Their Pallat's gon, nor Wine, nor Meat,</l>
            <l>Can plea<U+017F>e their no Ta<U+017F>t when they eat.</l>
            <l>Nor Beauty moves, nor Cupids dart:</l>
            <l>Forgetfulne<U+017F>s has <U+017F>eiz'd that part.</l>
            <l>Long <U+017F>ince he there has been bewitcht,</l>
            <l>'Tis a longe Age <U+017F>ince la<U+017F>t he itcht.</l>
            <l>Ob<U+017F>equious hand cannot excite</l>
            <l>The bafled Craven to the fight;</l>
            <l>From hoary loynes, and <U+017F>aple<U+017F>s trunk,</l>
            <l>In vain <U+017F>trives the indu<U+017F>trious punk</l>
            <l>To rai<U+017F>e the nerve quite num'd and <U+017F>hrunk.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>t captatori moveat fa<U+017F>tidia<note n="a" place="bottom">COSSO heredi petae ip<U+017F>i.</note> Co<U+017F><U+017F>o.</l>
               <l>Non eadem vini, atque cibi torpente palato</l>
               <l>Gaudia: nam coitus jam long a oblivio. vel <U+017F>i</l>
               <l>Coneris, jacet exiguus cum<note n="b" place="bottom">RAMICE: Hermia <U+017F>croti tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</note> ramice nervus,</l>
               <l>Et, quamvis tota palpetur nocte jacebit.</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:93159:27"/>
In <hi>Limberhams,</hi> if <hi>Will</hi> <U+017F>urvive,</l>
            <l>The impotents new ways contrive:</l>
            <l>Having exhau<U+017F>ted Natures Source</l>
            <l>To filthy arts will have recour<U+017F>e.</l>
            <l>His <hi>Hearing</hi> next is lo<U+017F>t, what joys</l>
            <l>Can he receive from Min<U+017F>tril Boys:</l>
            <l>Once in their Golden Liv'rys, lac'd,</l>
            <l>Before retrenchment had uncas'd:</l>
            <l>What boots a Le<U+017F><U+017F>on on the flute,</l>
            <l>Or if<note n="*" place="margin">A Per<U+017F>on famous for his Skill and
Hand on the Lute.</note> 
               <hi>La' Tou'r</hi> <U+017F>hould touch his Lute.</l>
            <l>If he would pa<U+017F>s his time at th' <hi>Opera,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>'Tis all to him an idle Foppery;</l>
            <l>Since plac'd either remote or near,</l>
            <l>No Actors voice can reach his ear.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>Anne aliquid <U+017F>perare pote<U+017F>t haec inguinis aegri</l>
               <l>Canities? quid, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d meritò<note n="a" place="bottom">
                     <p>SUSPECTA LIBIDO: Qui <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>enerem affectant fine viribus &amp; in coitu operam prae<U+017F>tare non po<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>int merito <U+017F>u<U+017F>pecti <U+017F>unt ne <U+017F>int fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latores ita enim <U+017F>acilius arrigan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, unde Martial<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</p>
                     <p>Summa petas i<U+017F>tic mentula vivit annus.</p>
                     <q>Quid me Thai <U+017F>enem <U+017F>ubinde dicis Nemo e<U+017F>t Thais <U+017F>enex ad irrumandum.
<bibl>Idem lib. 4. Ep. 50.</bibl>
                     </q>
                     <p>Senectus <U+017F>aepe promior e<U+017F>t ad id genus libidinis ut <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uit Tiberius: vide Suetoni. Cap. 44.</p>
                  </note> <U+017F>u<U+017F>pecta libido e<U+017F>t,</l>
               <l>Quae <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>enerem affect at <U+017F>ine viribus? ad<U+017F>pice<note n="b" place="bottom">PARTIS: Auditus.</note> partis</l>
               <l>Jam damnum alterius. nam quae cantante voluptas,</l>
               <l>Sit licet eximius citharaedus? <U+017F>ive <U+017F>eleucus,</l>
               <l>Et quibus aurata mos est fulgere lacerna.</l>
               <l>Quid refert magni <U+017F>edeat qua parte Theatri,</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:93159:27"/>He <U+017F>carcely hears the neighbr'ng noy<U+017F>e,</l>
            <l>Of Cornets, Trumpets, or Ho-boyes.</l>
            <l>His <U+017F>ervant in his ear mu<U+017F>t hollow</l>
            <l>Who vi<U+017F>its, or what hour does follow.</l>
            <l>Through his chill veins, no pul<U+017F>e does beat</l>
            <l>Lifes march; them only Feavers heat;</l>
            <l>All Maladies unite their force,</l>
            <l>Be<U+017F>ieging round his rotten cour<U+017F>e.</l>
            <l>And <U+017F>hould I <U+017F>trive of each di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e,</l>
            <l>To give the names and qualities.</l>
            <l>I'de <U+017F>ooner mu<U+017F>ter all the kept</l>
            <l>Stallions have ca<U+017F>t <hi>Aurelia</hi> lept:</l>
            <l>Reckon tho<U+017F>e Quacks la<U+017F>t Autum kild;</l>
            <l>And graves by<note n="*" place="margin">The new-found-wells at <hi>I<U+017F>ling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> <U+017F>o called.</note> Lou<U+017F>y-Tunbridge fill'd.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>Qui vix cornicines exaudiat, atque tubarum</l>
               <l>Concentus? clamore opus e<U+017F>t, ut <U+017F>entiat auris,</l>
               <l>Quem dicat veni<U+017F><U+017F>e puer, quot nunciat horas.</l>
               <l>Praeterea minimus gelido jam in corpore <U+017F>anguis</l>
               <l>Febre calet <U+017F>ola: circum<U+017F>ilit agmine facto</l>
               <l>Morborum omne genus: quorum <U+017F>i nomina quaeras,</l>
               <l>Promptius expediam, quot amaverit<note n="a" place="bottom">HIPPIA: Uxor Fabricio Vigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toni Romano Senatori, fuit maecha famo<U+017F>i<U+017F><U+017F>ima cum quodam Sergio gladiatori maecho <U+017F>uo in Aegyptum profugit.</note> Hippia maechos,</l>
               <l>Quos<note n="b" place="bottom">THEMISON: Medicus.</note> Themi<U+017F>on aegros autumno occideret uno,</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:93159:28"/>
What fellow Subjects were for Gold,</l>
            <l>As Slaves, by needy Vice-Roy <U+017F>old.</l>
            <l>Each heir by dice, drink, whores, or masking</l>
            <l>Or <hi>Sti<U+017F>tead</hi> brought unto the<note n="*" place="margin">The Cant word for a Pri<U+017F>on.</note> Naskin;</l>
            <l>Or Gallants Back in am'rous play,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Mall Hinton</hi> dreyn'd dry in a day:</l>
            <l>Count every School boy, name each Child</l>
            <l>By Chickin-treading Pedant <U+017F>poyl'd.</l>
            <l>Survey each Lordly Seat and Mannour</l>
            <l>Po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>t by valet Pimp of Honour.</l>
            <l>For Pains in back and knees this cryes;</l>
            <l>This mourns the lo<U+017F>s of both his eyes;</l>
            <l>Envyes the pur-blind; with pale lips,</l>
            <l>From others fingers feeds and <U+017F>ipps:</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>Quot<note n="a" place="bottom">BASILUS Quot provinciales in Societatem Romanam receptos, Ba<U+017F>ilus ille praefectus <U+017F>poliaverit.</note> 
                  <hi>Ba<U+017F>ilus <U+017F>ocios, quot circum<U+017F>crip<U+017F>erit</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="bottom">MAURA Quot medios viros, una die famo<U+017F>a illa et procera meretrix Maura lambendo, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere, et concubitu, exhauriat.</note> Hirrus</l>
               <l>Pupillos, quot longa viros ex<U+017F>orbeat uno</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="bottom">HIRRUS Quot pupillos <U+017F>uae tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elae commi<U+017F><U+017F>os, infidelis ille et frandulentus Tutor deceperit, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frauderit, et circumvenerit.</note> 
                  <hi>Maur a die, quot di<U+017F>cipulas inclinat</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="bottom">HAMILLUS Quot di<U+017F>cipul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s ille Pedagogus Sodomiticus ad <U+017F>tuprum inclinavit.</note> 
                  <hi>Hamillus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Percurram citius quot villas po<U+017F><U+017F>ideat nunc,</l>
               <l>Quo tondente gravis juveni mihi barba <U+017F>onabat.</l>
               <l>Ille humero, bic lumbis, bic coxa debilis, ambos</l>
               <l>Perdidit ille oculos, et lu<U+017F>cis invidet, hujus</l>
               <l>Pallida labra cibum capiunt digitis alienis.</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:93159:28"/>
With mouth wide ope like barrel bung,</l>
            <l>Or gapeing bill of <U+017F>wallows young;</l>
            <l>To whom the hungry Old-one brings</l>
            <l>The hunted prey with Joyful wings.</l>
            <l>But the num'd brains <U+017F>tupidity,</l>
            <l>Does all the members lo<U+017F>s out-vy:</l>
            <l>When th' Organs of the mind <U+017F>hall leave,</l>
            <l>To do their Office, and bereave</l>
            <l>Of Memory, then they forego,</l>
            <l>The knowledge both of friend and foe;</l>
            <l>Forget their Ancient Servants quite,</l>
            <l>And friends with whom they <U+017F>upp'd la<U+017F>t night;</l>
            <l>Their Children they no longer know;</l>
            <l>And by unnat'ral Will be<U+017F>tow</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>Ip<U+017F>e ad con<U+017F>pectum caenae diducere victum</l>
               <l>Suetus, hiat tantum, c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u pullus hirundinis, ad quem</l>
               <l>Ore volat pleno mater jejunia. Sed omni</l>
               <l>Membrorum damno major<note n="a" place="bottom">DEMENTIA: Subjungit jam plurima alia <U+017F>enectutis incommoda, et primo quidem quod plerique bis pueri <U+017F>enes <U+017F>iunt: Ordo e<U+017F>t, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentia omni Membrorum damno (quod <U+017F>enes caeci <U+017F>urdi vel claudi evadunt) major e<U+017F>t; Ouo <U+017F><gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ilicet animus prae<U+017F>tat corpore, ita Memoriae, rationis et mentis organorum, ami<U+017F><gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>io, defectibus corporalibus ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor e<U+017F>t, cum ratio titubet, Memoria f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>acci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>et, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> dementi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, quae nec</l>
               <l>Nomina <U+017F>ervorum, nec vultum agno<U+017F><gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it ami<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Cum quo praeterit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> caenavit noct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, nec illos</l>
               <l>Quos genuit, quos eduxit; nam<note n="b" place="bottom">NAM CODICE SAEVO; Saevis, iniquis, et inju<U+017F>tis, Te<U+017F>tamenti tabulis, <U+017F>uos liberos exhaeredant.</note> codice <U+017F>aevo</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:93159:29"/>
Their goods, on their lewd Cockatrice,</l>
            <l>Who<U+017F>e Mouth's the very <U+017F>ink of Vice:</l>
            <l>So much it's artifice prevails,</l>
            <l>Above all Charms of wanton Tailes.</l>
            <l>Who many years at <hi>Whet<U+017F>tone</hi> ply'd,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Morefields</hi> and other <hi>Stews</hi> be<U+017F>ide;</l>
            <l>At Brothel doors <U+017F>tood wheedling in</l>
            <l>Unwary Woodcocks to the Gin;</l>
            <l>If the Minds faculties continue</l>
            <l>Firm, and in age <U+017F>till vigorous in you,</l>
            <l>What troubles mu<U+017F>t afflict your thoughts,</l>
            <l>While your lov'd children crowd Church-vaults</l>
            <l>U<U+017F>h'red by you, Wives, Brothers, come</l>
            <l>To Natures dark retiring room.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>Haredes vetat e<U+017F><U+017F>e <U+017F>uos,<note n="a" place="bottom">BONA: tota ferunturad Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alem meritricem &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ellatricem <U+017F>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, quam ex a<U+017F><U+017F>e haeredem coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tituit, quae <U+017F>eni libidino<U+017F>o &amp; ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumatori fellandi ob<U+017F>equio <U+017F>ervi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, eju<U+017F>que animum <U+017F>ibi devin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciebat.</note> bona tot a feruntur</l>
               <l>Ad Phial<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m: ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tum artificis valet halitus oris,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="bottom">QUOD: per os intelligit Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alem meritricem: quae <U+017F>teterat id e<U+017F>t more meriticio prae<U+017F>tabat Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panari, nam meritrices prae o<U+017F>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um pro<U+017F>tibuli vel fornicis blandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiis <U+017F>cortatores allicientes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>titere <U+017F>olebant.</note> 
                  <hi>Quod <U+017F>tet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rat multis in Carcere fornicis annis.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="c" place="bottom">UT VIGEANT: tamen multi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tiam in extrema <U+017F>enectute, corpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, &amp; animo vigeant. Re<U+017F>pondit Poeta objectioni; Ut maxime vigeant, tamen in longa illa vita, multa quae nolint, vident, omni morte graviora. Ut mortem filiorum, conjugis, fratris, <U+017F>ororis, &amp; allos luctus, maerores, &amp; aerumnas innumeras.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>t vigeant <U+017F>en<U+017F>us animi, ducenda tamen <U+017F>unt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fumra natorum, rogus a<U+017F>piciendus amatae</l>
               <l>Conjugis, &amp; fratris.—</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:93159:29"/>
Nor can your care or <U+017F>orrow <U+017F>ave</l>
            <l>Your belov'd Si<U+017F>ters from the Grave.</l>
            <l>The<U+017F>e are the Comforts always wait</l>
            <l>On tho<U+017F>e who long defer their Fate.</l>
            <l>Still the fre<U+017F>h <U+017F>laughter of their Hou<U+017F>e</l>
            <l>Malitiou<U+017F>ly their grief renews:</l>
            <l>While cruel providence decreed</l>
            <l>They mu<U+017F>t grow old in mourning weed.</l>
            <l>Death Nature's debt, where long delay'd</l>
            <l>With cruel U<U+017F>ury is paid.</l>
            <l>King (27) <hi>Ne<U+017F>tor, Homers</hi> Records <U+017F>how</l>
            <l>In length of life, came next the Crow,</l>
            <l>Wore out more lives, as <U+017F>tory's told,</l>
            <l>Than Cat, Intayl, or Copy-hold.</l>
            <l>His happy years were ju<U+017F>tly wondred,</l>
            <l>That had <U+017F>urviv'd above three hundred.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>—plenaeque <U+017F>ororibus<note n="a" place="bottom">URNAE: va<U+017F>a in quibus mortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum cineres componebantur, po<U+017F>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam corpus ar<U+017F>i<U+017F><U+017F>ent.</note> urnae</l>
               <l>Haec data poena diu viventibus, ut renovata</l>
               <l>Semper clade domus multis in luctibus, inque</l>
               <l>Perpetuo maerore &amp; nigra ve<U+017F>te <U+017F>ene<U+017F>cunt.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="bottom">REX PILIUS: Ne<U+017F>tor, cujus exemplo demon<U+017F>trat, illos qui di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vivunt multa mala experire. Dicitur tertiam u<U+017F>que aetatem vixi<U+017F><U+017F>e id e<U+017F>t 300 anno, &amp; proxime ad cornicis ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem acce<U+017F><U+017F>it, quae vivere dicitur novem <U+017F>aecula vel aetates.</note> 
                  <hi>Rex Pylius, magno <U+017F>i quicquam credis Homero,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Exemplum vitae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uit a cornice <U+017F>ecundae.</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:93159:30"/>
Bore Winters Fro<U+017F>ts, and Summers thir<U+017F>t,</l>
            <l>As oft drank wine upon the mu<U+017F>t.</l>
            <l>See in what melancholly <U+017F>trains,</l>
            <l>Of the <hi>three Si<U+017F>ters</hi> he complains;</l>
            <l>Why they <U+017F>hould <U+017F>pin his Thread <U+017F>o tough</l>
            <l>Of cur<U+017F>ed everla<U+017F>ting <U+017F>tuff:</l>
            <l>Har<U+017F>h Laws! when the <U+017F>urviving Sire</l>
            <l>Waits bearded Son to fun'ral fire.</l>
            <l>In rage expo<U+017F>tulates why he</l>
            <l>Survives to <U+017F>o much mi<U+017F>ery:</l>
            <l>And <U+017F>o what Sin of his, the Hate</l>
            <l>Of Heavens Decrees <U+017F>uch lingring Fate:</l>
            <l>So <hi>Peleus</hi> for <hi>Achilles (28)</hi> cry'd,</l>
            <l>Snatch'd in the Temple from his Bride,</l>
            <l>Death in the nick the <hi>Banes</hi> deny'd:</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>Felix nimirum, qui tot per <U+017F>ecula mortem</l>
               <l>Di<U+017F>tulit, aique <U+017F>uos jam<note n="a" place="bottom">DEXTRA: Graeci numerum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fra centum digitis <U+017F>ini<U+017F>trae numera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur, numerum verò centarium &amp; illo majorem digitis dextrae.</note> dextra comput at annos,</l>
               <l>Quique novum toties mu<U+017F>tum bibit, oro, parumper</l>
               <l>Attendas, quantum de legibus ip<U+017F>e queratur</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="bottom">FACTORUM Parcarum: quod Atropos non citius <U+017F>tamen abrupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</note> 
                  <hi>Factorum, &amp; nimio de <U+017F>tamine, cum videt</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="bottom">ACRIS: fortis, bellico<U+017F>i. Hic enim Antilochus cum patri opem ferre vellet a Memnone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uit occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>us.</note> 
                  <hi>acris</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="bottom">ANTILOCHI: cum deflet filium <U+017F>uum cum ejus cadaver com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bureretur.</note> 
                  <hi>Antilochi barbam ardentem: tum quaerit ab omni</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Qui<U+017F>quis ade<U+017F>t <U+017F>ocius: cur haec in tempore duret,</l>
               <l>Quid facinus dignum tam longo admi<U+017F>erit aev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>Haec eadem<note n="e" place="bottom">PELEUS: Aeaci filius, Pater A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chillis, qui cum Pollixinae nuptias <U+017F>peraret in Templo Apolinis, ab Paride &amp; Diaphob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> <U+017F>agittis con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>us e<U+017F>t.</note> Peleus raptum cum luget A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hillem.</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:93159:30"/>
               <hi>Uly<U+017F><U+017F>es</hi> aged Sire did moan</l>
            <l>The ten years ramble of his Son:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Priam (29)</hi> had dy'd a happy <U+017F>hade</l>
            <l>E're <hi>Troy</hi> had been in rubbi<U+017F>h lay'd</l>
            <l>His mournful Rites with Pomp and State,</l>
            <l>Perform'd by peaceful Magi<U+017F>trate;</l>
            <l>His Corps born up by <hi>Hectors</hi> <U+017F>houlder,</l>
            <l>(Than whom, no Mortal e're was bolder)</l>
            <l>And'<hi>s</hi> fifty Sons, tall Bully-Rocks,</l>
            <l>As ever <U+017F>prung from Kingly Stocks.</l>
            <l>E're Fair <hi>Ca<U+017F><U+017F>andra</hi> Fate fore knowing</l>
            <l>Bewayl'd <U+017F>ack'd <hi>Troy,</hi> with eyes o're-flowing;</l>
            <l>Had he been dead as any Herring,</l>
            <l>E're <hi>Paris</hi> went a privateering;</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>Atque<note n="a" place="bottom">ALIUS: Laertes <U+017F>enex lugens filium <U+017F>uum Uly<U+017F><U+017F>em Ithacae ducem, orbem decem annos pererrantem &amp; navigantem.</note> alius, cui fas Ithacum l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gere natantem.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="bottom">INCOLUMI TROJA: id e<U+017F>t felix etiam fui<U+017F><U+017F>et Priamus, <U+017F>i Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ja adhuc incolumi, &amp; florente reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no, vel ante excidium, &amp; Trojae in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendium, mort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us <U+017F>ui<U+017F><U+017F>et, tunc enim magnis <U+017F>olemnibus à quinquaginta fili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s <U+017F>uis funus ejus deductum fui<U+017F><U+017F>et, &amp; tot mala, regnique <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ui interitum, non <U+017F>ui<U+017F><U+017F>et expertus.</note> 
                  <hi>Incolumi Tro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a Primus veni<U+017F><U+017F>et<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ad umbras</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A<U+017F><U+017F>araei magnis <U+017F>olennibus, H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctore funus</l>
               <l>Portante, ac reliquis fractrum<note n="c" place="bottom">CERVICIBUS. Ex veterum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>uetudine hoc dicit, nam filii olim funus patris portabat.</note> cervicibus, inter</l>
               <l>Iliadum lacrymas, ut primos eder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> planctus</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="bottom">CASSANDRA: Quia vates e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, &amp; futuri con<U+017F>cia mortem Patris <U+017F>civi<U+017F><U+017F>et, &amp; ante reliquas <U+017F>orores <U+017F>uas calamitates Patris &amp; Trojae flevi<U+017F><U+017F>et.</note> 
                  <hi>Ca<U+017F><U+017F>andra inciperet, <U+017F>ci<U+017F><U+017F>aque pollixina palla:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Si foret extinctus diver<U+017F>o tempore, quo non</l>
               <l>Creperat audaces<note n="e" place="bottom">PARIS: Si mortuus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ui<U+017F><U+017F>et Priamus, priu<U+017F>quam Paris <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ilius, ejus audaces naves illas aedificabat, quibus H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llenam Menelai Conjugem abducebat, quae rapina cau<U+017F>a <U+017F>uit excidii urbis Trojani.</note> Paris aedi<U+017F>icare Carinas.</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:93159:31"/>
For Whores and Plunder play'd le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Tricks,</l>
            <l>Which to the Gutts provok'd the Greeks.</l>
            <l>Who Clubbing in Revenge o' re-turn'd</l>
            <l>Their State, and Pyrat-City burn'd:</l>
            <l>At la<U+017F>t the trembling King throw's by</l>
            <l>His Turbant, and to's arms does fly;</l>
            <l>Buckles on's harne<U+017F>s, and invirons</l>
            <l>His weak limbs with unweildy irons.</l>
            <l>And at <hi>Joves</hi> Shrine re<U+017F>ignes his life,</l>
            <l>As an old Ox under the Knife.</l>
            <l>His weak-worn u<U+017F>ele<U+017F>s neck does bow,</l>
            <l>Ca<U+017F>heir'd from the ungrateful Plow.</l>
            <l>His griefs how er'e a period found,</l>
            <l>And in deaths deep aby<U+017F>s were drown'd.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>Long a dies igitur quid contulit? omnia vidif</l>
               <l>Ever<U+017F>a, &amp; flammis A<U+017F>iam ferroque cadentem.</l>
               <l>Tunc miles tremulus po<U+017F>ita tulit arma Tiara,</l>
               <l>Et ruit ante aram <U+017F>ummi Jovis, ut vetulus Bos,</l>
               <l>Qui domini cultris tenue &amp; mi<U+017F>erabile collum</l>
               <l>Praebet, ab ingrato jam fa<U+017F>tiditus aratro.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="bottom">EXITUS: demon<U+017F>trat Poeta his verbis, mortem &amp; fatum Pria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi fui<U+017F><U+017F>e tolerabilem &amp; multo op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabiliorem, quam mi<U+017F>erimae re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lictae conjugis ejus Hecubae.</note> Exitus ille utrunque hominis.</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:93159:31"/>
The Gods to his grim <U+017F>narling wife,</l>
            <l>Prolong'd indignities with life.</l>
            <l>Chang'd and deform'd to <U+017F>uch a pitch,</l>
            <l>Through rage, <U+017F>he dy'd, a barking bitch.</l>
            <l>Why <U+017F>hould we for Examples roam</l>
            <l>Abroad, when choice are found at home?</l>
            <l>The (30) <hi>Pontick</hi> King I will omit,</l>
            <l>And <hi>Crae<U+017F>us</hi> taught by <hi>Solons</hi> wit.</l>
            <l>We can pronounce none happy, none,</l>
            <l>Till the la<U+017F>t Sand of life be run.</l>
            <l>None ju<U+017F>tly we good Actors call,</l>
            <l>In lifes farce, till deaths Curtains fall.</l>
            <l>(31) <hi>Marius</hi> long-life was th'only rea<U+017F>on,</l>
            <l>Of Exile and Minturnian Pri<U+017F>on.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>—Sed torva canino</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="bottom">LATRAVIT: <hi>Hecuba</hi> capta Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ja in canem ver<U+017F>a fuit ut Ovidius li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bro 13 Metamorphos &amp; Virgilius: occa<U+017F>io fabulae putatur, quod cum a Graecis captiva abduceretur &amp; <U+017F>ili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ui Polidori corpus in mare fluctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antem agnovi<U+017F><U+017F>et, quoniam aliter injuriam ulci<U+017F><U+017F>ci non po<U+017F><U+017F>et, ami<U+017F><U+017F>a patentia, Graecos inanibus lace<U+017F><U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verit convitiis.</note> Latravit rictu, quae po<U+017F>t hunc vixerat, uxor.</l>
               <l>Fe<U+017F>tino ad no<U+017F>tros, &amp;<note n="b" place="bottom">REGEM: Mithridatem qui vixit anno 69 &amp; cum Romanis 40 annos varia bella ge<U+017F><U+017F>it 57 annis regna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit: a Sylla, Lucullo, &amp; Pompeio ter victus fuit, vitae &amp; belli taedia; cum non po<U+017F><U+017F>et veneno gladio vitam finivit.</note> regem tran<U+017F>eo Ponti,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="c" place="bottom">ET CRAESUM: Regem Lydiae diti<U+017F><U+017F>imum Solonem often<U+017F>o the<U+017F>auro rogavit vidi<U+017F><U+017F>et ne aliquem feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciorem? re<U+017F>pondit Philo<U+017F>ophus neminem b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atum judicandum ante obitum, <U+017F>ic Ovidius, <hi>Ante obitum nemo <U+017F>upremaque funera felix.</hi>
                  </note> Et Crae<U+017F>um, quem vox ju<U+017F>ti facunda Solonis</l>
               <l>Re<U+017F>picere ad longae ju<U+017F><U+017F>it <U+017F>patia ultima vitae.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="bottom">EXILIUM: Marium Arpinarem <U+017F>epties Con<U+017F>ul. vide Annotatione.</note> Exilium &amp; carcer, Minturnarumque paludes,</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:93159:32"/>
Made him beg bread for his relief,</l>
            <l>In <hi>Carthage</hi> where he once was chief.</l>
            <l>Nature did ne'r produce of old,</l>
            <l>Or <hi>Rome</hi> a happier man behold.</l>
            <l>Then <hi>Marius</hi> was, when he victorious,</l>
            <l>Proce<U+017F><U+017F>ion made in Chariot glorious;</l>
            <l>With Trophys and attending <U+017F>poyles,</l>
            <l>And Captives chain'd in ranks and files.</l>
            <l>Had Death <U+017F>natch'd his Tryumphing Spirit,</l>
            <l>That day, none e're had match'd his merit.</l>
            <l>Kind Fate, de<U+017F>igning to befriend</l>
            <l>Great (32) <hi>Pompey,</hi> did a Feaver <U+017F>end,</l>
            <l>That <U+017F>hould with favourable doom,</l>
            <l>Prevent his mi<U+017F>eries to come.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>Et mendicatus victa Carthagine panis,</l>
               <l>Hinc cau<U+017F>as habuere. Quid illo cive tuli<U+017F><U+017F><gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t</l>
               <l>Natura in terris, quid Roma beatius unquam,</l>
               <l>Si circum ducto Captivorum agmine, &amp; omni,</l>
               <l>Bellorum pompa, animam exhala<U+017F><U+017F>et opimam,</l>
               <l>Cum de I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utoni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o vellet de<U+017F>cendere curru?</l>
               <l>Provida<note n="a" place="bottom">POMPEIO: Exemplum Pompeii magni, qui ante bellum civile Correptus e<U+017F>t <U+017F>ebre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aventi &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevola, quia mortem &amp; ignominiam provide prevenire praecaveret, quae mors cum honor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ante<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> bellum civile illi optanda fui<U+017F><U+017F>et ne victus, ab Achilla obtruncaretur.</note> Pompeio dederat Campania felres</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Optandas:</hi>—</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:93159:32"/>
Whole Nations for his danger griev'd;</l>
            <l>Their publick prayers obtain, Repriev'd.</l>
            <l>Fate then that honour'd head did <U+017F>ave,</l>
            <l>Which <U+017F>he t' in<U+017F>ulting <hi>Cae<U+017F>ar</hi> gave.</l>
            <l>Slow <hi>Lentulus</hi> ne're underwent,</l>
            <l>For Trea<U+017F>on <U+017F>uch a Puni<U+017F>hment:</l>
            <l>Nor Ra<U+017F>h <hi>Cethegus,</hi> (33) <hi>Cataline</hi>
            </l>
            <l>A Corps intire in Arms did Shine.</l>
            <l>'Tis the fond Mothers con<U+017F>tant prayer</l>
            <l>Her Children may be pa<U+017F><U+017F>ing Fair.</l>
            <l>Excelling far all other faces,</l>
            <l>In beauty and rare Charming graces.</l>
            <l>Which Boon they beg with <U+017F>ighs and groans,</l>
            <l>Ince<U+017F><U+017F>antly on Marrow-bones.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>—Sed multae <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>rbes, &amp;<note n="a" place="bottom">PUBLICA VOTA quae a multis urbibus pro <U+017F>alute Pompeii Diis of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferebantur &amp; quae illum tantum a morte eripuerunt ut po<U+017F>tea mi<U+017F>eriùs moreretur ab Achilla occi<U+017F>us.</note> publica vota</l>
               <l>Vicerunt, igitur Fortuna ip<U+017F>ius, &amp; urbis</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="bottom">SERVATUM Caput: Per preces aliquandiu <U+017F>ervatum, donec po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tea Pompeii a Cae<U+017F>are victi Caput amputatione e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>et ablatum.</note> Servatum victo caput ab<U+017F>tulit. Hoc Cruciatu</l>
               <l>Lentulus, hac paenae caruit, ceciditque Cethegus</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="c" place="bottom">INTEGER: <U+017F>c. <U+017F>ine capitis am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putatione quod <U+017F>coptice dicit.</note> Integer, &amp; jacuit Catilina cadavere toto.</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="d" place="bottom">FORMAM: Tran<U+017F>it poeta à divitiis Honoribus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ad votum pulchritudinis aeque cum caerteris per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitio<U+017F>um.</note> Formam optat Modico pueris, Majore puellis</l>
               <l>Murmure, cum Veneris fanum videt anxia mater</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g><U+017F>que ad delicias Votorum.—</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:93159:33"/>
Who ju<U+017F>tly blames a Mothers joy,</l>
            <l>That huggs her wanton well-hung-boy.</l>
            <l>Or if for joy <hi>Latona</hi> cry,</l>
            <l>To <U+017F>ee her pretty daughter <hi>Dy:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Yet bright (34) <hi>Lucretias</hi> <U+017F>ullen fate,</l>
            <l>Shews fair-ones are not fortunate.</l>
            <l>(35) <hi>Virginia's</hi> chance may well confute you;</l>
            <l>Good luck don't always wait on beauty:</l>
            <l>Th' unhappy Fair's in wor<U+017F>e e<U+017F>tate,</l>
            <l>Than a <hi>crump</hi> rich and fortunate.</l>
            <l>Concern for hand<U+017F>ome boys does make,</l>
            <l>Ill-boading Parents hearts to ake.</l>
            <l>Still dreading mi<U+017F>chiefs when they <U+017F>ee,</l>
            <l>Few fair ones fam'd for Cha<U+017F>tity.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>—cur tamen, inquit</l>
               <l>Corripias? pulchra gaudet Latona Diana.</l>
               <l>Sed vetat optari faciem Lucretia, qualem</l>
               <l>Ip<U+017F>a habuit, cuperet<note n="a" place="bottom">RUTILAE: Lura Rutila, gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo<U+017F>a &amp; deformis. 97 annos exce<U+017F><U+017F>it.</note> Rutilae<note n="b" place="bottom">VIRGINIA: a Patre <U+017F>uo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terempta, ne ab Appio Decemviro <U+017F>ervitutem redigeretur, &amp; ca<U+017F>titate violaretur.</note> Virginia gibbum</l>
               <l>Accip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re, atque <U+017F>uum Rutilae dare. Filius autem</l>
               <l>Corporis egregii mi<U+017F>eros trepido<U+017F>que parentes</l>
               <l>Semper habet—</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:93159:33"/>
Beauty and Virtue often jarr,</l>
            <l>Joyn'd in one Per<U+017F>on <U+017F>eldom are;</l>
            <l>Though bred in hone<U+017F>t Country Cell,</l>
            <l>Where no debauch'd Examples dwell;</l>
            <l>Whence Lu<U+017F>t is bani<U+017F>h't, Vertue <U+017F>ways,</l>
            <l>As in Queen <hi>Dick</hi>'s plain hone<U+017F>t days.</l>
            <l>Though Nature's bounteous hand <U+017F>hould plant</l>
            <l>All Graces that can make a Saint;</l>
            <l>And in one mode<U+017F>t Cheek unite</l>
            <l>The blu<U+017F>hing Red Ro<U+017F>e with the White;</l>
            <l>What ever Nature can impart,</l>
            <l>Nature more prevalent than Art;</l>
            <l>Yet Vice will try her utmo<U+017F>t Power,</l>
            <l>And Court them in a golden Shower:</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>—Rara est adeo Concordia formae</l>
               <l>Atque pudicitiae; <U+017F>anctos licet<note n="a" place="bottom">HORRIDA: <U+017F>implex &amp; inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta domus a libidine aliena.</note> horrida mores</l>
               <l>Tradiderit domus, ac veteres imitata<note n="b" place="bottom">SABINAS: mulieres ca<U+017F>ti<U+017F><U+017F>imas.</note> Sabinas,</l>
               <l>Praeterea ca<U+017F>tum ingenium, vult umque mode<U+017F>to</l>
               <l>Sanguine ferventem tribuat natura benigna</l>
               <l>Larga manu (quid enim puero conferre pote<U+017F>t plus</l>
               <l>Cu<U+017F>tode &amp; cura<note n="c" place="bottom">NATURA: naturae vis ad pudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citiam inclinata multò prevalentior in<U+017F>titutione, doctrina &amp; educatione.</note> natura potentior omni?)</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:93159:34"/>
To kidd-nap Youth will lye in wait,</l>
            <l>And <U+017F>nap it er'e at Mans E<U+017F>tate.</l>
            <l>So to corrupting bribes they'le tru<U+017F>t,</l>
            <l>They'le Parents tempt for bawds to lu<U+017F>t:</l>
            <l>No Tyrant will the ill-<U+017F>hap'd chu<U+017F>e</l>
            <l>For Guardian Eunuchs for their <hi>Stews.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Or on a Youth deform'd will pitch,</l>
            <l>To cure his <hi>Sodomitick</hi> itch.</l>
            <l>Go now applaud thy fair Sons Fate,</l>
            <l>For whom perhaps wor<U+017F>e dangers wait.</l>
            <l>Let him turn Stallion to the Town,</l>
            <l>And dread each hair-brain'd Husband's frown.</l>
            <l>And undergo for puni<U+017F>hment,</l>
            <l>What inrag'd Cuckolds can invent.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="bottom">NON LICET, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Scilicet <U+017F>i pulchri <U+017F>unt aut ca<U+017F>trantur aut corrumpuntur (i. e.) aut <U+017F>padones fiunt vel cinaedi.</note> Non licet e<U+017F><U+017F>e viros: nam prodiga corruptoris</l>
               <l>Improbitas ip<U+017F>os audet tentare parentes.</l>
               <l>Tanta in muneribus fiducia. Nullus ephebum</l>
               <l>Deformem <U+017F>aeva ca<U+017F>travit in<note n="b" place="bottom">ARCE: In Arce Tarpeia <U+017F>ole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat Nero ca<U+017F>trare pueros.</note> arce Tyrannus.</l>
               <l>Nec<note n="c" place="bottom">PRAETEXTATUM: nobilem puerum ad <U+017F>tuprum rapuit.</note> praetextatum rapuit Nero Loripedem, nec</l>
               <l>Strumo<U+017F>um, atque utero pariter, gibboque tumentem.</l>
               <l>I nunc, &amp; juvenis <U+017F>pecie laetare tui, quem</l>
               <l>Major a expectant di<U+017F>crimina. Fiet adulter</l>
               <l>Publicus, &amp; poenas metuet, qua<U+017F>cunque mariti</l>
               <l>Irati debent.—</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:93159:34"/>
Ne're let him think by Wit or Care</l>
            <l>Still luckily to <U+017F>cape the <U+017F>nare:</l>
            <l>Surpriz'd, undone, Trappan'd, be<U+017F>et,</l>
            <l>He'le fall like <hi>Mars</hi> into the Net.</l>
            <l>Then <U+017F>hall revenge quit his old Scores,</l>
            <l>And pay him home for pa<U+017F>t Amours:</l>
            <l>They'le <U+017F>lit his No<U+017F>e, or Crop his Ears,</l>
            <l>And whip off Gun and Bandileers:</l>
            <l>Di<U+017F>patch with Poy<U+017F>on, Steel, or Bullet,</l>
            <l>Or Fundament plugg'd with a (36) <hi>Mullet.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>But thy <hi>Endimion</hi> <U+017F>hall inflame</l>
            <l>None but <U+017F>ome choice fair wealthy Dame,</l>
            <l>By whom, profu<U+017F>ely cram'd with coin,</l>
            <l>His peerle<U+017F>s Pomp <U+017F>hall all out-<U+017F>hine.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>—nec erit felicior astro</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="bottom">MARTIS: depren<U+017F>i in laqueis cum Venere in adulterio.</note> Martis ut in laqueos nunquam incidat. Exigit autem</l>
               <l>Interdum ille dolor plus, quam lex ulla dolori</l>
               <l>Conce<U+017F><U+017F>it. Necat hic ferro, <U+017F>ecat ille cruentis</l>
               <l>Verberibus, quo<U+017F>dam moechos &amp;<note n="b" place="bottom">MUGILIS: Vetus depren<U+017F>orum maechorum <U+017F>upplicium, cum depil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant nates cinere calido, &amp; tunc mugiles, pi<U+017F>ces quo<U+017F>dam cum gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di capite in podicem immittebant.</note> mugilis intrat.</l>
               <l>Sed tuus<note n="c" place="bottom">NATUS: tuus formo<U+017F>us ut En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimion à luna amatus.</note> Endimion dilectae fiet adulter</l>
               <l>Matronoe:—</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:93159:35"/>
But when through vain Expence, or Play,</l>
            <l>His hoarded Bank <U+017F>hall melt away;</l>
            <l>He for recruit, mu<U+017F>t let to hire</l>
            <l>His Hackney Back, to the de<U+017F>ire</l>
            <l>Of <U+017F>ome old filthy Hagg for coyn,</l>
            <l>And <U+017F>ell the labour of his Chine;</l>
            <l>Then he mu<U+017F>t <U+017F>trip and buckle to't,</l>
            <l>Or from loath'd Task mu<U+017F>t reap no fruit.</l>
            <l>Whither by Nature free or ba<U+017F>e;</l>
            <l>No <hi>Buttock's</hi> hide-bound in this ca<U+017F>e:</l>
            <l>Or will be nigardly and grudge</l>
            <l>A lib'ral <U+017F>al'ry to her drudge.</l>
            <l>And if he '<U+017F>cape the<U+017F>e threatning Rocks,</l>
            <l>He'le <U+017F>urely <U+017F>hipwrack on the Pox:</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>—mox cum dederit<note n="a" place="bottom">SERVILIA: turpis &amp; de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis, mater Bruti.</note> Servilia nummos</l>
               <l>Fiet &amp; illius quam non amat,<note n="b" place="bottom">EXUET: omnia dabit, ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a ornamenta corporis, etiam ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>timenta <U+017F>ua ad <U+017F>atisficiendam libi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem.</note> exuet omnem</l>
               <l>Corporis ornatum; quid enim ulla negaverit<note n="c" place="bottom">UDIS: per udum inguen, mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brum muliebre intelligitur.</note> udis</l>
               <l>Inguinibus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ive e<U+017F>t haec<note n="d" place="bottom">HIPPIA: <U+017F>ive <U+017F>it prodiga &amp; nobilis ut Hippia, vel avara, ut Catulla.</note> Hippia <U+017F>ive Catulla?</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="e" place="bottom">DETERIOR: (i. e.) vel pe<U+017F><U+017F>ima faemina habet omnes mores, <hi>viz:</hi> liberalitatem beneficentiam <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in remunerandis Amatoribus.</note> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>terior totos habet illic faemina mores.</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:93159:35"/>
Ere throughly ripe he'l rot away,</l>
            <l>Like early fruits that <U+017F>oon decay:</l>
            <l>His <U+017F>mall remaining <U+017F>tock he trucks,</l>
            <l>With Quack for dyet-drink and Flux;</l>
            <l>In which his No<U+017F>e and Pallat fall,</l>
            <l>Rots peice-meal, noy<U+017F>ome grown to all;</l>
            <l>Ends his loath'd life in Ho<U+017F>pitall.</l>
            <l>What harm will hone<U+017F>t Beauty do,</l>
            <l>He may prove Cha<U+017F>t, and hand<U+017F>ome too.</l>
            <l>What did his<note n="*" place="margin">Hippolito.</note> rigid Vertue boot,</l>
            <l>That baulk'd his Step-dames lu<U+017F>tful <U+017F>uite:</l>
            <l>What did (37) <hi>Bellerephon</hi> betyde,</l>
            <l>When he returns of love deny'd?</l>
            <l>In both their <hi>Queans</hi> Revenge did Reign,</l>
            <l>Rows'd by repul<U+017F>e of Cold Di<U+017F>dain.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>Sed ca<U+017F>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quid forma nocet?<note n="a" place="bottom">QUID<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> 
                     <hi>&amp;c:</hi> re<U+017F>pondit hic ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectioni, o<U+017F>tendens exempla ca<U+017F>tita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis <U+017F>atalis &amp; exitialis in Hippolito &amp; Bellerophonte. Hippolitus erat fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius The<U+017F>ei, à Novercà Phaedriâ cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus ince<U+017F>to amori non re<U+017F>pondebat, apud patrem <U+017F>tupri fal<U+017F>o accu<U+017F>atus, dum patris iram <U+017F>ugeret, ab equis territis disjectus curru &amp; di<U+017F>cerptus e<U+017F>t. Bellerophon infinitis periculis expo<U+017F>itus e<U+017F>t, propter contemptum amorem Sthenobeae Praeti Regis Uxoris.</note> quid profuit immo</l>
               <l>Hipp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lyto grave propo<U+017F>itum, quid Bellerophonti?</l>
               <l>Erubuit nen pe haec, ceu fa<U+017F>tidita repul<U+017F>o.</l>
               <l>Nec Sthenobae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> minus quam<note n="b" place="bottom">CRESSA: Phaedria <U+017F>ic dicta, quia Minoidis Creten<U+017F>ium Regis Pilia,</note> Cre<U+017F><U+017F>a excanduit, &amp; <U+017F>e</l>
               <l>Conc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap><U+017F><U+017F>ere ambae—</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:93159:36"/>
Then Women rage with cruel'<U+017F>t <U+017F>pite</l>
            <l>When <U+017F>hame their hatred does excite:</l>
            <l>When trifling Lovers <U+017F>ea<U+017F>ons lo<U+017F>e,</l>
            <l>And kind advances do refu<U+017F>e:</l>
            <l>From loath'd Contempt of profer'd love</l>
            <l>Their Brea<U+017F>ts with furious tran<U+017F>ports move.</l>
            <l>Call Council quickly to advi<U+017F>e,</l>
            <l>Our pre<U+017F>ent Ca<U+017F>e proves very nice:</l>
            <l>Here's <hi>Cae<U+017F>ars</hi> (38) Wife re<U+017F>olv'd to marry,</l>
            <l>Nor for the Emperours Death will tarry.</l>
            <l>She has de<U+017F>ign'd with lu<U+017F>tful Eyes</l>
            <l>The Noble Youth her Sacrifice.</l>
            <l>The Prie<U+017F>t and honour'd Gue<U+017F>ts invites</l>
            <l>To witne<U+017F>s Matrimonial Rites.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>—mul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er <U+017F>aevi<U+017F><U+017F>ima tunc est,</l>
               <l>Cum <U+017F>timulos odio pudor admovet. Elige quid nam</l>
               <l>Suadendum e<U+017F><U+017F>e putes, cui nubere Cae<U+017F>aris uxor</l>
               <l>De<U+017F>tinat.<note n="a" place="bottom">OPTIMUS: Caius Silius, prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobilis Romanus, in quem exar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>it Me<U+017F><U+017F>alina Uxor Claudii (faemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Libidinis mon<U+017F>trum) &amp; qui co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actus di<U+017F>mi<U+017F><U+017F>a uxore <U+017F>ua palam Me<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>alinam ducere, re cognita ab Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratore necatus erat.</note> optimus hic, &amp; formo<U+017F>i<U+017F><U+017F>imus idem</l>
               <l>Gentis Patriciae rapitur mi<U+017F>er extinguendus</l>
               <l>Me<U+017F><U+017F>alinae occulis: dudum <U+017F>edet illa parato</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="b" place="bottom">FLAMEOLO: quo nova nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta operitur.</note> Flameolo—</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:93159:36"/>
The Portion's told, the Genial Bed</l>
            <l>With Pomp is in the Garden <U+017F>pread:</l>
            <l>Does with <hi>Capricious</hi> fancy burn;</l>
            <l>Marriage can only <U+017F>erve her turn:</l>
            <l>With which, if he will not comply</l>
            <l>He tempts his pre<U+017F>ent de<U+017F>tiny:</l>
            <l>What <U+017F>hall he do? obedience give,</l>
            <l>And that may gain a <U+017F>hort reprieve:</l>
            <l>Till all the Town the Story hears;</l>
            <l>At la<U+017F>t 'twill reach the Prince's ears.</l>
            <l>There's hopes in that, for the di<U+017F>grace</l>
            <l>The Cuckold learns in the la<U+017F>t place:</l>
            <l>Then to her Will obedience pay;</l>
            <l>Your Fate may thence admit delay,</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>—Tyriu<U+017F>que palam genialis in hortis</l>
               <l>Sternitur, &amp; ritu<note n="a" place="bottom">DECIES CENTENA: Se<U+017F>tertia, qui numerus erat legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timus &amp; <U+017F>olemnis in Dote lautio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, danda marito propter matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monii onera.</note> decies centena dabuntur</l>
               <l>Antiquo, veniet cum<note n="b" place="bottom">SIGNATORIBUS: Qui ob<U+017F>ignabant tabulas &amp; in<U+017F>trumenta matrimonii.</note> <U+017F>ignatoribus<note n="c" place="bottom">AUSPEX: Nullae nuptiae prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ertim Legitimae fiebant <U+017F>ine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>picio.</note> au<U+017F>pex.</l>
               <l>Haec tu <U+017F>ecreta, &amp; paucis commi<U+017F><U+017F>a putabas?</l>
               <l>Non ni<U+017F>i legitime vult nubere: quid placeat, dic:</l>
               <l>Ni parere velis, pereundum erit ante lucernas:</l>
               <l>Si <U+017F>celus admittas, dabitur mora parvula, dum res</l>
               <l>Nota urbi &amp; populo contin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at Principis aures,</l>
               <l>Dedecus ille domus <U+017F>ciet ultimus. interea<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> tu</l>
               <l>Ob<U+017F>equere imperio—</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:93159:37"/>
If at the rate of <U+017F>uch a Wife</l>
            <l>you'l purcha<U+017F>e a <U+017F>hort <U+017F>lavi<U+017F>h life.</l>
            <l>Both ways his certain Fate's decreed</l>
            <l>The wretched lovely Youth mu<U+017F>t bleed.</l>
            <l>Shall men ask nothing then? be wi<U+017F>e,</l>
            <l>And li<U+017F>ten well to <U+017F>ound advice.</l>
            <l>Refer de<U+017F>ires to Providence,</l>
            <l>With thanks take what the Gods di<U+017F>pence.</l>
            <l>Let not your <U+017F>tubborn Will repine,</l>
            <l>What'ere they <U+017F>hall for you de<U+017F>ign.</l>
            <l>They better know than human wit,</l>
            <l>What does our Exigents befit.</l>
            <l>Their wi<U+017F>e all-<U+017F>eeing eyes di<U+017F>cern,</l>
            <l>And give what be<U+017F>t <U+017F>uits our concern.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>—<U+017F>i tanti vita dierum</l>
               <l>Paucorum. Quiquid melius leviu<U+017F>que putaris,</l>
               <l>Praebenda e<U+017F>t gladio pulchra haec, &amp; candida cervix.</l>
               <l>Nil ergo, optabunt homines? Si con<U+017F>ilium vis,</l>
               <l>Permittes ip<U+017F>is,<note n="a" place="bottom">EXPENDERE: Con<U+017F>iderare.</note> expendere Numinibus, quid</l>
               <l>Conveniat nobis, rebu<U+017F>que <U+017F>it utile no<U+017F>tris.</l>
               <l>Nam pro jucundis apti<U+017F><U+017F>ima queaque dabunt Dii.</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:93159:37"/>
We blindly harmful things implore<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
            </l>
            <l>Which they refu<U+017F>ing, love us more.</l>
            <l>By love and blind de<U+017F>ires <U+017F>till led,</l>
            <l>Wee're hurryed to the Marriage bed:</l>
            <l>With hopes of i<U+017F><U+017F>ue from our Love,</l>
            <l>But Heaven fore<U+017F>aw how both would prove;</l>
            <l>Forbearing to di<U+017F>turb our Life,</l>
            <l>With Bratts unnatural, and dam'd wife.</l>
            <l>Pray then, that in a Body <U+017F>ound,</l>
            <l>A Firm and Con<U+017F>tant mind be found.</l>
            <l>A Mind no fear of death can daunt,</l>
            <l>Nor Exile, Pri<U+017F>on, Paines nor Want.</l>
            <l>That ju<U+017F>tly reckons death to be</l>
            <l>Kind Author of our liberty,</l>
            <l>From Fle<U+017F>h, a Goal-Delivery.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>Carior e<U+017F>t illis homo, quam <U+017F>ibi. Nos animorum</l>
               <l>Impul<U+017F>u, &amp; caeca, magnaque cupidine ducti,</l>
               <l>Conjugium petimus, partumque uxoris: at illis</l>
               <l>Notum, qui pueri, quali<U+017F>que futura <U+017F>it uxor.</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>t tamen &amp; po<U+017F>cas aliquid, vovea<U+017F>que <U+017F>acellis</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="a" place="bottom">EXTA: Inte<U+017F>tina delicata.</note> Exta, &amp; candiduli divina<note n="b" place="bottom">TOMACULA: Farcimina pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guia è Porcinis carnibus.</note> tomacula porci:</l>
               <l>Orandum e<U+017F>t, ut <U+017F>it mens <U+017F>ana in corpore <U+017F>ano.</l>
               <l>Fortem po<U+017F>ce animum, mortis terrore carentem,</l>
               <l>Qui <U+017F>patium <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc><<U+25CA>></desc>
                  </gap> extremum inter munera ponat</l>
               <l>Naturae—</l>
            </note>
            <l>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:93159:38"/>
Bani<U+017F>hing Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion from our Bre<U+017F>t,</l>
            <l>Re<U+017F>ting Content with what's po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>t.</l>
            <l>That ev'ry hone<U+017F>t Action loves,</l>
            <l>And Great <hi>Alcides</hi> (39) toyles approves,</l>
            <l>Above the Lu<U+017F>ts, Fea<U+017F>ts, beds of Down,</l>
            <l>Which did <hi>Sardanapalus</hi> (40) drown.</l>
            <l>This, mortals to them<U+017F>elves may give;</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Vertue</hi>'s, the happy rule to live.</l>
            <l>Chance bears no <U+017F>way, where <hi>Wi<U+017F>dome</hi> Rules,</l>
            <l>An empty Name, ador'd by fools.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Folly</hi> Blinde <hi>Fortune</hi> did Create</l>
            <l>A Godde<U+017F>s, and to Heaven Tran<U+017F>late.</l>
            <note place="bottom">
               <l>—qui ferre queat quo<U+017F>cunque labores,</l>
               <l>Ne<U+017F>ciat ira<U+017F>ci, cupiat nil, &amp;<note n="a" place="bottom">POTIORES: praeferendos.</note> potiores</l>
               <l>Herculis aerumnas, credat, <U+017F>aevo<U+017F>que labores,</l>
               <l>Et Venere, &amp; caenis, &amp; pluma<note n="b" place="bottom">SARDANAPALI: Ultimus A<U+017F><U+017F>yriorum Rex, omni libidini ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foeminatae deditus.</note> Sardanapali.</l>
               <l>Mon<U+017F>tro, quod ip<U+017F>e tibi po<U+017F><U+017F>is dare, Semita certe</l>
               <l>Tranquillae per virtutem patet unica vitae.</l>
               <l>Nullum<note n="c" place="bottom">NUMEN HABES: Scilicet tu Fortuna nullum numen habes. i. e. non Dea exi<U+017F>timaris a prudenti homine.</note> Numen habes <U+017F>i <U+017F>it prudentia:<note n="d" place="bottom">NOS: <U+017F>ed nos <U+017F>tolidi homines facimus Fortunam Deam no<U+017F>tram.</note> nos, te</l>
               <l>Nos facimus, Fortuna, Deam, coeloqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> locamus.</l>
            </note>
         </div>
         <div type="annotations">
            <pb facs="tcp:93159:38"/>
            <head>THE ANNOTATIONS ON THE Tenth SATYR.</head>
            <p>(1.) IN this Wi<U+017F>e Satyr, the Author does reprove and accu<U+017F>e the Ignorance
of Mankind, imploring things of the Gods, which often prove preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial;
As, <hi>Riches, Honours, Martial-Glory, Long-Life,</hi> &amp; <hi>Beauty:</hi> But
neglect to ask Endowments and Ble<U+017F><U+017F>ings of the <hi>Mind;</hi> as, <hi>Wi<U+017F>dom,
Vertue, Ju<U+017F>tice,</hi> and <hi>Integrity</hi> of <hi>Life,</hi> which alone can be e<U+017F>teemed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
Good, of which neither Chance, Violence, nor Shipwrack can deprive us;
true and <U+017F>olid Happine<U+017F>s con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ting in the Indolency of the Body, and tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
of the Mind; and <U+017F>hews that very few men in the World, <hi>viz.</hi> from <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diz</hi>
an I<U+017F>land in <hi>Spain,</hi> at the Mouth of the <hi>Streights</hi> of <hi>Gibralter,</hi> which in our
Authors time, was thought the Bounds of the We<U+017F>tern World, and where <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi>
placed his Pillars, to the Famous River <hi>Ganges,</hi> Ea<U+017F>tward, who<U+017F>e Head ari<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
in Mount <hi>Cauca<U+017F>us</hi> in <hi>Scythia,</hi> runs a long Cour<U+017F>e through the <hi>Eastern-Indies,</hi>
who<U+017F>e Channel where narrowe<U+017F>t, is 8 miles broad, and about 20 where wide<U+017F>t;
and in the <U+017F>hallowe<U+017F>t place 100 Foot deep. Page <hi>1st.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(2) <hi>Milo:</hi> The Poet ob<U+017F>erving, that many Eminent in Civil and Military
Affairs, &amp; fam'd for Eloquence, tru<U+017F>ting to their own Abilities have been ruin'd;
gives a lively In<U+017F>tance of one betray'd by his own <U+017F>trength; in <hi>Milo</hi> the <hi>Crotan,</hi>
who unfortunately pre<U+017F>uming on his Gygantick <U+017F>trength, in an Attempt to
rive an Oak, had his Arm wedged in the Trunk; whence not having power to
di<U+017F>engage him<U+017F>elf, he was held in a Trapp in the <U+017F>olitary Woods, where he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
a Prey to Wild Bea<U+017F>ts. This <hi>Milo</hi> in the Olympick Games carryed an
Ox on his back a furlong, and after <U+017F>lew him at one Blow of his Fi<U+017F>t, and the
<U+017F>ame day intirely eat him up. Page <hi>4th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(3) <hi>In Neroes:</hi> The Poet ob<U+017F>erves this Emperour infamous for Tyranny, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ju<U+017F>tice,
and all manner of Villany &amp; Wickedne<U+017F>s; who took all unju<U+017F>t advantages
to trappan and take away the Lives of his wealthie<U+017F>t Subjects, thereby to po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s
him<U+017F>elf of their E<U+017F>tates, and proceeded to <U+017F>uch a height, he did not <U+017F>pare the
Lives of his Dome<U+017F>tick Servants and Favourites, imbrewing his hands in the
<pb facs="tcp:93159:39"/>
Blood of his Mother, Brother, and Wife; and others of his neare<U+017F>t Relations.
Page <hi>5th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(4) <hi>Longinus: Caius Ca<U+017F><U+017F>ius Longinus</hi> the Lawyer, whom <hi>Nero</hi> commanded
to be <U+017F>lain, being charged with no other Crime, but having the Statue of <hi>Cae<U+017F><U+017F>ius</hi>
(one of <hi>Ca<U+017F>ar</hi>'s Murderers) in his hou<U+017F>e. But his great Riches and Po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>ions was
the true rea<U+017F>on of his Death. Page <hi>6th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(5) <hi>Seneca:</hi> The Tutor of <hi>Nero,</hi> who by the favour of the Emperour, in his
ten years <U+017F>ole Mini<U+017F>try of Affairs, had ama<U+017F><U+017F>ed together a va<U+017F>t Trea<U+017F>ure, and got
<U+017F>plendid Gardens and Po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>ions; but lo<U+017F>t them all by the Command of his cruel
Pupil, with his life. As al<U+017F>o did the rich Family of the <hi>Laterani.</hi> Page <hi>6th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(6) <hi>The brace of Wi<U+017F>e-men:</hi> Are meant <hi>Democritus</hi> of <hi>Abdera</hi> the laughing,
and <hi>Heraclitus</hi> of <hi>Ephe<U+017F>us,</hi> the weeping Philo<U+017F>opher; the fir<U+017F>t, in a carele<U+017F>s merry
humour, continually <U+017F>coffing and deriding the Vanity and Foppery of Mankind;
the other bewailing their Folly and Misfortune. Page <hi>8th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(7) <hi>Knees:</hi> It was cu<U+017F>tomary with the <hi>Antients,</hi> when they had any great or
con<U+017F>iderable Reque<U+017F>t or Boon to beg of the Gods, to write their Reque<U+017F>t in Paper
or waxen Tables; together, with a Conditional Vow, which they promi<U+017F>ed to
perform if they obtained their <U+017F>uit; which being <U+017F>ealed, they left fa<U+017F>tned to the
<hi>Knees</hi> of the God, from whom the Ble<U+017F><U+017F>ing was expected; in which if they
proved <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>sful, they took off the Paper <U+017F>o fa<U+017F>tened, and performed their
Vow. Page <hi>12th</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(8) <hi>Clius Sejanus:</hi> A <hi>Tu<U+017F>can</hi> born, he was in <U+017F>o great favour with the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour
<hi>Tyberius,</hi> that he denyed him nothing: He was made Colleague in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ul<U+017F>hip
and Roman Empire with <hi>Tyberius,</hi> was likewi<U+017F>e Prefect of the Pretorian
Bands, and grand Ma<U+017F>ter of the Pallace: Publick Statues were erected to him,
and the <hi>Romans</hi> u<U+017F>ed to <U+017F>wear by his Fortune; his Birth-day was kept a Fe<U+017F>tival:
Yet falling into Di<U+017F>grace with <hi>Tyberius,</hi> by whom, he with others, were <U+017F>u<U+017F>pected
to have con<U+017F>pired his Death; the Emperour from the I<U+017F>land of <hi>Capra</hi> <U+017F>ent a long
Epi<U+017F>tle to the Senate, charging <hi>Sejanus</hi> with Ingratitude again<U+017F>t the life of <hi>Cae<U+017F>ar;</hi>
whereupon he was by the Senate forthwith Condemned with his whole Family;
and the <U+017F>ame day having his hands bound behind him, was by the Executioner
drawn through the <U+017F>treet to the <hi>Scalae Gemoniae;</hi> his Statues pulled down with
Contempt and Ignominy, his only daughter then but a child was deflour'd and
executed by the Hangman. A Notable Example of the mutability of Humane
Affairs. Page <hi>13th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(9) <hi>Capra:</hi> An I<U+017F>land near <hi>Naples,</hi> whither <hi>Tyberius</hi> retired, <U+017F>pending his
time in ob<U+017F>cene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ilthy Plea<U+017F>ures, whence he wrote to the Senate again<U+017F>t <hi>Sejanus.</hi>
Page <hi>14th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:93159:39"/>
(10) <hi>Old-Fox: Tyberius</hi> who may well merit that Name, being a mo<U+017F>t pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found
di<U+017F><U+017F>embler, and <U+017F>ubtil Politician, who<U+017F>e Actions had rendred him <U+017F>o odious
to the <hi>Romans,</hi> that as <hi>Suetonius</hi> relates on the fir<U+017F>t news of his Death, <U+017F>ome of
the People cryed out, that he <U+017F>hould be thrown into the <hi>Tyber;</hi> others would allow
no <U+017F>epulchre; others threatned to drag the Body to the <hi>Scalae Gemoniae.</hi> Page <hi>15th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(11) <hi>Cicero:</hi> The Author <U+017F>hews by the Examples of <hi>Cicero</hi> and <hi>Demo<U+017F>thenes,</hi>
that Wit and Eloquence have been pernicious to Orators: <hi>Cicero</hi> the Chief of
the <hi>Roman</hi> Orators and Philo<U+017F>ophers, as appears by his works; he being the fir<U+017F>t
that tran<U+017F>planted the <hi>Grecian</hi> Learning into the <hi>Roman</hi> Language: He rai<U+017F>ed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elf
through all the degrees of civil Imployments to the Con<U+017F>ul<U+017F>hip, being the
highe<U+017F>t pitch of Honour in the <hi>Roman</hi> Common-wealth; and in his year of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ul<U+017F>hip,
broke and defeated the Con<U+017F>piracy of <hi>Cataline:</hi> He made <U+017F>everal invec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
Orations again<U+017F>t <hi>Mark Anthony,</hi> which he with evil O men Intituled his Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>llippicks,
in imitation of <hi>Demo<U+017F>thenes,</hi> who in like manner declaymed again<U+017F>t
<hi>Phillip</hi> of <hi>Macedon;</hi> but in the turn of the <hi>Roman</hi> State he was in revenge pro<U+017F>cribed
by <hi>Anthony</hi> and <hi>Augu<U+017F>tus,</hi> and had his Head and Hands nailed on the <hi>Ro<U+017F>trum</hi>
or <hi>Pulpet,</hi> whence he declaimed again<U+017F>t <hi>Anthony.</hi> Page <hi>21<U+017F>t.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(12) <hi>Demo<U+017F>thenes</hi> the <hi>Athenian,</hi> the mo<U+017F>t famous <hi>Grecian</hi> Orator, and Stout
Champion for the Liberty of <hi>Greece;</hi> he declaimed again<U+017F>t King <hi>Phillip,</hi> as one
who de<U+017F>igned to de<U+017F>troy the Publick Liberty and en<U+017F>lave <hi>Greece;</hi> for which he
was expelled his Country; and again, after <hi>Phillips</hi> Death recalled: but after
<hi>Alexanders</hi> Death, under the Government of <hi>Antipater,</hi> di<U+017F>covering <U+017F>ome De<U+017F>igns
again<U+017F>t his Life, he fled and took Sanctuary in <hi>Neptune</hi>'s Temple, whither <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chias</hi>
the Tragedian came, endeavouring to wheadle him to recour<U+017F>e to <hi>Antipater;</hi>
affirming he had no de<U+017F>ign again<U+017F>t him; but their Plott being well under<U+017F>tood by
<hi>Demo<U+017F>thenes,</hi> he told <hi>Archias,</hi> that he had never plea<U+017F>ed him on the Stage as an
Actor, and much le<U+017F>s now when he played the Part of an Amba<U+017F><U+017F>ador: but <hi>Archias</hi>
threatning he would draw him out by Force; the Orator told him, he perceived
now he was in earne<U+017F>t, whereas before he did but act his Part, and de<U+017F>iring his
Patience till he di<U+017F>patched <U+017F>ome nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary Orders to his Dome<U+017F>ticks; he retired
to <U+017F>ome di<U+017F>tance, and drew out his Table-Book as if he would write, when <U+017F>uck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Poy<U+017F>on from a quill which he had always kept therein for a dead lift, He ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired:
thereby mocking the malice and revenge of his Adver<U+017F>aries. Page <hi>21<U+017F>t.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(13) <hi>Barbari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n:</hi> When <hi>Greece</hi> Flouri<U+017F>hed, She called all the World be<U+017F>ides
Barbarous: which Title <hi>Plautus</hi> as freely be<U+017F>tows on the <hi>Romans;</hi> but when <hi>Rome</hi>
came in Power, and Arts Flouri<U+017F>hed, <U+017F>he treated the World with the <U+017F>ame lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage.
Page <hi>24th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(14) <hi>Hannibal:</hi> Here the Poet pa<U+017F><U+017F>es from <hi>Eloquence</hi> to <hi>Martial-Glory,</hi> and
inquires what Advantages it brought to that Captain <hi>Hannibal,</hi> the <U+017F>on of <hi>Amil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car,</hi>
the <hi>Carthaginian</hi> General, by whom he was in his youth <U+017F>olemnly worn an
<pb facs="tcp:93159:40"/>
Irreconcileable Enemy to the <hi>Romans;</hi> the Poet traces his life through all the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver<U+017F>es
of his pro<U+017F>perous &amp; adver<U+017F>e Fortune, demon<U+017F>trating he had been happier,
had he limited his Ambition, and not hara<U+017F><U+017F>ed and con<U+017F>umed Him<U+017F>elf and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
about <U+017F>uch vain and improbable De<U+017F>igns of Conquering <hi>Italy.</hi> Page <hi>25th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(15) <hi>Affrick:</hi> He taxes the Haughty and Re<U+017F>tle<U+017F>s Spirit of <hi>Hannibal,</hi> who
e<U+017F>teemed <hi>Affrick,</hi> though then one full third part of the known World, too
narrow a Stage and ob<U+017F>cure a Scene for his Boundle<U+017F>s and Ambitious Actions.
Page <hi>25th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(16) <hi>Alps:</hi> A continued ridge of high Mountains, extending one hundred
thou<U+017F>and paces, &amp; dividing <hi>France</hi> &amp; <hi>Germany</hi> from <hi>Italy:</hi> they are continually co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered
with Snow, from who<U+017F>e whitene<U+017F>s they took their Denomination in Greek,
a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>< in non-Latin alphabet ></desc>
               </gap> <U+017F>trong and <U+017F>afe barricade to the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, again<U+017F>t the <hi>Gauls</hi> and
Barbarous Nations. Page <hi>26th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(17) <hi>With Vinegar:</hi> Our Author laughs at the ridiculous Relation given by
<hi>Livy,</hi> of <hi>Hannibals</hi> pa<U+017F><U+017F>ing the <hi>Alps,</hi> reporting, that when the Army was ob<U+017F>truc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
by a Rock in their pa<U+017F><U+017F>age; they made a va<U+017F>t Pile of Trees, and with the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage
of the Wind, <U+017F>etting them on Fire, they poured Vinegar on the red-hot
Stone, which <U+017F>oftned, di<U+017F><U+017F>olved, and rotted them away; which idle Invention of
the <hi>Hi<U+017F>torian,</hi> is by <hi>Polibius</hi> omitted as fabulous; for what needs <U+017F>uch an Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
when before <hi>Hannibal</hi>'s time, the <hi>Gauls</hi> had five times pa<U+017F><U+017F>ed the <hi>Alps:</hi>
It might be nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary the Army making <U+017F>o long a pa<U+017F><U+017F>age, and <U+017F>o tedious, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on
of the number, and the narrowne<U+017F>s, where no Garriages could come up;
that each Souldier <U+017F>hould carry his proportion of Bread &amp; Vinegar for the whole
Pa<U+017F><U+017F>age; the Vinegar being nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary to make Beveredge with the Mountain
Water: Which great Preparation of Vinegar provided for the March, might
give occa<U+017F>ion to <U+017F>uch Fabulous Report, Page. <hi>26th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(18) <hi>Bythinian Tyrants Gate: Hannibal</hi> being overcome by <hi>Scipio Affricanus</hi>
at the Battle of <hi>Zama,</hi> near <hi>Carthage</hi> in <hi>Affrick;</hi> de<U+017F>pairing of <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s or <U+017F>afety,
fled to <hi>Antiochus</hi> the King of <hi>Syria;</hi> but <U+017F>u<U+017F>pecting that King was in Treaty to
deliver him to the <hi>Romans;</hi> he left him and went to <hi>Pru<U+017F>ius</hi> King of <hi>Bythinia,</hi>
where, as his General he overcame <hi>Eumenes;</hi> but the <hi>Romans</hi> not thinking them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elves
<U+017F>ecure, while <U+017F>o Politick and Inveterate an Enemy <U+017F>urvived, dealt with
<hi>Pru<U+017F>ius</hi> by Emba<U+017F><U+017F>y to deliver him up; which <hi>Hanibal</hi> di<U+017F>covering, to prevent
<U+017F>hame, di<U+017F>patched him<U+017F>elf by Poy<U+017F>on, which he always carryed in his Ring for
that purpo<U+017F>e: A poor Revenge of <hi>Rome,</hi> and below the Con<U+017F>ideration of <U+017F>o
Great and Victorious a Common-wealth. Page <hi>28th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(19) <hi>Canna:</hi> Where <hi>Hannibal</hi> in a pitch't Battle overcame <hi>Paulus Emilius,</hi>
and <hi>Terentius Varro,</hi> the two <hi>Roman</hi> Con<U+017F>uls, together with their whole Army,
being the Flower of the <hi>Roman</hi> Militia, killing mo<U+017F>t of their Hor<U+017F>e, and above
<pb facs="tcp:93159:40"/>
40000 Foot upon the Place; he filled three bu<U+017F>hels of Rings, taken from the Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers
of the <U+017F>lain Nobility, which he <U+017F>ent to <hi>Carthage</hi> as a Witne<U+017F>s of his Victory;
and therefore our Poet wittily Remarks, that <hi>Hannibals</hi> own Ring did revenge
the <U+017F>laughter of the Owners of <U+017F>o many Rings at <hi>Canna.</hi> Page <hi>28th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(20) <hi>Macedonian King:</hi> He laughs at the Vanity of Young <hi>Alexander,</hi> for
being melancholly becau<U+017F>e there was but one World could fall to his <U+017F>hare, as not
a <U+017F>ufficient Prize for his Ambition: 'tis <U+017F>aid, <hi>Alexander</hi> hearing a Philo<U+017F>opher
endeavouring to prove there were many Worlds, he bur<U+017F>t into tears, to his Friends
complaining that he had not as yet Conquered One among <U+017F>o many. Page <hi>29th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(21) <hi>Jove: Alexander</hi> was <U+017F>o puft up with his Succe<U+017F>s again<U+017F>t the Cowardly
Effeminate <hi>Per<U+017F>ians,</hi> and tran<U+017F>ported to that degree of Pride and Vanity, that
he procured and corrupted the Prie<U+017F>ts of <hi>Jupiter Ammon,</hi> to receive and own him
as the true Son of that God; and <U+017F>et on foot a formal <U+017F>tory, that the God had in
a vi<U+017F>ible Figure conver<U+017F>ed with his Mother about the time of his Conception;
which though it might be politickly done, to awe the <U+017F>uper<U+017F>titious <hi>Per<U+017F>ians</hi> and
barbarous Nations, who might think it vain to re<U+017F>i<U+017F>t the power of a God, yet it
le<U+017F><U+017F>ened him in the Hearts &amp; Opinions of his Gallant &amp; Victorious <hi>Macedonians;</hi>
and by a<U+017F>cribing all to <U+017F>ole Valour and Conduct of his God<U+017F>hip, he robbed every
brave Souldier &amp; Commander of his <U+017F>hare of the Honour and Victory. Page <hi>30th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(22) <hi>Babylon:</hi> A City of the <hi>Per<U+017F>ians,</hi> built by <hi>Semiramis</hi> the Wife of <hi>Ninus,</hi>
the Founder of the <hi>A<U+017F><U+017F>yrian</hi> Monarchy; it was <U+017F>urrounded with Walls of brick,
being 60 Miles in Compa<U+017F>s, 50 Foot in Height, and 200 Foot in Breadth, where
<hi>Alexander</hi> dyed by Poy<U+017F>on: <hi>Pythagoras</hi> the Magician had foretold, that <hi>Babylon</hi>
<U+017F>hould be fatal to him, where, notwith<U+017F>tanding the Oracle, he was found mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal.
Page <hi>30th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(23) <hi>Athos:</hi> Here the Poet confirms his Argument with the Example of <hi>Xerx<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es,</hi>
the <hi>Per<U+017F>ian</hi> King, who not content with his va<U+017F>t Dominions, makes an expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
with a numerous Army into <hi>Greece;</hi> and as the <hi>Greek</hi> Hi<U+017F>torians relate, cut
a deep trench, wherein he let the Sea, and thereby divided that high Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,
which was a Promontory from the main Land, and cau<U+017F>ed Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els to <U+017F>ail
round; which is the Expo<U+017F>ition the Commentators give of <hi>Velificatus Athos;</hi> which
does not <U+017F>atisfy me, who rather conjecture that Mount <hi>Athos</hi> abounding with
Pines; they were by <hi>Xerxes</hi> cut down and made into Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els, and then <hi>Veleficati</hi>
or put to <U+017F>ail, and afterwards with them compo<U+017F>ed a Bridge over the <hi>Helle<U+017F>pont,</hi>
he adding immediately, <hi>con<U+017F>tatum cla<U+017F><U+017F>ibus ei<U+017F>dem—<U+017F>uppo<U+017F>itumque rotis <U+017F>olidum
mare.</hi> Which if allowed, the <U+017F>ence will be parallel, as if we <U+017F>hould <U+017F>ay; The
King in his great Navy put the Forre<U+017F>t of <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an</hi> to <U+017F>ea, calling the Wood by the
name of the Place where it grew: the Poet reflecting on the <hi>Greeks,</hi> who writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
their own Hi<U+017F>tory, magnify their own Courage and Conduct, by <U+017F>tuffing their
Legends with mon<U+017F>trous Fables, expo<U+017F>e their Enemies to deri<U+017F>ion, <U+017F>uch as the
<pb facs="tcp:93159:41"/>
making a trench about <hi>Athos,</hi> and the drinking Rivers dry at one Meal.
Page. <hi>30th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(24) <hi>Eolus:</hi> the <hi>Grecian</hi> Hi<U+017F>tories tell us, that <hi>Xerxes,</hi> to hold a Corre<U+017F>pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
between <hi>A<U+017F>ia</hi> and <hi>Europe,</hi> laid a Bridge of Boats over the <hi>Helle<U+017F>pont,</hi> at
the Place where <hi>Se<U+017F>tos</hi> and <hi>Abidos</hi> <U+017F>tood, and the Place where now the <hi>Dardanelli</hi>
are placed, where the <U+017F>ea is about a mile broad; where the Current being deep,
the Ve<U+017F><U+017F>els could not ride at Anchor again<U+017F>t the <U+017F>tream, but mu<U+017F>t be fa<U+017F>tened to
each other; which long line of Boats upon the fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>tiff Gale of Wind, at Ea<U+017F>t,
then called a <hi>Levant,</hi> and blowing with the Currant, mu<U+017F>t nece<U+017F><U+017F>arily <U+017F>eparate
and brake, which was the Fate of <hi>Xerxe</hi>'s Bridge: who to be revenged on <hi>Eurus</hi>
or the Ea<U+017F>t Wind, cau<U+017F>ed <U+017F>everal Thou<U+017F>ands of his Army being drawn up upon
the <U+017F>hoar, with rods to <U+017F>trike and whip again<U+017F>t the Winde; the Poet reflecting on
the folly of the interprize, <U+017F>ays in a jeer, <hi>Eolus</hi> the Prince of the Winds, under
who<U+017F>e Government and re<U+017F>traint they are kept in the Caverns of the Earth, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
u<U+017F>ed his Subjects the Winds <U+017F>o Barbarou<U+017F>ly. Page 31.</p>
            <p>(25) <hi>Neptune:</hi> An Ironical Relation of a freak of <hi>Xerxe</hi>'s, who being offended
with <hi>Neptune,</hi> as well as the VVinds, for breaking his Bridge; did ca<U+017F>t Fetters and
Manacles into the Sea, to <U+017F>hew he had dominion over <hi>Neptune,</hi> &amp; could chain him
at his plea<U+017F>ure as well as <U+017F>courge the VVinds: &amp; perhaps to as much purpo<U+017F>e as
the Duke of <hi>Venice</hi> with <U+017F>olemn Pompe and State does yearly e<U+017F>pou<U+017F>e the <hi>Adria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi>
by throwing a Ring with Ceremony into that Sea; the Poet ob<U+017F>erves, that
<hi>Neptune</hi> was kindly dealt with, that he was not branded as fugitive <U+017F>laves u<U+017F>ed to
be <U+017F>erved. Page 32.</p>
            <p>(26) <hi>Ferrys: Xerxe</hi>'s being overcome by the Greeks neer <hi>Salamine,</hi> under the
Conduct of <hi>Themi<U+017F>tocles</hi> with great <U+017F>laughter, and a Total defeat of his <hi>Navy,</hi> fled
with a few by Land to <hi>Abidos;</hi> and finding the Bridge broken, was in a great Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour
wafted over in a <U+017F>mall fi<U+017F>herboat, concluding <U+017F>o great and glorious an expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
with a ba<U+017F>e and <U+017F>hameful flight. Page 32.</p>
            <p>(27) <hi>Ne<U+017F>tor King of Pylos:</hi> The VVi<U+017F>e<U+017F>t and mo<U+017F>t Eloquent of all the Greeks,
who continued <U+017F>trong and vigorous at an extream age, being near 300 years old
when he went to the Seige of <hi>Troy:</hi> by his rare Example, the Poet <U+017F>hews the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable
grief and calamities, that nece<U+017F><U+017F>arily attend old age, when at the death
of his Son he introduced him in a bitter complaint again<U+017F>t the de<U+017F>tinies, for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing
his mi<U+017F>erable life. Page 41.</p>
            <p>(28) <hi>Peleus</hi> the Son of <hi>Eacus,</hi> and Father of <hi>Achilles</hi> the valiant Greek, who
could not be comforted for the death of his valiant Son <U+017F>lain in the Temple of
<hi>Apollo</hi> by <hi>Paris</hi> and <hi>Diaphobus,</hi> in the in<U+017F>tant when he attended to Marry <hi>Pollixena</hi>
their Si<U+017F>ter. Page 42.</p>
            <p>(29) <hi>Priam:</hi> the la<U+017F>t King of <hi>Troy,</hi> who <U+017F>urviving to a great age, lived to <U+017F>ee
<pb facs="tcp:93159:41"/>
his chief City taken, <U+017F>acked and burnt with the <U+017F>laughter of his numerous i<U+017F><U+017F>ue, and
<U+017F>ubjects, having Fifty Sons, and was him<U+017F>elf <U+017F>lain in the Temple of <hi>Jupiter.</hi> The
Poet ob<U+017F>erves he had been happy, had he dyed before the<U+017F>e Calamities, which
was-all he gained by his Long-Life; yet pur<U+017F>uing his Argument again<U+017F>t Long-Life,
he prefers his Fate, though it met a di<U+017F>ta<U+017F>trous Conclu<U+017F>ion before his Wife
<hi>Hecuba</hi>'s who <U+017F>urviveing him, was transformed into a Bitch. Page <hi>43d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(30) <hi>The Pontick King: Mithridates,</hi> who lived 69 years, and reigned 57,
and waged continual war with the <hi>Romans</hi> 40 years; by whom he was thrice
overcome under the Conduct of <hi>Scylla, Lucullus,</hi> and <hi>Pompey;</hi> his affairs were
at la<U+017F>t reduced to that extreamity, that he attempted to de<U+017F>troy him<U+017F>elf by Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on,
but finding by Antidotes, he had <U+017F>o fortified his Body, it would not work the
de<U+017F>ired Effect: he perfected his Intention with a Do<U+017F>e of cold Iron. Page <hi>45th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(31) <hi>Caius Macius:</hi> Produced as another In<U+017F>tance of the misfortune of Long-Life;
he led the beginning of his Life as a labouring Husband-man, and after
<U+017F>erved as a common Souldier, and pa<U+017F><U+017F>ing through <U+017F>everal degrees of the Army,
at length obtained the <U+017F>upream Command and Con<U+017F>ul<U+017F>hip. He Conquered <hi>Jugur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha</hi>
in <hi>Affrick,</hi> and led him in Triumph: So great was the opinion of his Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour
and Conduct, that when the Inva<U+017F>ion of the <hi>Cimbrians</hi> and <hi>Teutons,</hi> had filled
<hi>Italy</hi> with Terror and Confu<U+017F>ion; <hi>Marius</hi> was the only Man that was thought fit
to defend his Country, and on that occa<U+017F>ion was five times <U+017F>ucce<U+017F><U+017F>ively cho<U+017F>en
Con<U+017F>ul; and at la<U+017F>t in two Battles overcame the va<U+017F>t Armyes of the <hi>Cimbrians</hi>
and <hi>Teutons,</hi> and Triumphed with a general Admiration and Applau<U+017F>e, as the
Deliverer of his Country. The Poet pur<U+017F>uing his Argument, <U+017F>hews his Long-Life
was incommodious to him, for had he (<U+017F>ays the Poet) dyed the day of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph,
no man had ever left behind him a more glorious Memory and Character:
whereas, he after <U+017F>ullyed the Glory of his Reputation and Actions, and <U+017F>urvived
his great Reputation, and for his Folly and Cruelty was <U+017F>corned and dete<U+017F>ted of
all, and <U+017F>o weari<U+017F>ome to him<U+017F>elf, that he at la<U+017F>t di<U+017F>patched his mi<U+017F>erable Life.
Page <hi>45th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(32) <hi>Great Pompey:</hi> Who having before the Civil Wars performed <U+017F>everal
great Actions, fell <U+017F>ick at <hi>Capua</hi> of a Feavor; his death (the Poet <U+017F>ays) was then
prevented by the publick Prayers that were made for his Recovery; but had he
then dyed, his Head had happily e<U+017F>caped an ignominious Death; Fortune <U+017F>eem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
then to re<U+017F>erve it, to be cut off by the treachery of <hi>Achillas</hi> in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and
pre<U+017F>ented to his great Rival of the World, <hi>Julius Cae<U+017F>ar,</hi> who (Crocodile like)
<U+017F>hed tears (no doubt of joy) over it. Page <hi>46th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(33) <hi>Cataline:</hi> The Poet ob<U+017F>erves that <hi>Lentulus</hi> and <hi>Cethegus</hi> Traytors and
Con<U+017F>pirators with <hi>Cataline,</hi> dyed a more decent death, than unfortunate <hi>Pompey,</hi>
as not being beheaded or mangled, which was e<U+017F>teemed unfortunate and di<U+017F>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured:
<hi>Cataline</hi> the Arch Traytor, dyed at the Head of his Army Gallantly
fighting, and made a good Figure, covering the Spot where he <U+017F>ought. Page <hi>47th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:93159:42"/>
(34) <hi>Lucretia:</hi> He pa<U+017F><U+017F>es now from Long-Life, &amp; con<U+017F>iders the many di<U+017F>a<U+017F>trous
fates have attended Innocent &amp; Beautiful Per<U+017F>ons; producing the <hi>Roman Lucrece</hi>
for an Example, who being ravi<U+017F>hed by <hi>Tarquinius Sextus,</hi> was the occa<U+017F>ion of
many troubles, and nobly ended her Life &amp; Di<U+017F>honor with a Ponyard. Page <hi>48th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(35) <hi>Virginia:</hi> With who<U+017F>e rare Beauty, <hi>Appius Claudius</hi> the <hi>Decemvir</hi> fell
de<U+017F>perately in Love, and having tryed all means to corrupt her Cha<U+017F>tity without
<U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s, at la<U+017F>t <U+017F>uborns a Creature of his own, to <U+017F>wear before him as Judge, that
<hi>Virginia</hi> was not the true Daughter of <hi>Lucius Virginius</hi> the Centurion her reputed
Father, but a <U+017F>lave born, and con<U+017F>equently, ought not to be free, and was judged
as a <U+017F>lave; by which judgment, <U+017F>he was abandoned (without her Fathers Protection)
to the Lu<U+017F>t of her Ravi<U+017F>her; which <hi>Virginius</hi> perceiving, <U+017F>eeming <U+017F>atisfyed with
the Sentence, de<U+017F>ired to take leave off his <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>ed Daughter, &amp; approaching her,
<U+017F>tabbed Her with his Dagger; whereby he prevented her Di<U+017F>honor, &amp; di<U+017F>apoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
the Intent of the unju<U+017F>t Judge; it not being puni<U+017F>hable in him to kill Her, being
adjudged a <U+017F>lave, &amp; taking the bleeding Body on his <U+017F>houlders, he returned with
it to the Camp, where <U+017F>hewing the bloody Corps, and declaring his Injury,
the Souldiers were <U+017F>tirred up to revenge his Wrong, which was puni<U+017F>hed in the
unju<U+017F>t Judge with Death, and occa<U+017F>ioned the Extingui<U+017F>hing of the Government,
in the <hi>Decem-viri.</hi> Page <hi>48th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(36) <hi>Mullet:</hi> The Poet ob<U+017F>erves, that beautiful Sons are obnoxious to the
Temptations of Great Men, and often Care<U+017F><U+017F>ed by wanton Wives and Ladies;
though they mu<U+017F>t expect <U+017F>ometimes to be taken, like their Predece<U+017F><U+017F>or <hi>Mars,</hi>
who notwith<U+017F>tanding his Planet and his Sentinel the Cock was taken in <hi>Vulcans</hi>
Net; where they mu<U+017F>t expect all the Cruelty and Outrage, Injured and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengful
Men can commit: and mentions here the <hi>Roman</hi> Revenge, that u<U+017F>ed to
force a <hi>Mullet</hi> up the Fundament of the Offender, with the Head foremo<U+017F>t,
which having Bri<U+017F>tles on the Back, and Finns like a Pearch, was no way to be
pulled out. Page <hi>51<U+017F>t.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(37) <hi>Bellerephon:</hi> The Author <U+017F>hews that Beauty in young men, accompanied
with a Re<U+017F>olution of rigied Vertue, turns very often to the di<U+017F>advantage of the Po<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>or,
which is made out by the Examples of <hi>Belerephon</hi> &amp; <hi>Hippolito:</hi> with the
Shape and Beauty of the fir<U+017F>t of which <hi>Sthenobea</hi> the Wife of <hi>Praetus,</hi> the King
of the <hi>Argives</hi> being Inamoured, <U+017F>ollicited him to unlawful Plea<U+017F>ures, which he
refu<U+017F>ed; whereupon <U+017F>he accu<U+017F>ed him for attempting a Rape upon her; which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca<U+017F>ioned
many Hazards and Dangers, which his Vertue at la<U+017F>t overcame: <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polito</hi>
being a very Beautiful Youth, gave him<U+017F>elf up wholly to the Diver<U+017F>ion of
Hunting, regardle<U+017F>s of the Charms and Conver<U+017F>ation of Women, with whom
his Step-Mother <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aedra</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell in love, and Courted him to her Bed, but was by him
refu<U+017F>ed; <U+017F>he accu<U+017F>es him to her Husband, for attempting a Rape upon her, <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lito</hi>
perceiving <U+017F>he had gained Belief of her ea<U+017F>y Husband, and that his Life was
in danger, Flies in his Chariot; but in the way his Hor<U+017F>es being affrightened,
<pb facs="tcp:93159:42"/>
would not be governed, but running down a Precipice, dragged the unfortunate
Youth in peices. The<U+017F>e with the Story of <hi>Jo<U+017F>eph</hi> may be a Caution to Cuckolds,
not to be over Credulous. Page <hi>53d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(38) <hi>The Emperors Wife Me<U+017F><U+017F>alina:</hi> She was married young, to <hi>Claudius</hi>
the Old doating Emperor: Her <U+017F>alacious Appetite was not to be <U+017F>atisfied, though
with many Incumbents: She played a tryal of skill for a prize, with one of the
Able<U+017F>t, and mo<U+017F>t Famous <hi>Roman</hi> Courtezans, who <U+017F>hould endure the mo<U+017F>t A<U+017F><U+017F>ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants;
in which Conte<U+017F>t, the Empre<U+017F>s bore away the Bell, and out-did the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<U+017F>t
Harlot in her own Art: She u<U+017F>ed in a di<U+017F>gui<U+017F>e, to go to the Publick Stews
by night, and there accoutred like a common Courtezan, <U+017F>he maintained her
Po<U+017F>t again<U+017F>t all Commers, and in <U+017F>everal Incounters was found Invincible, <U+017F>taying
till the <hi>Brothel Tap-too</hi> went about, as de<U+017F>irous to <U+017F>ee the la<U+017F>t Man born: At la<U+017F>t <U+017F>he
grew <U+017F>o openly Extravagant, that being in love with <hi>Caius Silius</hi> a hand<U+017F>ome
Youth, and of a mo<U+017F>t Noble Family; made him put his Wife away and open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
marry Her, though the Emperor her Husband was alive, and not twenty miles
from <hi>Rome;</hi> for which Purpo<U+017F>e all Ceremonies were prepared for the Wedding,
and the Portion ready down upon the nayle, the Wedding Bed prepared in
a <U+017F>umptuous Pavilion in the Garden, of which the Emperour being adverti<U+017F>ed,
forbid the Banes, and cau<U+017F>ing both to be <U+017F>ei<U+017F>ed, they both were <U+017F>lain; the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate
<hi>Silius,</hi> fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>uffering before the eyes of the Lu<U+017F>tful Empere<U+017F>s. Page <hi>56th.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(39) <hi>Alcides: Hercules</hi> the Son of <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mena;</hi> he was for his Ju<U+017F>tice,
Valour, and hardy Exploits, worthily tran<U+017F>lated among the Gods. The Poet
propo<U+017F>es his Toyles and Labours, rather to be imitated and undergone, by a
Brave and Virtuous Man, and preferrable to the Indulgence and Debauchery of a
Sloathful and Voluptuous Per<U+017F>on. Page <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>lt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>(40) <hi>Sardanapalus:</hi> The la<U+017F>t of the <hi>A<U+017F><U+017F>yrian</hi> Monarchs, and the <hi>30th.</hi> from
<hi>Ninus</hi> the Founder: He <U+017F>o degenerated into all the <U+017F>orts of Lu<U+017F>t and Debauche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;
that he was not a<U+017F>hamed to <U+017F>it and <U+017F>pin among a Multitude of Strumpets,
And therefore was by the <hi>A<U+017F><U+017F>yrian</hi> Nobility worthily de<U+017F>pi<U+017F>ed and depo<U+017F>ed.
Page <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>lt.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Cato his An<U+017F>wer to Labienus when he Reque<U+017F>ted him to Con<U+017F>ult the
Oracle of Jupiter Ammon.</head>
            <head type="sub">Being a Tran<U+017F>lation of Part of the 9th. Book of Lucan; Begining
at—Quid quaeri Labiene Jubes, &amp;c.</head>
            <l>WHat <U+017F>hould I Ask my Friend, if best it be</l>
            <l>To Live En<U+017F>lav'd, or thus in Arms Dy free?</l>
            <l>If it our Real Happine<U+017F>s import,</l>
            <l>Whither Life's fooli<U+017F>h Scene be Long or Short?</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:93159:43"/>
If any Force true Honour can Abate,</l>
            <l>Or Fortune's Threats make Vertue bow to Fate?</l>
            <l>If when at Noble Ends we justly aim,</l>
            <l>The Bare Attempt Entitles us to Fame?</l>
            <l>If a Bad Cau<U+017F>e that Ju<U+017F>tice would oppre<U+017F>s,</l>
            <l>Can ever grow more Hone<U+017F>t by Succe<U+017F>s?</l>
            <l>All this we know, wove in our Mind it <U+017F>ticks,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Which</hi> Ammon <hi>nor his</hi> Prie<U+017F>ts <hi>can deeper fix.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>They need not Teach with Venale Cant and Pains</l>
            <l>
               <hi>That</hi> God<hi>'s Inevitable</hi> Will <hi>holds ours in Chains,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Who Act but only what he Praeordaines.</l>
            <l>He needs no Voice to Thunder out his Law,</l>
            <l>Or keep his Creatures Wild De<U+017F>ires in awe:</l>
            <l>Both what we ought to do or what forbear,</l>
            <l>He once for All did at our Births declare:</l>
            <l>What for our Knowledge, needful was or fit</l>
            <l>With La<U+017F>ting Characters in Humane Soul he Writ.</l>
            <l>But never did he <U+017F>eek out De<U+017F>ert Lands</l>
            <l>To Skulk, or Bury Truth in pathle<U+017F>s Sands:</l>
            <l>Or to a Corner of the World withdrew</l>
            <l>Head of a Sect, and Partial to a few.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Natures Va<U+017F>t Fabrick he Controuls</hi> alone;</l>
            <l>
               <hi>This</hi> Globe'<hi>s his Foot<U+017F>tool, and high</hi> Heaven <hi>his Throne;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>In Earth, Sea, Air, and what e're el<U+017F>e Excels,</l>
            <l>In Knowing Heads, and Hone<U+017F>t Hearts he dwels.</l>
            <l>Why vainly <U+017F>eek we then in Barren Sands</l>
            <l>And narrow Shrines, in Temples Built with Hands,</l>
            <l>HIM, who<U+017F>e Dread Pre<U+017F>ence does all Places fill,</l>
            <l>Or look, but in our Rea<U+017F>on, <hi>for his</hi> Will.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>What e're we <U+017F>ee is</hi> GOD, <hi>in all we find</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Apparent Prints of his Eternal Mind.</l>
            <l>Let Floating Fools their Cour<U+017F>e by Prophets Steer,</l>
            <l>And live of future Chances <U+017F>till in Fear:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>No</hi> Oracle <hi>or</hi> Dream <hi>the Crowd is told,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Shall make me more or le<U+017F>s Re<U+017F>olv'd and Bold:</l>
            <l>Death <hi>is my <U+017F>ure Retreat, which mu<U+017F>t on All</hi>
            </l>
            <l>As well on Cowards, as on the Gallant fall.</l>
            <l>This <U+017F>aid, he turn'd him with Di<U+017F>dain about,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>And left <U+017F>corn'd</hi> Ammon <hi>to amu<U+017F>e the Rout.</hi>
            </l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:93159:43"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>

