<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The French Lucian made English; By J.D. Esq</title>
            <title>Nouveaux dialogues des morts. Part 1. English.</title>
            <author>Fontenelle, M. de (Bernard Le Bovier), 1657-1757.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 124 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2008-09">2008-09 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84661</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1412C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202364</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896692</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896692</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135343</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the
	       work described above is co-owned by the institutions
	       providing financial support to the Early English Books
	       Online Text Creation Partnership. This Phase I text is
	       available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">Creative
	       Commons 0 1.0 Universal</ref>. The text can be copied,
	       modified, distributed and performed, even for
	       commercial purposes, all without asking permission.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A84661)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135343)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2443:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The French Lucian made English; By J.D. Esq</title>
                  <title>Nouveaux dialogues des morts. Part 1. English.</title>
                  <author>Fontenelle, M. de (Bernard Le Bovier), 1657-1757.</author>
                  <author>Dryden, John, 1631-1700, attibuted name.</author>
                  <author>Davies, John, 1625-1693, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 135, [3] p., [1] leaf of plates   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for R. Bentley, at the Post-House in Russel-street, in Covent-Garden,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, variously attributed to John Dryden and to John Davies, of the first part of:  Fontenelle.  Nouveaux dialogues des morts.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:135343:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135343:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135343:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>THE FRENCH LUCIAN MADE ENGLISH</head>
                  <p>Sold by R<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> Bentley in Couent Garden, 1693.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135343:2"/>
            <p>THE French Lucian, MADE ENGLISH; By <hi>J. D.</hi> 
               <abbr>E<U+017F>q</abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for R. <hi>Bentley,</hi> at the Po<U+017F>t-Hou<U+017F>e in <hi>Ru<U+017F><U+017F>el-<U+017F>treet,</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:135343:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135343:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To</hi> Lucian <hi>in</hi> Ely<U+017F>ium.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Illu<U+017F>trious Decea<U+017F>ed,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Should injure Ju<U+017F>tice if that after I have a<U+017F><U+017F>umed an <hi>Idea</hi> which is properly Yours, I did not thereupon ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you <U+017F>ome kind of Homage. The Author that <U+017F>upports us mo<U+017F>t in our Writings, is the true <hi>Hero</hi> of the <hi>Dedicatory;</hi> his Prai<U+017F>es we ought to publi<U+017F>h with <U+017F>incerity, and chu<U+017F>e him for our Protector. It may perhaps be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hought, that I have been very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>old in daring to work upon your
<pb facs="tcp:135343:4"/>
Ground-plat; but it <U+017F>eems to me that I <U+017F>hould have been far bolder, if I had wrought upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Ground of my own Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I flatter my <U+017F>elf with <U+017F>ome hopes that the de<U+017F>ig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> being Yours, it will mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> way for what is mine, and thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> much I dare tell you, that if b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> chance my <hi>Dialogues</hi> had an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> <U+017F>o little <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s, they woul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gain You more Honour the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your own have, <U+017F>ince it would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that this <hi>Idea</hi> is <U+017F>o taking that it matters not whether it b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> duly executed or no. I depen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> <U+017F>o fully upon it, that I thought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> part of it onely would <U+017F>erve m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:135343:4"/>
turn. I have taken no notice of <hi>Pluto, Caron, Cerberus,</hi> nor of no one of the infernal Crew. How concerned am I that you have drained all tho<U+017F>e rare mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the equality of the Dead, of their trouble at Life, of the fal<U+017F>e con<U+017F>tancy which <hi>Philo<U+017F>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers</hi> affect to make appear at their dying hour, of the ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous misfortune of tho<U+017F>e young people, that dye before the old<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of whom they thought to inherit, and whom they <U+017F>o much courted. But when all is done, <U+017F>ince you had invented this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ign, it was but just and rea<U+017F>on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able that you <U+017F>hould pick and
<pb facs="tcp:135343:5"/>
choo<U+017F>e what was be<U+017F>t in it. I have at lea<U+017F>t endeavoured to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate you in the end you had propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ed to your <U+017F>elf. All your <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues</hi> include their Moral, and I make all my Dead moralize, otherwi<U+017F>e it had not been worth while to make them <U+017F>peak; <U+017F>ome of the living would have <U+017F>erved well enough to te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l frivolous things. Moreover, there is this conveniency in it, that a Man may <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e the Dead to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ons of great Reflection, as well for their experience-<U+017F>ake, as becau<U+017F>e of their vacant time; and one ought to believe, that they think a little more then is
<pb facs="tcp:135343:5"/>
u<U+017F>ual whil<U+017F>t alive. They di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour<U+017F>e of things here above bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than we, becau<U+017F>e they behold them with greater indifferency and more tranquility, and they are willing enough to di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>e of them, becau<U+017F>e they <U+017F>till pretend to <U+017F>ome interest in them. You have made the mo<U+017F>t part of their <hi>Dialogues</hi> <U+017F>o <U+017F>hort, that 'tis apparent you did not believe them to be great Talkers, and in this I can ea<U+017F>ily agree with you. As the Dead are very witty, they ought to make a quick di<U+017F>covery of the ending of all matters. I could believe too, that they might be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ily enlightened as to agree with
<pb facs="tcp:135343:6"/>
one another about every thing, and con<U+017F>equently that they <U+017F>hould <U+017F>carce ever <U+017F>peak; for I fancy that it belongs to us Ignorants only to di<U+017F>pute, who do not di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the Truth; even as it is the property only of the Blind, who <U+017F>ee not the place they are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to, to jo<U+017F>tle one another as they go along. But here we cannot be per<U+017F>waded that the Dead <U+017F>hould have changed their qualities, <U+017F>o far as not to be any longer of contrary Judgments. When we have once conceived an opinion of Per<U+017F>ons in this World, we cannot alter it. Thus I have made it my bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s to make
<pb facs="tcp:135343:6"/>
the Dead known again, at lea<U+017F>t <U+017F>uch as are mo<U+017F>t eminent. You made no difficulty to <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>e <U+017F>ome, and <U+017F>ome of the Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures too perhaps which you allot them; but I <U+017F>tood in no need of that Priviledge. <hi>Hi<U+017F>tory</hi> did <U+017F>upply me with plenty enough of real Dead, and real Adventures, to di<U+017F>pen<U+017F>e with my borrowing any a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tance from Fiction. You will not be <U+017F>urpri<U+017F>ed, that the Dead do <U+017F>peak of what did hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen a long time after them, you that do <U+017F>ee them entertain them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elves every day with the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of each other. I am <U+017F>ure that at this very moment you
<pb facs="tcp:135343:7"/>
know <hi>France,</hi> upon a multitude of Reports that have been made you, and that you know that <U+017F>he is at this day in point of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, what <hi>Greece</hi> was formerly. Above all, your famous Tran<U+017F>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, who has made you <U+017F>peak our Language <U+017F>o well, will not have failed to tell you, that <hi>Paris</hi> has had the <U+017F>ame e<U+017F>teem for your Works as had <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens.</hi> Happy the Man that could follow your Style as that great Man did, and in his Expre<U+017F><U+017F>ions lay hold of that fine <U+017F>implicity, and that natural plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>antne<U+017F>s, which are <U+017F>o proper for <hi>Dialogues!</hi> For my part, 'tis
<pb facs="tcp:135343:7"/>
far from my Thoughts, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to the glory of having imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated you well; I de<U+017F>ire none but that of having well known, that a Man cannot imitate a more excellent <hi>Model</hi> than your Self.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:135343:8"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135343:8"/>
            <head>The Titles and Subjects of the Dialogues contained in this Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume.</head>
            <list>
               <head>The Dialogues of the Ancient Dead.</head>
               <item>I. ALexander, Phrinea. <hi>What Characters noi<U+017F>e it mo<U+017F>t.</hi> Page 1.</item>
               <item>II. Milo, Smindirides. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>pon Nicene<U+017F>s.</hi> p. 9.</item>
               <item>III. Dido, Stratonice. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>pon the Intrigue which</hi> Virgil <hi>does wrongfully attribute to</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do. p. 15.</item>
               <item>IV. Anacreon, Ari<U+017F>totle. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>pon Philo<U+017F>ophy.</hi> p. 21.</item>
               <item>V. Homer, Ae<U+017F>op. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>pon the My<U+017F>teries of</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer<hi>'s Works.</hi> p. 29.</item>
               <item>VI. Athenais, Ica<U+017F>ia. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>pon the Fanta<U+017F>ticalne<U+017F>s of Fortunes.</hi> p. 34.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Dialogues of the Ancient Dead, with the Modern Dead.</head>
               <item>I. AUgu<U+017F>tus, Peter Aretine. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>pon Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>es.</hi> p. 40.</item>
               <item>II. Sapho, Laura. <hi>Whether it has been well or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, that Men <U+017F>hould attack, and the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men de<U+017F>end them<U+017F>elves.</hi> p. 51.</item>
               <item>III. Socrates, Montaigne. <hi>Whether the Ancients have had more Vertue than We.</hi> p. 57.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:135343:9"/>
IV. <hi>The Emperor</hi> Adrian, Margarite <hi>of</hi> Au<U+017F>tria. <hi>What Deaths are the mo<U+017F>t Generous.</hi> p. 66.</item>
               <item>V. Era<U+017F>i<U+017F>trates, Herveus. <hi>Of what u<U+017F>e are the Di<U+017F>coveries, the Modern have made in Natural Cau<U+017F>es, and in Phy<U+017F>ick.</hi> p. 78.</item>
               <item>VI. Berenice, Co<U+017F>mus Medicis <hi>the Second. <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Immortality of Name.</hi> p. 85.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Dialogues of the Modern Dead.</head>
               <item>I. ANne <hi>of</hi> Britanny, Mary <hi>of</hi> England. <hi>A Compari<U+017F>on betwixt Ambition and Love.</hi> p. 92.</item>
               <item>II. Charles V. Era<U+017F>mus. <hi>If there is any thing wherein Man may glory.</hi> p. 102.</item>
               <item>III. Elizabeth <hi>of</hi> England, <hi>The Duke of</hi> Alen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon. <hi>Upon the little Solidity of Plea<U+017F>ures.</hi> p. 110.</item>
               <item>IV. William Cabe<U+017F>tan, Albert Frederick <hi>of</hi> Brandebourg. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>pon Folly.</hi> p. 116.</item>
               <item>V. Agnes Sorel, Roxelana. <hi>Upon the Power of Women.</hi> p. 123.</item>
               <item>VI. Jane I. <hi>of</hi> Naples, An<U+017F>elm. <hi>Upon Di<U+017F>quiet for Time to come.</hi> p. 132.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:135343:9"/>
            <head>NEW DIALOGUES OF THE DEAD.</head>
            <div n="1" type="dialogue">
               <head>The Fir<U+017F>t Dialogue.</head>
               <stage>Alexander. Phrinea.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phrinea.</speaker>
                  <p>YOU may know it of all the <hi>Thebanes</hi> that lived in in my time. They will tell you that I offered them to rebuild at my own charges the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:135343:10"/>
Walls of <hi>Thebes;</hi> which you had beaten down, upon condition they would put this In<U+017F>cription upon them. <hi>Alexander the Great did beat down the<U+017F>e Walls, but Phrinea the Courti<U+017F>an has rai<U+017F>ed them up again.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>You were afraid then that future Ages <U+017F>hould not know what Trade you had driven?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phrin.</speaker>
                  <p>I tell you I had been excellent at it; and all per<U+017F>ons that are extraordinary in any Profe<U+017F><U+017F>ion whatever, are po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>ed with this folly of Monuments and In<U+017F>criptions.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis true that <hi>Rhodopea</hi> had this humour before you. Her Beauty gained her <U+017F>o much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, that with it <U+017F>he built one of tho<U+017F>e famous Pyramids in <hi>Egypt</hi> which are <U+017F>tanding to this day; and I remember that as <U+017F>he was <U+017F>peaking of it the other day to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:135343:10"/>
<U+017F>ome dead French Ladies, who pretended to have been very love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the<U+017F>e Shadows began to weep, <U+017F>aying, that in the Age and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try where they had lately lived, Beauties did not now make ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages whereby to rai<U+017F>e Pyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mids.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phrin.</speaker>
                  <p>But for my part, I had that advantage above <hi>Rhodopea,</hi> that in rai<U+017F>ing up again the Walls of <hi>Thebes,</hi> I made my <U+017F>elf equal to you, who had been the greate<U+017F>t Conquerour in the World, and made it appear that my Beauty was able to repair what your Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour had de<U+017F>troyed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>The<U+017F>e are two things which certainly did never enter into compari<U+017F>on with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. You are plea<U+017F>ed with your <U+017F>elf then, that you have been <U+017F>o Gallanted.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phrin.</speaker>
                  <p>And you, you are very
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:135343:11"/>
well <U+017F>atisfied that you have made de<U+017F>olate the better part of the World? Why was there not a <hi>Phrinea</hi> in each Town which you de<U+017F>troyed! There <U+017F>hould have remained no <U+017F>igns of your furies.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Were I to live again, I would again be a famous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phrin.</speaker>
                  <p>And I would be a love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Conquerour. Beauty has a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural right to command Men, and Valour has but a right gained by force. Beauties have a right in all Countries, <U+017F>o have not Kings nor Conquerours. But yet the better to convince you, <hi>Philip</hi> your Father was a very valiant man, <U+017F>o were you too, however you would neither of you work any fear into <hi>Demo<U+017F>thenes</hi> the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratour, who, whil<U+017F>t he lived, did nothing but inveigh again<U+017F>t you both; and another <hi>Phrinea,</hi> far
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:135343:11"/>
beyond me (for the name is lucky) being likely to lo<U+017F>e a Suit in Law of con<U+017F>equence, her Lawyer, who in vain had <U+017F>poken his be<U+017F>t for her, bethought him<U+017F>elf of putting by a great Veil, which partly co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered her, and pre<U+017F>ently upon the <U+017F>ight of her beauty, the Judges who were ju<U+017F>t going to ca<U+017F>t her, chang'd their minds. So the noi<U+017F>e of your Arms could not in a long run of years <U+017F>ilence an Oratour, and the attractives of a fair Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture did, in a moment, corrupt all <hi>Areopagus</hi> with its <U+017F>everity.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Though you have called another <hi>Phrinea</hi> to your a<U+017F><U+017F>i<U+017F>tanc, I do not believe that <hi>Alexanders</hi> Party is at all the weaker. It would be very <U+017F>ad if.....</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phrin.</speaker>
                  <p>I know what you are going to <U+017F>ay to me. <hi>Graecia, A<U+017F>ia, Per<U+017F>ia,</hi> the <hi>Indies,</hi> all the<U+017F>e make a fine <U+017F>hew: Yet, if I <U+017F>hould with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:135343:12"/>
from your glory, what does not belong to you upon that <U+017F>core; if I did give to your Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, to your Captains, to Chance it <U+017F>elf, the <U+017F>hare belonging to them, don't you think you would be a lo<U+017F>er by it? But a Fair Lady ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <U+017F>hares with any one the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of her Conque<U+017F>ts, all is her own. Believe me, the condition of a pretty Woman is a pretty condition.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>It has appeared that you have been <U+017F>o per<U+017F>waded. But do you think this part reaches <U+017F>o far as you have pu<U+017F>hed it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phrin.</speaker>
                  <p>No, no, for I am ea<U+017F>y of belief. I confe<U+017F>s I have, in an high degree, injured the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of a pretty Woman, but you hove done as much by that of a Great Man. You and I have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered too much. If I had been contented with two or three Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantries
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:135343:12"/>
at the mo<U+017F>t, I had not been irregular, and no exceptions could have been taken; but to have been galanted to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree as to have had wherewithall to rebuild the Walls of <hi>Thebes,</hi> that was indeed too too much. On the other <U+017F>ide, if you had conquered <hi>Greece</hi> only, the neighbouring I<U+017F>lands, and <U+017F>ome little part too perhaps of the Le<U+017F><U+017F>er <hi>A<U+017F>ia,</hi> and made up a State of them for your <U+017F>elf, nothing had been more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>onable; but to run on <U+017F>till with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out knowing whither, and be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways taking of Towns, and know not why, and always upon execution, without de<U+017F>ign, 'tis that that was not approved of by many judicious per<U+017F>ons.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Let tho<U+017F>e judicious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ons <U+017F>ay what they will. If I had made u<U+017F>e of my valour and good fortune with <U+017F>o much di<U+017F>cretion,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:135343:13"/>
there would <U+017F>carce have been any talk of me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phrin.</speaker>
                  <p>Nor of me neither, if I had been too di<U+017F>creet in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of my Beauty. When one will make a noi<U+017F>e only, tho<U+017F>e qualities which <U+017F>eem mo<U+017F>t rea<U+017F>on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able are not the fitte<U+017F>t for that purpo<U+017F>e.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="dialogue">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:135343:13"/>
               <head>The Second Dialogue.</head>
               <stage>Milo. Smindirides.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Smindirides.</speaker>
                  <p>THou art very proud then, <hi>Milo,</hi> of having carried an <hi>Ox</hi> on thy <U+017F>houlders, at the Olimpick Games.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Milo.</speaker>
                  <p>For certain it was a very brave action. All <hi>Greece</hi> did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud it, and the honour of it reached as far as the City of <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tona</hi> my native Country, which has afforded an infinite number of <U+017F>tout lu<U+017F>ty men. On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, thy City of <hi>Sibaris</hi> will be cried down to eternity becau<U+017F>e of the effeminacy of her Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, who bani<U+017F>hed all Cocks from their Town, le<U+017F>t they <U+017F>hould
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:135343:14"/>
be wakened by them; and when they made any invitation to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ons, they invited them a year before-hand, that they might have the more lea<U+017F>ure to make their Treat with as much dainti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s as they would them<U+017F>elves.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Smin.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou jeere<U+017F>t the <hi>Sibari<U+017F>ts;</hi> but thou gro<U+017F>s <hi>Crotonian,</hi> do<U+017F>t not thou think that in boa<U+017F>ting to have carried an Ox is not to be very like them?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Milo.</speaker>
                  <p>And thou, do<U+017F>t thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve to have behaved thy <U+017F>elf Man-like, when thou made<U+017F>t thy complaint that thou had<U+017F>t pa<U+017F><U+017F>ed a night without <U+017F>leeping, becau<U+017F>e one of the Ro<U+017F>es wherewith thy Bed was <U+017F>trewed, lay folded in two under thee?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Smin.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis true, I was <U+017F>o nice as that comes to; but why do<U+017F>t thou think it <U+017F>o <U+017F>trange?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Milo.</speaker>
                  <p>And how can it be but I mu<U+017F>t think it <U+017F>o?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:135343:14"/>
                  <speaker>Smin.</speaker>
                  <p>What did<U+017F>t thou never <U+017F>ee a Lover, who being loaded with the favours of a Mi<U+017F>tre<U+017F>s, to whom he had rendred <U+017F>ome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable <U+017F>ervices, was troubled in the po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F><U+017F>ion of his happine<U+017F>s, for fear that grateful acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <U+017F>hould work more in the heart of the Beauty, than her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Milo.</speaker>
                  <p>No, I never <U+017F>aw any <U+017F>uch. But what if <U+017F>uch a thing <U+017F>hould be?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Smin.</speaker>
                  <p>And did<U+017F>t thou never hear talk of <U+017F>ome Conqueror, who, at his return from a glorious Expedition, <U+017F>hould not be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether <U+017F>atisfied with his Triumphs, becau<U+017F>e Fortune might have had a greater <U+017F>hare than either his Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour or his Conduct, and that his de<U+017F>igns might have taken upon fal<U+017F>e and ill grounded Mea<U+017F>ures?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:135343:15"/>
                  <speaker>Milo.</speaker>
                  <p>No, I never heard <U+017F>peak of any <U+017F>uch. But once again, what do<U+017F>t thou infer hereupon?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Smin.</speaker>
                  <p>That this <U+017F>ame Lover, and this Conqueror, and generally all men, although they <U+017F>hould lie upon Flowers, could not <U+017F>leep if one <U+017F>ingle Leaf only were foulded in two. A little thing <U+017F>poils a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ure. Plea<U+017F>ures are Beds of Ro<U+017F>es, where 'tis very hard to have every Leaf remain <U+017F>pread out, and not one to lie double; yet the fould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of one alone is enough to cau<U+017F>e a great unea<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Milo.</speaker>
                  <p>I am not very much ver<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the<U+017F>e affairs; but methinks, that thou, and the Lover, and thy <U+017F>uppo<U+017F>ed Conqueror, and all of you together, are extreamly too blame. Why do you make your <U+017F>elves <U+017F>o nice?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Smin.</speaker>
                  <p>Ah <hi>Milo!</hi> your Wits are not <hi>Crotonians,</hi> as thou art; but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:135343:15"/>
they are <hi>Sibari<U+017F>ts,</hi> more refined yet than I was.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Milo.</speaker>
                  <p>I <U+017F>ee well enough what the matter is. Your Wits, a<U+017F><U+017F>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly, enjoy more plea<U+017F>ures than they need, and they let their nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s retrench what they have too much. They are willing to have <U+017F>ome feeling of the lea<U+017F>t di<U+017F>likes, becau<U+017F>e there are other ways de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights enough for them; and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that account I find they are in the right.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Smin.</speaker>
                  <p>There's nothing at all of that. Your Wits enjoy no more plea<U+017F>ures than they need.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Milo.</speaker>
                  <p>They are fools then to make them<U+017F>elves <U+017F>o nice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Smin.</speaker>
                  <p>There is the mi<U+017F>chief of it. Nicene<U+017F>s does become men ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well: it ari<U+017F>es from the good qualities, both of the mind, and heart: Man takes a delight to have them, and he that wants them en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:135343:16"/>
for them; in the mean time, nicene<U+017F>s does le<U+017F><U+017F>en the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of plea<U+017F>ures, and one is not overloaded with them. It makes them le<U+017F>s <U+017F>en<U+017F>ible; and plea<U+017F>ures, of them<U+017F>elves, are not over lively. How men are to be pitied! Their natural condition <U+017F>upplies them with few plea<U+017F>ing things, and their rea<U+017F>on teaches them to delight yet le<U+017F>s in them.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="dialogue">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:135343:16"/>
               <head>The Third Dialogue,</head>
               <stage>Dido. Stratonice.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dido.</speaker>
                  <p>ALas! how wretched am I, my poor <hi>Strationice!</hi> you know how I have lived. I was <U+017F>o exact in my fidelity to my fir<U+017F>t Husband, that I burnt my <U+017F>elf alive rather than I would take a <U+017F>econd. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, I could not pre<U+017F>erve my <U+017F>elf from being ill <U+017F>poken of. A Poet, <hi>Virgil</hi> by name, has been plea<U+017F>ed to change a wi<U+017F>e Woman, <U+017F>o <U+017F>trict as my <U+017F>elf, into a young Go<U+017F><U+017F>ip, that lets her <U+017F>elf be taken with the hand<U+017F>omene<U+017F>s of a Stranger the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fir<U+017F>t day <U+017F>he <U+017F>ees him. My whole <U+017F>tory is quite contrary. To tell the truth, as to the pile of Wood
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:135343:17"/>
wherein I was con<U+017F>umed, I had right done me. But gue<U+017F>s why I ca<U+017F>t my <U+017F>elf into it? It is not out of any farther fear of being obliged to marry a <U+017F>econd time, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cau<U+017F>e I am grown de<U+017F>perate upon this <U+017F>tranger's leaving of me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Stratonice.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed, the con<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of this may be very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous. There will hardly be any more Women that will burn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elves out of a conjugal fidelity, if, after their death, a Poet may have the liberty to <U+017F>ay what he will of them. May be too, your <hi>Virgil</hi> was not <U+017F>o much in the wrong. Has he not cleared <U+017F>ome intrigues in your life, which you hoped would not have been known? Who knows? I would not an<U+017F>wer for you, upon the faith of your Pile.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dido.</speaker>
                  <p>If the Gallantry which <hi>Virgil</hi> does lay to me had any truth in it, I would be content to be <U+017F>u<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:135343:17"/>
but he allots me to be a Lover of <hi>Aeneas,</hi> a man that was in his Grave three hundred years before I came into the world.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Strat.</speaker>
                  <p>You <U+017F>ay <U+017F>omething now. Neverthele<U+017F>s, <hi>Aeneas</hi> and you, you <U+017F>eemed much to be a fit match for one another: You both of you had been forced to leave your Country; you both of you <U+017F>eeked a fortune in <U+017F>tranger Countries; he was a Widower, you a Widow: the<U+017F>e points agree well together. It is true, you were born three hundred years after him; but <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gil</hi> <U+017F>aw <U+017F>o many rea<U+017F>ons to match you together, that he thought three hundred years difference betwixt you were of no con<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dido.</speaker>
                  <p>What an Argument there is? How three hundred years are not three hundred years, and in <U+017F>pight of that ob<U+017F>tacle, two per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ons
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:135343:18"/>
may meet together, and love one another?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Strat.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh! 'Tis in that point <hi>Virgil</hi> did mean <U+017F>ome Cunning: Sure he was a man of the times: He would make it appear, that in matter of Love Concerns, we mu<U+017F>t not judge upon Appearances; and that tho<U+017F>e that have the lea<U+017F>t, are many times the true<U+017F>t.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dido.</speaker>
                  <p>What had he to do to call my Reputation in que<U+017F>tion, by in<U+017F>erting this <U+017F>ine My<U+017F>tery in his Works?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Strat.</speaker>
                  <p>But what? has he turn'd you into ridicule? has he made you <U+017F>peak impertinencies?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dido.</speaker>
                  <p>No, not at all. Here he has recited his Poem to me; and the whole piece where he makes me appear, is indeed divine, Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>in Germain to detraction. In it I am all Beauty, there I <U+017F>peak rare things upon my pretended Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:135343:18"/>
and if <hi>Virgil</hi> were obliged to own me for an hone<U+017F>t Woman in his <hi>Aeneid,</hi> the <hi>Aeneid</hi> would be the wor<U+017F>e for it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Strat.</speaker>
                  <p>What do you complain of then? you have a Gallantry put upon you which you did not enjoy; a great mi<U+017F>chance indeed! But, to make you amends again, you are <U+017F>et out for a Beauty and a Wit, which you were not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dido.</speaker>
                  <p>What a comfort!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Strat.</speaker>
                  <p>I know not what hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour you are of; but mo<U+017F>t Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, if I am not mi<U+017F>taken, had rather have their Vertue a little que<U+017F>tioned, than either their Wit or their Beauty: for my part, that was my humour. A Painter at the Court of the King of <hi>Syria,</hi> my Husband, was di<U+017F><U+017F>atisfied with me; and out of revenge, he drew me as in the Arms of a Soldier. He expo<U+017F>ed his Picture to view, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:135343:19"/>
took his heels. My Subjects, zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of my Glory, would have burnt this Picture publickly; but I being drawn admirably well, and full of Beauty, though the po<U+017F>tures allotted me therein were not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious to my Vertue, I forbad the burning of it, and recalled the Painter, whom I pardoned. If you'll believe me, you'll do the <U+017F>ame by <hi>Virgil.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dido.</speaker>
                  <p>That would do well, if the fir<U+017F>t degree of Merit in a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man did con<U+017F>i<U+017F>t in being hand<U+017F>om, or in being witty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Stratonice.</speaker>
                  <p>I do not take upon me to decide what that fir<U+017F>t merit is; but commonly, the fir<U+017F>t que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tion one asks of a Woman one knows not, is, Is <U+017F>he hand<U+017F>ome? next, has <U+017F>he any Wit? a third is <U+017F>eldom asked.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="dialogue">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:135343:19"/>
               <head>The Fourth Dialogue.</head>
               <stage>Anacreon, Ari<U+017F>totle.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ari<U+017F>totle.</speaker>
                  <p>I Could never have thought that a petty Ballad-maker would have dared to compare him<U+017F>elf with a Philo<U+017F>opher of <U+017F>o great repute as I am.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anacreon.</speaker>
                  <p>You make the name of <hi>Philo<U+017F>opher</hi> <U+017F>ound very loud; but, I wi<U+017F>h my petty Songs, have notwith<U+017F>tanding been called <hi>the wi<U+017F>e Anacreon,</hi> and methinks the Title of <hi>Philo<U+017F>opher</hi> is not <U+017F>o good as that of <hi>Wi<U+017F>e.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ari<U+017F>t.</speaker>
                  <p>Tho<U+017F>e who a<U+017F>cribed you that quality, did not very well mind what they <U+017F>aid. What had you ever done to de<U+017F>erve it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:135343:20"/>
                  <speaker>Anacr.</speaker>
                  <p>I had done nothing but drink, <U+017F>ing, and fall in love; and the wonder is, that I had this name of <hi>Wi<U+017F>e</hi> given me for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus, whereas you had only that of <hi>Philo<U+017F>opher</hi> given you, which co<U+017F>t you a world of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours: For how many Nights have you <U+017F>pent in <U+017F>ifting the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate Que<U+017F>tions of the <hi>Diale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctick?</hi> How many great Volumes have you writ upon ob<U+017F>cure mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which perhaps you did not very well under<U+017F>tand your <U+017F>elf.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ari<U+017F>t.</speaker>
                  <p>I confe<U+017F>s you have taken a more ea<U+017F>ie way to attain to <hi>Wi<U+017F>dom,</hi> and you mu<U+017F>t needs have been an able man to find out a way to purcha<U+017F>e more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with your Lute and your Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, then the greate<U+017F>t men have gained with their watchings and toyls.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anacr.</speaker>
                  <p>You think to jeer, but
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:135343:20"/>
I will maintain that 'tis harder to drink and <U+017F>ing, as I have <U+017F>ung, and as I have drunk, than to philo<U+017F>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phize as you have done; to <U+017F>ing and to drink as I have, a man's Soul <U+017F>hould be freed from all vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions, <U+017F>hould aim no more at what does not depend upon us, <U+017F>hould always be in a di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ition to take time as it <U+017F>hould come. In fine, there would be many little Affairs to regulate about him; and though there be no great matter of Philo<U+017F>ophy in all this, one has trouble enough for all that to compa<U+017F>s it. But a man may philo<U+017F>ophize as you have done upon more rea<U+017F>onable terms. One is not obliged to cure ones <U+017F>elf neither of Ambition, nor of Covetou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s; a man may have a favourable acce<U+017F>s to <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Court; he may purcha<U+017F>e Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ents of five hundred thou<U+017F>and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:135343:21"/>
Crowns, which he does not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether apply in experiments of Nature, according to the intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Donor; and in a word, this kind of Philo<U+017F>ophy leads to things that are oppo<U+017F>ite enough to Philo<U+017F>ophy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ari<U+017F>t.</speaker>
                  <p>Some body here below mu<U+017F>t needs have <U+017F>poken ill of me to you; but when all is done, Man is not Man, but upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Rea<U+017F>on, and nothing is more excellent than to teach o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers what u<U+017F>e they <U+017F>hould make of <U+017F>tudying Nature, and clearing all tho<U+017F>e Intricacies which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F>es unto us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anacr.</speaker>
                  <p>Thus men pervert the u<U+017F>e of every thing: Philo<U+017F>ophy in it <U+017F>elf is an admirable thing, and may be very <U+017F>erviceable to them; but becau<U+017F>e <U+017F>he would be unea<U+017F>ie to them, if <U+017F>he did meddle with their Concerns, and <U+017F>ettle her <U+017F>elf
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:135343:21"/>
among them to regulate their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<U+017F><U+017F>ions, they have di<U+017F>patched <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er away into the Heavens to <U+017F>et <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Planets in order, and mea<U+017F>ure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heir motions, or el<U+017F>e they pace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er up and down the Earth, to make her examine all they <U+017F>ee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pon it. In <U+017F>hort, they always <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mploy her as far off them<U+017F>elves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s 'tis po<U+017F><U+017F>ible. In the mean time, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s they will be Philo<U+017F>ophers at an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<U+017F>ie rate, they have the art how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o extend and <U+017F>et out this Title, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd they give it for the mo<U+017F>t part <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o tho<U+017F>e that dive into natural Cau<U+017F>es.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ari<U+017F>t.</speaker>
                  <p>And how can one give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hem a fitter Title?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anacreon.</speaker>
                  <p>Philo<U+017F>ophy concerns <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er <U+017F>elf with Men only, and not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t all with the re<U+017F>t of the World. The A<U+017F>tronomer mu<U+017F>es on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tars and Planets, the Naturali<U+017F>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on<U+017F>iders Nature, and the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>opher
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:135343:22"/>
thinks of him<U+017F>elf. But wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> would have been one upon <U+017F>uc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hard Conditions? Alas! <U+017F>carc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> any body. Philo<U+017F>ophers then ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> di<U+017F>pen<U+017F>ed withal from being Phi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lo<U+017F>ophers, and men are contente<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> they <U+017F>hould be A<U+017F>tronomers, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Naturali<U+017F>ts. For my part, I wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not of a temper to engage my<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/><U+017F>elf into Speculations; but I'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> <U+017F>ure, that there is le<U+017F>s Philo<U+017F>ophy i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> many Books, that make profe<U+017F><U+017F>io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of treating of it, then in <U+017F>ome o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tho<U+017F>e petty Songs which you <U+017F>o much undervalue; for exampl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in this.</p>
                  <lg type="song">
                     <l>If Gold length of life did be<U+017F>tow,</l>
                     <l>Farther my ambition <U+017F>hould not go<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Then greedily to heap up trea<U+017F>ure.</l>
                     <l>When Death to me a vi<U+017F>it made,</l>
                     <l>Quickly return would I bid her to her <U+017F>hade,</l>
                     <l>In giving her, what I had, without mea<U+017F>ure.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb n="27" facs="tcp:135343:22"/>
But if <hi>Atropos</hi> and her Si<U+017F>ters <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere do not of this allow,</l>
                     <l>Gold <U+017F>hall no more be my care,</l>
                     <l>Women, Wine, and good Cheer</l>
                     <l>Shall my diver<U+017F>ions make I vow.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ari<U+017F>t.</speaker>
                  <p>If you will call that Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo<U+017F>ophy only which looks into Manners, there is in my Morals that which is as good as your Song; for that ob<U+017F>curity which I'm taxed of, and which is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps in <U+017F>ome of my Books, is not to be found in my Writings upon that matter; and the whole World has owned that there was nothing finer nor more clear than what I have <U+017F>aid concerning Pa<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ions.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anacr.</speaker>
                  <p>What an abu<U+017F>e! The que<U+017F>tion is not to define Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions methodically, as 'tis <U+017F>aid you have done, but to ma<U+017F>ter them. Men willingly deliver up their Evils to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:135343:23"/>
Philo<U+017F>ophy for her to con<U+017F>ider them, but not to cure them; and they have found the <U+017F>ecret of fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming a Moral which reaches them no nearer than A<U+017F>tronomy does Can a man forbear laughing, to <U+017F>ee <U+017F>ome, that for money, preach up the contempt of riches, and Cowards that fall together by the ears about the definition of Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimous?</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="dialogue">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:135343:23"/>
               <head>The Fifth Dialogue.</head>
               <stage>Homer. Ae<U+017F>op.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Homer.</speaker>
                  <p>ALL tho<U+017F>e <hi>Fables</hi> which you have now related to me, cannot, indeed, be admired e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: You mu<U+017F>t needs have been indued with a great deal of art, that you could thus di<U+017F>gui<U+017F>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n little Tales, the mo<U+017F>t important <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<U+017F>tructions of Morality, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver your thoughts under the<U+017F>e Repre<U+017F>entations which are <U+017F>o pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and <U+017F>o familiar.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ae<U+017F>op,</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis very plea<U+017F>ing to me that I am applauded by you for an Art, wherein you were <U+017F>o care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Homer,</speaker>
                  <p>I? I did never pretend to it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:135343:24"/>
                  <speaker>Ae<U+017F>op,</speaker>
                  <p>How, did you not make it your bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s to hide great my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>teries in your works?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hom.</speaker>
                  <p>Alas! not at all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ae<U+017F>.</speaker>
                  <p>Neverthele<U+017F>s all the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of my time did <U+017F>ay as much; there was not a word in the <hi>Ili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ads,</hi> nor in the <hi>Odi<U+017F><U+017F>ea,</hi> but they gave it the fine<U+017F>t Allegories in the World. They did maintain, that all the Secrets of Divinity, of Natural and Moral Philo<U+017F>ophy, and of the Mathematicks, were inclo<U+017F>ed in your Writings. Truly 'twas <U+017F>omewhat difficult to di<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clo<U+017F>e them, and where one found out a Moral <U+017F>ence, another found out a Natural <U+017F>ence; but they agreed that you knew all, and had <U+017F>aid all to him that right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly under<U+017F>tood it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hom.</speaker>
                  <p>Without lying, I did mi<U+017F>tru<U+017F>t that <U+017F>ome <U+017F>ort of people would conceive I had <U+017F>ome cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:135343:24"/>
meaning, where I intended none. As there is nothing like Prophecying things afar off in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of the event; <U+017F>o there is nothing like putting off <hi>Fables,</hi> in expectation of the Allegory.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ae<U+017F>op,</speaker>
                  <p>You mu<U+017F>t needs have been a bold man, to entru<U+017F>t your Readers with the care of putting Allegories in your Poems. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts would you have been, if they had been taken literally?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Homer,</speaker>
                  <p>Well then, the harm would not have been <U+017F>o great.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ae<U+017F>.</speaker>
                  <p>What? tho<U+017F>e <hi>Gods who maim</hi> one another; that Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering <hi>Jove,</hi> who in a Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Deities</hi> threatens to beat Maje<U+017F>tical <hi>Juno;</hi> That <hi>Mars,</hi> who being wounded by <hi>Diomedes,</hi> bawls, you <U+017F>ay, like nine or ten thou<U+017F>and men, and does not act like one alone; (for in<U+017F>tead of routing all the <hi>Greeks,</hi> he goes and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:135343:25"/>
complains of his Wound to <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter)</hi> all this would have been well without an Allegory?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hom.</speaker>
                  <p>Why not? You fancy that the Minds of men <U+017F>eek for Truth altogether? Di<U+017F>abu<U+017F>e your <U+017F>elf. Man's mind and fal<U+017F>hood <U+017F>ympathize mo<U+017F>t <U+017F>trangely. If you have a truth to <U+017F>peak, you'l do very well to fold it up in <hi>Fables,</hi> 'twill be far more plea<U+017F>ing. If you'l relate <hi>Fables,</hi> they may take without having the lea<U+017F>t colour of truth in them. Thus Truth has need to borrow the <U+017F>hape of Fal<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood to be kindly received in the mind of man; but Fal<U+017F>hood creeps into it well enough in its own proper <U+017F>hape, for that is the place of its birth, and its u<U+017F>ual place of aboad, and Truth is there a meer <U+017F>tranger. Nay, I will tell you more than this comes to. If I <U+017F>hould have killed my <U+017F>elf to fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:135343:25"/>
allegorical <hi>Fables,</hi> it might ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y well have happened that mo<U+017F>t people would have taken the <hi>Fable,</hi> as a thing likely enough to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ave had been <U+017F>o, and would have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et the Allegory alone; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eed, you ought to know that my Gods, <U+017F>uch as they are (and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll My<U+017F>teries laid a<U+017F>ide) have not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>een thought ridiculous.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ae<U+017F>.</speaker>
                  <p>This makes me quake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: I am terribly afraid that it will be thought that Bea<U+017F>ts might have <U+017F>poken as they do in my A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologies.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hom.</speaker>
                  <p>A pretty fear indeed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ae<U+017F>op,</speaker>
                  <p>Why what? If people have believed that the Gods could have held tho<U+017F>e Di<U+017F>cour<U+017F>es you made them hold; why will they not believe that Bea<U+017F>ts did <U+017F>peak in the manner as I made them <U+017F>peak?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hom.</speaker>
                  <p>Ah! the Ca<U+017F>e is not the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:135343:26"/>
<U+017F>ame; Men are willing enoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that the Gods <U+017F>hould be as grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> great Fools as they; but the are not willing that Bea<U+017F>ts <U+017F>hou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> be <U+017F>o wi<U+017F>e.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="dialogue">
               <head>The Sixth Dialogue<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g>
               </head>
               <stage>Athenais. Ica<U+017F>ia.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ica<U+017F>ia.</speaker>
                  <p>SInce you will know my Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tune, I will tell it you: T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Emperour under whom I live had a mind to marry; and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> he might the better choo<U+017F>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Empre<U+017F>s, he cau<U+017F>ed it to be pub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>li<U+017F>hed, That all Women th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> thought them<U+017F>elves hand<U+017F>om an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> taking enough to pretend to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Throne, <U+017F>hould come to <hi>Con<U+017F>tan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinople.</hi> God only knows what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:135343:26"/>
world of people there was. I went thither, and I made no doubt but with my youth, my brisk eyes, and my way, which was plea<U+017F>ant and curious enough, I might not put in for the Empire. The day of the meeting together of <U+017F>o many pretty Pretenders, we all of us ran over in a di<U+017F>tracted manner the faces of each other; and I took notice with <U+017F>atisfaction, that my Rivals did look but with an ill eye upon me. The Emperour ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared; at fir<U+017F>t he pa<U+017F><U+017F>ed by <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral rows of Beauties without <U+017F>aying a word; but when he came at me, my eyes were very <U+017F>erviceable to me, and they <U+017F>tayed him. Indeed, quoth he, looking upon me with a countenance <U+017F>uch as I could wi<U+017F>h, <hi>Women are very dangerous; they may do a great deal of harm:</hi> I thought<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> there was only a little wit to be u<U+017F>ed in
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:135343:27"/>
the ca<U+017F>e, and then I was Empre<U+017F>s: and in the trouble I was in, what with hope, what with joy, I <U+017F>trove to make an an<U+017F>wer. <hi>In recompence of that, Lord, Women may do, and <U+017F>ometimes have done much good.</hi> This An<U+017F>wer <U+017F>poiled all; the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour thought it <U+017F>o godly, that he dur<U+017F>t not marry me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Athenais,</speaker>
                  <p>Sure this Emperour was of a <U+017F>trange humour, to be <U+017F>o afraid of Wit, and 'tis to be pre<U+017F>umed he had but little judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in it, to believe that your An<U+017F>wer did argue much; for to be free with you, 'tis no very good one, and you have no great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to lay to your own charge.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ica<U+017F>ia,</speaker>
                  <p>Thus go Fortunes; Wit alone made you an Empre<U+017F>s, and an appearance only of Wit hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred me from being one. You were ver<U+017F>ed to in Philo<U+017F>ophy, which is far wor<U+017F>e than to be witty; and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:135343:27"/>
notwith<U+017F>tanding all this, you mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the young <hi>Theodo<U+017F>ius.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Athen.</speaker>
                  <p>If I <U+017F>hould have had <U+017F>uch an example as yours before me, it would have frighted me. After my Father had made me a very learned, and a very godly La<U+017F>s, he did di<U+017F>inherit me; <U+017F>o <U+017F>ure did he make him<U+017F>elf, that with my learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and my fine wit, I could not mi<U+017F>s of making my Fortune; and to <U+017F>ay the truth, I believed it as well as he. But now I <U+017F>ee I ran a great hazard, and that it was not impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible but I might remain without any means, and have Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo<U+017F>ophy alone for my Portion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ica<U+017F>.</speaker>
                  <p>No <U+017F>ure, but as good luck would have it for you, my adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had not yet happened. It would be plea<U+017F>ant enough that upon the like occa<U+017F>ion as that which befel me, <U+017F>ome other that knew my Story, and would draw
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:135343:28"/>
an advantage from it, were <U+017F>o crafty as to make no <U+017F>hew of wit, and that people would laugh at her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Athen.</speaker>
                  <p>I would not be an<U+017F>wer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for her <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s herein, in ca<U+017F>e <U+017F>he were upon de<U+017F>ign; but many times one does by chance commit the happie<U+017F>t Follies in the world. Have you not heard talk of a Painter who had <U+017F>o well drawn <U+017F>ome Bunches of Grapes, that <U+017F>ome Birds were deceived in them, and came and nibled at them? Do you judge what a Repute this gave him. But the Grapes were born in the Picture by a little Country Boy; and the Painter was told, That truly they mu<U+017F>t needs be well done, <U+017F>ince they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<U+017F>ed the Birds to them; but that the little Country Boy mu<U+017F>t needs be very ill done, <U+017F>ince the Birds were not afraid of him. They
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:135343:28"/>
were in the right; Yet if the Painter had not over-<U+017F>een him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elf in the little Pea<U+017F>ant, the Grapes would not have had that prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s as they had.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ica<U+017F>.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly, let a man do what he will in the world, he does not know what he does; and after the adventure of this Painter, we ought to tremble even in tho<U+017F>e Affairs, where we behave our <U+017F>elves well, and fear le<U+017F>t we have done no fault that might have been nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary; all is uncertain. It looks as though Fortune took care to give different Succe<U+017F><U+017F>es to one and the <U+017F>ame thing, to the end <U+017F>he may always laugh at hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Rea<U+017F>on, which is uncaple of any certain Rule.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:135343:29"/>
            <head>DIALOGUES OF THE <hi>Ancient Dead</hi> WITH THE <hi>Modern Dead.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="dialogue">
               <head>The Fir<U+017F>t Dialogue.</head>
               <stage>Augustus. Peter Aretine.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Peter Aretine.</speaker>
                  <p>YES, I was a fine Wit in my time, and I made a pretty con<U+017F>iderable Fortune with Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:135343:29"/>
                  <speaker>Augu<U+017F>tus,</speaker>
                  <p>You writ then many Books for them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P. Aretine,</speaker>
                  <p>None at all; I had a Pen<U+017F>ion from all the Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> and that could not have been if I <U+017F>hould have <U+017F>ate writing of Prai<U+017F>es. They had Wars with one another; when one had the better of the Day, the other had the better of it: it was not po<U+017F><U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to give them all their Prai<U+017F>es.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Augu<U+017F>tus,</speaker>
                  <p>What did you then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P. Aret.</speaker>
                  <p>I made Ver<U+017F>es again<U+017F>t them: They could not be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into a <hi>Panegyrick,</hi> but into a <hi>Satyr</hi> they might. I had <U+017F>o well <U+017F>pread abroad the Terrous of my Name, that they allowed me Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to enable me to commit Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies in <U+017F>afety.</p>
                  <p>The Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, who you mu<U+017F>t needs have heard <U+017F>peak of here below, being gone very unadvi<U+017F>edly towards
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:135343:30"/>
the Coa<U+017F>ts of <hi>Africa,</hi> to receive an Overthrow, did immediately <U+017F>end me a Chain of Gold. I received it; and looking <U+017F>adly upon it, <hi>Ah!</hi> <U+017F>aid I aloud, <hi>this is but a <U+017F>mall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for <U+017F>o great a folly as he has committed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <p>You had found a new kind of way to get money of Princes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P. Aret.</speaker>
                  <p>Had not I cau<U+017F>e to conceive <U+017F>ome hopes of a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Fortune, in <U+017F>ettling my <U+017F>elf a Revenue upon the follies of others? It is a good foundation, and does yield well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <p>Whatever you can <U+017F>ay of it, the prai<U+017F>ing Trade is <U+017F>ure<U+017F>t, and by con<U+017F>equence the be<U+017F>t.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P. Aret.</speaker>
                  <p>What would you have? I was not impudent enough to prai<U+017F>e.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <p>Why? You were impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent enough to make Satyrs upon Crowned Heads.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:135343:30"/>
                  <speaker>P. Aret.</speaker>
                  <p>It is not the <U+017F>ame thing to make Satyrs: it is not always nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary to undervalue tho<U+017F>e they are made of; but to give <U+017F>ome certain unreli<U+017F>hing prai<U+017F>es, I fancy a man mu<U+017F>t in <U+017F>ome kind contemn tho<U+017F>e very per<U+017F>ons he prai<U+017F>es, and think them great Cullies. With what face could <hi>Virgil</hi> tell you, that it was unknown in what qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity you would rank your <U+017F>elf among the Gods; and that it was uncertain, whether you would take upon you the care of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of the Earth, or whether you would make your <U+017F>elf a God of the Sea, by taking to Wife a Daughter of <hi>Thetis,</hi> who would willingly have purcha<U+017F>ed the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of your Alliance, though it had co<U+017F>t her all her Waters; or, in fine, whether you would quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter your <U+017F>elf in the Heavens, near <hi>Scorpio,</hi> who held the place of two
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:135343:31"/>
Signs, and who, upon your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, would have <U+017F>traitned him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elf more?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <p>Be not <U+017F>urpri<U+017F>ed at <hi>Virgil</hi>'s boldne<U+017F>s. When a man is prai<U+017F>ed<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> he does not take take tho<U+017F>e prai<U+017F>es in the <U+017F>tricte<U+017F>t <U+017F>en<U+017F>e; he helps out the Letter, and the Writer's ba<U+017F>h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulne<U+017F>s receives great ea<U+017F>e from the <U+017F>elf-love of them to whom he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies them. Many times we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine we de<U+017F>erve prai<U+017F>es which we have not; and how <U+017F>hall we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that we did not de<U+017F>erve tho<U+017F>e we have?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P. Aret.</speaker>
                  <p>You did hope then, upon <hi>Virgil</hi>'s word, that you <U+017F>hould marry a Sea-Nymph, or that you <U+017F>hould have an Apartment in the <hi>Zodiac?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <p>No, no. There is <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be deducted from tho<U+017F>e kind of prai<U+017F>es, to reduce them to <U+017F>ome rea<U+017F>onable mea<U+017F>ure; but, to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:135343:31"/>
<U+017F>peak the truth, the abatement we make is very little, and we take them at our own rates. In <U+017F>hort, let a man be prai<U+017F>ed in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner you will, he will always take the advantage of believing that he is above all common prai<U+017F>es, and that his merit did reduce the prai<U+017F>er to go beyond all bounds. Vanity has diver<U+017F>ity of Shapes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P. Aret.</speaker>
                  <p>I <U+017F>ee well enough, there mu<U+017F>t be no difficulty made to pu<U+017F>h prai<U+017F>es to the heighth of exce<U+017F>s; but, at lea<U+017F>t, as to <U+017F>uch as are contrary to one another, how can one have the impudence to allow them to Princes? I will lay a wager, for example, that when you did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge your <U+017F>elf of your Enemies without any <U+017F>hew of mercy, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was thought more glorious by all your Court, than to thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der out your fury upon every thing that had the Temerity to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<U+017F>e
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:135343:32"/>
you; but <U+017F>o <U+017F>oon as you had done any action that was mild, the face of things changed, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was found in revenge, but a barbarous and inhumane Glory: one part of your life was prai<U+017F>ed to the prejudice of the other. For my part, I <U+017F>hould have been afraid le<U+017F>t you would have given your <U+017F>elf the recreation to take me at my own words, and would have <U+017F>aid to me; <hi>Chu<U+017F>e either Severity, or Clemency, to make the Character of an Hero: but when this is done, <U+017F>tick to your own choice.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, will you have one look <U+017F>o narrowly to it? 'Tis for the advantage of great per<U+017F>ons, that all matters <U+017F>hould be proble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical for flattery. Do what they will, they cannot fail to be prai<U+017F>ed; if it be for things that are oppo<U+017F>ite, 'tis becau<U+017F>e they have more than one kind of merit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:135343:32"/>
                  <speaker>P. Aret.</speaker>
                  <p>But what? Had you never no <U+017F>cruple upon you about all tho<U+017F>e Elegies which were heap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon you? was there any need of <U+017F>training a man's wit, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that they were intended to you? Prai<U+017F>es do not di<U+017F>tingui<U+017F>h Princes; Heroes have no more than others: but Po<U+017F>terity does di<U+017F>tingui<U+017F>h the prai<U+017F>es which have been given to different Princes. Some <U+017F>he confirms, and others <U+017F>he declares to be ba<U+017F>e flatteries.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <p>You will then, at lea<U+017F>t, yield, that I did de<U+017F>erve the prai<U+017F>es given me, <U+017F>ince 'tis certain that Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>terity has ratified them by her Judgment. Nay, in this ca<U+017F>e, I have <U+017F>ome cau<U+017F>e to complain of her; for <U+017F>he has <U+017F>o u<U+017F>ed her <U+017F>elf to look upon me as the Model of Princes, that 'tis u<U+017F>ual to prai<U+017F>e them, by comparing them to me, and oftentimes the compari<U+017F>on does injure me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:135343:33"/>
                  <speaker>P. Aret.</speaker>
                  <p>Comfort your <U+017F>elf: you will be no farther troubled with this cau<U+017F>e of complaint. To hear how all the Dead that come hither do <U+017F>peak of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth now reigning in <hi>France,</hi> 'tis he that will be looked upon hereafter as the Model of Princes; and I fore<U+017F>ee, that henceforwards it will be thought that greater prai<U+017F>es cannot be given them, than by allotting them <U+017F>ome re<U+017F>emblance with this great King.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <p>Well then? Do not you believe that tho<U+017F>e to whom <U+017F>o great an exaggeration <U+017F>hall be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<U+017F><U+017F>ed, will hearken to it with plea<U+017F>ure?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P. Aret.</speaker>
                  <p>That may be. People are <U+017F>o de<U+017F>irous of Prai<U+017F>es, that Equality and Truth are di<U+017F>pen<U+017F>ed withall; and <U+017F>o are all requi<U+017F>ite Properties.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:135343:33"/>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <p>It's clear enough to be <U+017F>een that your aim is to exterminate all prai<U+017F>es. If none but good ones <U+017F>hould be given, who would trouble him<U+017F>elf to give them?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P. Aret.</speaker>
                  <p>All that <U+017F>hould be<U+017F>tow them without Intere<U+017F>t, 'tis their right alone to prai<U+017F>e. How hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens it that your <hi>Virgil</hi> did prai<U+017F>e <hi>Cato</hi> <U+017F>o much, when he <U+017F>aid that he did pre<U+017F>ide in the A<U+017F><U+017F>embly of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>etter <U+017F>ort of per<U+017F>ons, who are <U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from the others in the <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ian</hi> Shades? 'Tis becau<U+017F>e he was dead; and <hi>Virgil,</hi> that expected nothing from him, nor from his Family, be<U+017F>towed but one Ver<U+017F>e upon him, and made a rea<U+017F>onable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hought the bounds of his Elogy. How comes it that he <U+017F>poke <U+017F>o ill of you in <U+017F>o many words, at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eginning of the <hi>Georgicks?</hi> You <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llowed him a Pen<U+017F>ion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:135343:34"/>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <p>I have then flung away <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> great deal of money in prai<U+017F>es?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>P. Aret.</speaker>
                  <p>I am <U+017F>orry for it. Why did not you do as one of your Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F><U+017F>ors has done; who, as <U+017F>oon a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he had attained the Empire, did by a Declaration, expre<U+017F>ly forbi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the making of Ver<U+017F>es for him a any time?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <p>Alas! He had greater rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/><U+017F>on than I. Tho<U+017F>e prai<U+017F>es whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pre<U+017F>ent them<U+017F>elves to us are not th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> true ones, but tho<U+017F>e are which w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> <U+017F>natch up by the by.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="dialogue">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:135343:34"/>
               <head>The Second Dialogue.</head>
               <stage>Sapho. Laura.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Laura.</speaker>
                  <p>IT is true, the Mu<U+017F>es had a <U+017F>hare in the Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions which we two have had, and they rendred them very plea<U+017F>ant: But this difference there is, you writ the Prai<U+017F>es of your Lovers, whereas my Gallants did all they could to extol mine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sapho.</speaker>
                  <p>What then? the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, that I loved as much as I was beloved.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Laura.</speaker>
                  <p>This does not <U+017F>urpri<U+017F>e me, for I know that Women com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly are more tender hearted than Men. That which does <U+017F>ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pri<U+017F>e me is, that you <U+017F>hould let your Lovers know your inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:135343:35"/>
for them, and that you <U+017F>hould in <U+017F>ome manner work upon their heart by your Poe<U+017F>ies. A Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's part is but to defend her <U+017F>elf.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sapho.</speaker>
                  <p>Betwixt you and I, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> was a little troubled at it; 'tis an inju<U+017F>tice that Men have done us: They have taken the a<U+017F><U+017F>ailing part, which is far more ea<U+017F>ie than the defen<U+017F>ive.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Laura.</speaker>
                  <p>Let us not complain, we have our advantages. We that defend our <U+017F>elves, we yield when we plea<U+017F>e; but they that attack us, they do not always overcome, though they would never <U+017F>o fain.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sapho.</speaker>
                  <p>But you do not con<U+017F>ider that if the<U+017F>e Men do attack us, they follow the inclination they have to attack us: but when we defend our <U+017F>elves, we are not very much inclined to make a defence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:135343:35"/>
                  <speaker>Laura.</speaker>
                  <p>Do you make nothing of the plea<U+017F>ure in <U+017F>eeing by <U+017F>o ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <U+017F>weet A<U+017F><U+017F>aults of <U+017F>o long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, and <U+017F>o often redoubled, how they value the Conque<U+017F>t of your heart?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sapho.</speaker>
                  <p>And do you reckon as nothing the difficulty to re<U+017F>i<U+017F>t the<U+017F>e <U+017F>weet Attacks? they <U+017F>ee with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light the <U+017F>ucce<U+017F>s of them in all their proceedings with us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Laura.</speaker>
                  <p>But in fine, though af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all their diligences, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Victors in a fair way, you do them a favour in acknowledging them to be <U+017F>o. You can no longer make a defence, and they cea<U+017F>e not to let you <U+017F>ee the value they have for you, becau<U+017F>e you make no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther defence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sapho.</speaker>
                  <p>Ah! this does not hinder, but that that which is a Victory for them, is always a kind of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat on our <U+017F>ide. In being loved,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:135343:36"/>
they have no other delight tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that of triumphing over the per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/><U+017F>on who loves them; and happy Lovers are not happy but becau<U+017F>e they are Conquerors.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Laura.</speaker>
                  <p>What? would you have had it ordered that Women <U+017F>hould attack the Men?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sapho.</speaker>
                  <p>And what nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity is there, that the one <U+017F>hould attack, and the others defend them<U+017F>elves? Let both <U+017F>ides love one another as much as the heart will allow.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Laura.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh! things would run too fa<U+017F>t; and Love is <U+017F>uch a pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty plea<U+017F>ing kind of Trade, that it was very well done to give it time to la<U+017F>t as long as it was po<U+017F><U+017F>ible. What would it be if one <U+017F>hould be entertained upon the fir<U+017F>t offers? What would become of all tho<U+017F>e cares to plea<U+017F>e, of all that re<U+017F>tle<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s, when we tax our <U+017F>elves of <U+017F>ome neglect to give <U+017F>atisfaction,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:135343:36"/>
of all that earne<U+017F>tne<U+017F>s wherewith we endeavoured for one happy moment? to conclude, all that delightful mixture of plea<U+017F>ure and pain, which is called Love? No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing would be more in<U+017F>ipid, if we did only exchange love for love.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sapho.</speaker>
                  <p>Well then, if Love mu<U+017F>t needs be, as it were, a Fight, I could rather wi<U+017F>h that Men had been obliged to <U+017F>tand upon the defen<U+017F>ive. And have not you told me too, that Women were more inclined to be tender hearted than they? Upon that <U+017F>core Women would attack them the better.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Laura.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, but they would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them<U+017F>elves too well. When 'tis de<U+017F>igned that one Sex <U+017F>hould re<U+017F>i<U+017F>t, 'tis intended the re<U+017F>i<U+017F>tance <U+017F>hould be no more than would make the Victory better plea<U+017F>ing to the Victor, but not <U+017F>trong
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:135343:37"/>
enough to gain it. It ought not to be <U+017F>o weak as to yield upon the fir<U+017F>t A<U+017F><U+017F>ault, nor <U+017F>o vigorous as not to yield at all. Here is our Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, and 'tis likely it would not be the Mens. Believe me, when we have well argued the ca<U+017F>e of Love, or of any other matter whatever, it is found in the end, that things are well as they are, and that the pretended Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion would <U+017F>poil all.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="dialogue">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:135343:37"/>
               <head>The Third Dialogue.</head>
               <stage>Socrates. Montaigne.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Montaigne.</speaker>
                  <p>IT is you then, Divine <hi>Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes!</hi> How glad am I to <U+017F>ee you! I am ju<U+017F>t now arrived in this Country, and I was no <U+017F>ooner come hither, but I looked up and down for you. In fine, after having filled up my Book with your Name, and with your Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, I can now entertain my <U+017F>elf with you, and learn how you came by that Vertue, <U+017F>o <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taigne</hi>'s Terms in French, down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, which had <U+017F>uch natural go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and which could not be fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with any example, even in that happy Age you lived in.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:135343:38"/>
                  <speaker>Socrates.</speaker>
                  <p>I am glad to <U+017F>ee a dead per<U+017F>on that <U+017F>eems to me to have been a Philo<U+017F>opher; but you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lately come from above, and I not having <U+017F>een any body here of a long time (for I am left lonely enough, and there is no great <U+017F>triving for my Conver<U+017F>ation) will you not be di<U+017F>gu<U+017F>ted if I ask you <U+017F>ome News? How goes the World? Is it not hugely chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
                  <p>Extreamly: You would not know it again.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socrat.</speaker>
                  <p>I am glad of it at my heart. I did ever <U+017F>u<U+017F>pect that it would of nece<U+017F><U+017F>ity become better and wi<U+017F>er than it was in my days.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
                  <p>What is your meaning? It is grown more fooli<U+017F>h, and more corrupted than ever. That is the change I meant, and I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to know of you the <U+017F>tory of the time you <U+017F>aw, and wherein
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:135343:38"/>
reigned <U+017F>o much goodne<U+017F>s and righteou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socrat.</speaker>
                  <p>And I, on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, did expect to hear wonders of the Age in which you have lately lived. What? Have not the Men of the<U+017F>e times corrected them<U+017F>elves of the follies of Antiquity?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
                  <p>I believe 'tis becau<U+017F>e you are ancient your <U+017F>elf, that you <U+017F>peak <U+017F>o familiarly of Antiquity; but know that there is cau<U+017F>e enough to lament its Manners, and that daily every thing grows wor<U+017F>e.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socrat.</speaker>
                  <p>Can that be? Methinks all went very cro<U+017F>s in my days. I thought that in the end they would take a more rea<U+017F>onable cour<U+017F>e, and that Men would bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them<U+017F>elves by the experience of <U+017F>o many years.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
                  <p>And do Men try Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riences? They are ju<U+017F>t like Birds,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:135343:39"/>
who let them<U+017F>elves be caught in the <U+017F>ame Net, in which an hundred thou<U+017F>and Birds had been already taken. There is not a Man that does not enter into Life all raw, and the follies of Fathers are of no advantage to Children.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socrat.</speaker>
                  <p>But why do not they make <U+017F>ome Experiences? I <U+017F>hould think that the World ought to be wi<U+017F>er, and more regular in its old days, than it had been in its youth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
                  <p>Men in all Ages have the <U+017F>elf <U+017F>ame Inclinations, over which Rea<U+017F>on has no power at all. So in all places where there are Men, there are follies, and the <U+017F>ame fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socrat.</speaker>
                  <p>And upon that <U+017F>core, how would you have had the Ages of Antiquity been better than this Age is?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:135343:39"/>
                  <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
                  <p>Ah <hi>Socrates!</hi> I knew well enough you had a <U+017F>ingular way of arguing, and drawing <U+017F>o dexterou<U+017F>ly tho<U+017F>e you had to deal with into Arguments whereof they did not fore-<U+017F>ee the Conclu<U+017F>ion, that you lead them whither you had a mind; and it was that which you called to be the Midwife of their thoughts, and bring them to Bed. I confe<U+017F>s here I am brought to Bed of a Propo<U+017F>ition quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that which I propo<U+017F>ed; for all that, I cannot yield yet. Sure it is, there are no more any of tho<U+017F>e vigorous and <U+017F>turdy Souls of Antiquity, no <hi>Ari<U+017F>tides,</hi> no <hi>Phocions,</hi> no <hi>Pericles,</hi> nor, in <U+017F>hort, no <hi>Socrates.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socrat.</speaker>
                  <p>Where does it <U+017F>tick? Is it that Nature has exhau<U+017F>ted her <U+017F>elf, and has no farther <U+017F>trength to produce tho<U+017F>e great Souls? And why <U+017F>hould <U+017F>he have wa<U+017F>ted her
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:135343:40"/>
<U+017F>elf in nothing but in rational Men? None of her Works did degenerate yet; why <U+017F>hould men only degenerate?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
                  <p>That is a point indeed; they do degenerate. Nature <U+017F>eems to have <U+017F>hewed us heretofore <U+017F>ome patterns of great men, thereby to per<U+017F>uade us, that <U+017F>he could have made <U+017F>ome if <U+017F>he had had a mind to it, and that afterwards <U+017F>he had made all the re<U+017F>t with neglect enough.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socrat.</speaker>
                  <p>One thing mind. Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is an object of a particular kind, a far off, does add to it. Had you known <hi>Aristides, Phocion, Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> and my <U+017F>elf, <U+017F>ince you will put me in that number, you would have found in your Age <U+017F>ome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ons that were like us. That which does u<U+017F>ually cau<U+017F>e this prevention in people for Antiquity, is, becau<U+017F>e they are out of humour with their
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:135343:40"/>
Age, and Antiquity takes advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage thereof. Men exalt the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients, to pull down their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporaries. When we lived, we e<U+017F>teemed our Ance<U+017F>tors more than they de<U+017F>erved; and now, our Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>terity e<U+017F>teem us more than is our de<U+017F>ert: but our Ance<U+017F>tors, and we, and our Po<U+017F>terity, all this is equal enough; and I believe the Spectacle of the World would be very tedious to him that <U+017F>hould look upon it with an eye of Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, for 'tis always the <U+017F>ame.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
                  <p>I <U+017F>hould have believed that every thing was in motion, that all did change, and that the different Ages had their different Characters, as men had. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, Are not <U+017F>ome Ages learned, and are not others ignorant? Are not <U+017F>ome plain and downright, and others again <U+017F>ubtil and crafty? Some are <U+017F>erious, and <U+017F>ome are
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:135343:41"/>
toyi<U+017F>h: <U+017F>ome again are fine and quaint, and others are gro<U+017F>s and dull.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socrat.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis true.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
                  <p>Why <U+017F>hall there not be then <U+017F>ome Ages more vertuous, and others more wicked?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socrat.</speaker>
                  <p>That is no con<U+017F>equence. Cloaths change; but by that it is not meant that the Bodies change their form too: The neatne<U+017F>s or the gro<U+017F><U+017F>ne<U+017F>s, the knowledge or the ignorance, the more or le<U+017F>s of a certain kind of downrightne<U+017F>s, the <U+017F>erious or the toyi<U+017F>h Genius; the<U+017F>e make but the out-<U+017F>ide of Man, and all this does change; but the heart does not change, and whole Man con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ts in the heart. People are ignorant in one Age, but the mode to be learned may come: People are intere<U+017F>ted, but the mode to be di<U+017F>-intere<U+017F>ted will never come. Of the prodigious
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:135343:41"/>
number of Men unrea<U+017F>onable enough that are born in an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years, Nature, may be, has two or three dozen of them that are rea<U+017F>onable, which <U+017F>he mu<U+017F>t di<U+017F>per<U+017F>e over the whole Earth; and you judge well enough, that there are never in no place <U+017F>o many as may make a mode there of Vertue and of Righteou<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
                  <p>Is this di<U+017F>tribution of ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional men equally made? There might have been <U+017F>ome Ages that might have had a better <U+017F>hare than others.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socrat.</speaker>
                  <p>Nature does ever act very regularly, but we do not judge as <U+017F>he acts.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="dialogue">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:135343:42"/>
               <head>The Fourth Dialogue.</head>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Adrian</hi> the Emperor. <hi>Margaret</hi> of  <hi>Au<U+017F>tria.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>M.</hi> of <hi>Au<U+017F>tria.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>WHat ail's you? I <U+017F>ee you are all in an heat.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adrian.</speaker>
                  <p>I have ju<U+017F>t now had a <U+017F>trong Conte<U+017F>t with <hi>Cato</hi> of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>tica,</hi> about the manner how we both died. I pretended that in this la<U+017F>t action I had <U+017F>hewed my <U+017F>elf more a Philo<U+017F>opher than he had.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>M.</hi> of <hi>Au<U+017F>tria.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>I think you ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bold, that you dare que<U+017F>tion <U+017F>o famous a death as his. Was there any thing more glorious, than to take care that all was well <U+017F>etled in <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>tica,</hi> <U+017F>ecure his Friends, and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:135343:42"/>
kill him<U+017F>elf, that he might end with the Liberty of his Country, and avoid falling into the hands of a Vanqui<U+017F>her, who would, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever have <U+017F>pared him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adrian.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh! if you did nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly examine that death, you would find there were <U+017F>everal things to que<U+017F>tion in it. In the fir<U+017F>t place, he had been <U+017F>o long in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring him<U+017F>elf for it, and he did prepare him<U+017F>elf with <U+017F>uch vi<U+017F>ible <U+017F>trifes, that no body in <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V"><U+01B2></g>tica</hi> made any que<U+017F>tion, but that <hi>Cato</hi> would kill him<U+017F>elf. Secondly, Before he gave him<U+017F>elf the blow, he was fain to read often the Dialogue where <hi>Plato</hi> treats of the Immortality of the Soul. Thirdly, The de<U+017F>ign he had laid put him <U+017F>o out of humour, that, going to Bed, and not find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Sword under his Beds-head, (for, as people rightly gue<U+017F><U+017F>ed what he had a mind to do they had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:135343:43"/>
it away) he called one of his Slaves to ask him for it, and gave him <U+017F>o great a blow with his fi<U+017F>t upon the face, that with it he <U+017F>truck out his teeth: this is <U+017F>o true, that he drew back his hand all bloody.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>M.</hi> of <hi>Au<U+017F>tria.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>I confe<U+017F>s, this blow with the fi<U+017F>t does very much <U+017F>poil this Philo<U+017F>ophical death.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adrian.</speaker>
                  <p>You cannot believe what a <U+017F>tir he made about this Sword taken away, and how he railed at his Son and at his Servants; <U+017F>aying, that they had a mind to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver him up to <hi>Cae<U+017F>ar,</hi> hands and feet tied together. In fine, he <U+017F>col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them all in <U+017F>uch a manner, that they were fain to go out of his Chamber, and let him kill him<U+017F>elf.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>M.</hi> of <hi>Au<U+017F>tria.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Indeed, indeed, things might have gone on a little more mildly. He needed but have peaceably <U+017F>tayed till the next day to give him<U+017F>elf his death. Nothing
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:135343:43"/>
is more ea<U+017F>ie than to die when one is bent upon it. But in all likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, the mea<U+017F>ures he had taken upon the account of his con<U+017F>tancy, were <U+017F>o exact, that he could <U+017F>tay no longer; and he had not, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, killed him<U+017F>elf, had he delay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a day longer.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adrian.</speaker>
                  <p>You <U+017F>ay right; and I <U+017F>ee that you have skill in generous deaths.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>M.</hi> of <hi>Au<U+017F>tria.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Yet <U+017F>ome <U+017F>ay, that after they had carried this Sword to <hi>Cato,</hi> and had withdrawn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>elves, he fell a<U+017F>leep, and <U+017F>nored. That would be brave enough.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adrian.</speaker>
                  <p>And do you believe this? He had but done <U+017F>colding every body, and beating his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants: a man does not <U+017F>o ea<U+017F>ily fall a<U+017F>leep after <U+017F>uch an exerci<U+017F>e. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, his hand he had <U+017F>truck his Slave with did pain him too much to let him fall a<U+017F>leep, for he was
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:135343:44"/>
not able to bear the pain he felt: and he made it be bound up by a Phy<U+017F>ician, though he was ju<U+017F>t go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to kill him<U+017F>elf. In <U+017F>hort, from the time his Sword was brought, till Mid-night, he read <hi>Plato</hi>'s Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues twice over. Then I could prove ea<U+017F>ily by a great Supper he made for all his friends, by a walk he took afterwards, and by all pa<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ages that happened till he was left alone in his Chamber, that it mu<U+017F>t be very late when that Sword was brought him: Moreover, the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue he read twice over is very long; and by con<U+017F>equence, if he <U+017F>lept, he <U+017F>lept but a little while. Truly, I am much afraid he did but make as if he <U+017F>nored, that he might have the honour of it from tho<U+017F>e that hearkned at his Chamber door.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>M.</hi> of <hi>Au<U+017F>tria.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>You do not play the Critick ami<U+017F>s upon his death;
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:135343:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
which, however, does carry in the bottom <U+017F>omething that is very he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roical. But which way can you pretend that yours has the better of it? For as much as I can remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, you died in your Bed, in a plain and unremarkable manner.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adrian.</speaker>
                  <p>What? Are not tho<U+017F>e Ver<U+017F>es remarkable at all, which I made as I was ju<U+017F>t giving up the Gho<U+017F>t?
<q>
                        <l>My little Soul, my dear Darling, Thou;</l>
                        <l>Going thou art, Girl; and whither, God does know.</l>
                        <l>Alone thou goe<U+017F>t, naked, and all over quaking. Alas!</l>
                        <l>What'll become of thy pretty fooling humour, La<U+017F>s?</l>
                        <l>What'll become of <U+017F>o many plea<U+017F>ant frolicks, I can't gue<U+017F>s.</l>
                     </q>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:135343:45"/>
                     <hi>Cato</hi> treated Death like a bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s that was too <U+017F>erious, but you <U+017F>ee, I drolled with it: and herein it is that I pretend that my Philo<U+017F>ophy went far beyond <hi>Cato</hi>'s. It is not <U+017F>o difficult haughtily to out-brave Death, as it is to joak her in a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<U+017F>s manner; nor is it <U+017F>o hard a thing to receive her kindly when we call her to our aid, as when <U+017F>he comes when we have no need of her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>M.</hi> of <hi>Au<U+017F>tria.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Yes, I grant, <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi>'s death is not <U+017F>o brave as yours; but, as ill luck would have it, I had not ob<U+017F>erved that you had made the<U+017F>e <U+017F>mall Ver<U+017F>es, in which the bravery of yours does con<U+017F>i<U+017F>t.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adrian.</speaker>
                  <p>This is the way of all the world. <hi>Cato</hi> may tear out his Bowels, rather than fall into the hands of his Enemy: it is, perhaps, no <U+017F>uch great matter, if it be throughly examined; yet <U+017F>uch a
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:135343:45"/>
feat as that makes a va<U+017F>t <U+017F>hew in Hi<U+017F>tory, and there's not one but is taken with it. Another may die fair and quietly, and be in a capacity to make drolling Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>es upon his death, 'tis more than <hi>Cato</hi> has done; but this has no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it that is taking. and Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tory does <U+017F>carce take notice of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>M.</hi> of <hi>Au<U+017F>tria.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Alas! nothing is truer than what you <U+017F>ay; And I my <U+017F>elf that now <U+017F>peak to you, I have a death that I pretend is far before yours, and yet 'tis le<U+017F>s taken notice of. 'Tis not, however, a downright death; but <U+017F>uch as 'tis, it exceeds yours, that does exceed <hi>Cato</hi>'s.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adrian.</speaker>
                  <p>How? what do you mean?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>M.</hi> of <hi>Au<U+017F>tria.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>I was an Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror's Daughter. I was contracted to a King's Son; and this Prince, after his father's death, <U+017F>ent me
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:135343:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
back to mine, notwith<U+017F>tanding the <U+017F>olemn promi<U+017F>e he had mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to marry me. After this, the contracted me to the Son of ano<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther King; and as I was going b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Sea to this Husband, my Ship w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> beaten with a terrible Tempe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> which ca<U+017F>t my life into evide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> danger. Then it was that I mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> my <U+017F>elf this Epitaph:</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Megg,</hi> that pretty Dam<U+017F>el does h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> lie;</l>
                     <l>Has two Husbands, and yet a M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> does die.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>The truth is, I did not die <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc><…></desc>
                     </gap>, but 'twas not my fault. Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceive well this kind of death, yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> be <U+017F>atisfied with it. <hi>Cato</hi>'s Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/><U+017F>tancy is injured in one kind, yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in another, mine is natural. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> too high, you are too drolling am rea<U+017F>onable.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:135343:46"/>
                  <speaker>Adrian.</speaker>
                  <p>What? You tax me of having had too little fear of death.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>M.</hi> of <hi>Au<U+017F>tria.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>I do. It is not likely that a man <U+017F>hould be in no di<U+017F>order at his dying hour; and I am confident you did force your <U+017F>elf then to droll, as much as <hi>Cato</hi> did to tear out his Entrails. I am every moment in expectation of Shipwrack without frightning my my <U+017F>elf, and I mak my Epitaph in cold blood; this is very extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, and if there were nothing to moderate this Hi<U+017F>tory, there would be <U+017F>ome rea<U+017F>on not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, or to believe that I did act only by way of <hi>Rhodomantado.</hi> But in the mean while, I am a poor Girl, twice contracted, and yet have been <U+017F>o unlucky, as to die a Maid: I <U+017F>hew my Concern for it, and that gives my Hi<U+017F>tory all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui<U+017F>ite appearance of truth. Your Ver<U+017F>es, mind them well, carry no
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:135343:47"/>
meaning with them; there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a <hi>Gibbri<U+017F>h,</hi> made up of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> few Childi<U+017F>h Terms; but min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> have a very clear Sen<U+017F>e, and giv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> content at the very fir<U+017F>t: which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a <U+017F>ign that Nature <U+017F>peaks in them much more than in yours.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adrian.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly, I <U+017F>hould neve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> have believed, that the trouble to die a Virgin ought to have been <U+017F>o much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o your Glory.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>M.</hi> of <hi>Au<U+017F>tria.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Make your <U+017F>el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> as plea<U+017F>ant with this as you plea<U+017F>e but my death, if it may be terme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> <U+017F>o, has another e<U+017F>pecial advantag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> over <hi>Cato</hi>'s, and over yours. Yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> had both of you played the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ophers <U+017F>o much whil<U+017F>t you lived that you had engaged your <U+017F>elve upon Honour, not to be afraid o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> death: and if you had had the li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>berty to fear it, I cannot tell wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> would have come on it. But I, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> long as the <U+017F>torm la<U+017F>ted, I had a
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:135343:47"/>
Right to tremble, and make my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ries reach Heaven, without any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ody's taking exception at it, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aving a le<U+017F>s e<U+017F>teem for me. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erthele<U+017F>s, I remained quiet enough <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o make my Epitaph.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adrian.</speaker>
                  <p>Betwixt you and I, Was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot the Epitaph made on Shore?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>M.</hi> of <hi>A<U+017F>tria.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Ah! this wrangling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>us is ill-becoming: I did not <U+017F>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y you, about your Ver<U+017F>es.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adrian.</speaker>
                  <p>I yield then, in good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arne<U+017F>t; and I grant, that when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ertue does not go beyond the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ounds of Nature, <U+017F>he is very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reat.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="dialogue">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:135343:48"/>
               <head>The Fifth Dialogue.</head>
               <stage>Era<U+017F>i<U+017F>trates. Herveus.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Era<U+017F>i<U+017F>trates.</speaker>
                  <p>YOU tell me wonders. What the Blood circulates in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Body? the Veins carry it from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Extremities of the Heart, and go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> from the Heart into the Arterie which convey it back again to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wards the Extremities?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Herveus.</speaker>
                  <p>I have <U+017F>hewed <U+017F>o m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny Experiences of this, that n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>body makes any further que<U+017F>tio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ara<U+017F>i<U+017F>t.</speaker>
                  <p>We deceived our <U+017F>elve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> very much then, we Phy<U+017F>icians o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Antiquity, who took the Blood t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> have but one <U+017F>low motion fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Heart, towards the Extrem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:135343:48"/>
of the Body; and people are highly obliged to you, for having <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>boli<U+017F>hed this ancient Error.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Herv.</speaker>
                  <p>So I pretend. And people <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ught too to be <U+017F>o much the more obliged to me, in that I was the fir<U+017F>t that <U+017F>et them in the way to make all tho<U+017F>e fine Di<U+017F>coveries, as are now made in Anatomy. Since I once found out the Circulation of the Blood, 'tis now, who <U+017F>hall find a new Conduit out, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey the Blood into all parts of the Body; a new Re<U+017F>ervatory? It <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ooks as though whole Man were melted down again. Behold the advantages our Modern Phy<U+017F>ick ought to have above yours. You made it your bu<U+017F>ine<U+017F>s to cure the Body of Man, and his Body was altogether unknown to you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Era<U+017F>i<U+017F>t.</speaker>
                  <p>I own that your modern Phy<U+017F>itians are better Naturali<U+017F>ts than we; they under<U+017F>tand Nature
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:135343:49"/>
better, but they are not better Phy<U+017F>itians; we cured the Sick as well as they cure them. I could wi<U+017F>h all the<U+017F>e modern ones, and you the very fir<U+017F>t of all, had had Prince <hi>Antiochus</hi> in hand to cure of his Quartern Ague. You know how I went about it, and how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> di<U+017F>covered by the more than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary beating of his Pul<U+017F>e in the pre<U+017F>ence of <hi>Stratonice,</hi> that he was enamoured with that beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Queen, and that his whole Di<U+017F>ea<U+017F>e did proceed from his vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <U+017F>triving to hide his Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> And yet I made <U+017F>o difficult and <U+017F>o con<U+017F>iderable a Cure as that was without knowing that the blood did circulate; and I am of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that notwith<U+017F>tanding the help you might have received from this knowledge, you would have been very much puzled had you been in my place. The Point then in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitation
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:135343:49"/>
was not about new Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duits, nor new Re<U+017F>ervatories, what was mo<U+017F>t con<U+017F>iderable to be known in the Patient, was the heart.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Herv.</speaker>
                  <p>The heart is not always the Point in que<U+017F>tion, and all <U+017F>ick people are not in love with their Mother-in-law, as <hi>Antiochus</hi> was. I make no doubt but for want of knowing that the blood does cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate, you have let a great many people die under your hands.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Era<U+017F>.</speaker>
                  <p>What? you take your new di<U+017F>coveries to be very u<U+017F>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Herv.</speaker>
                  <p>Sure enough.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Era<U+017F>.</speaker>
                  <p>An<U+017F>wer then, if you plea<U+017F>e a little que<U+017F>tion, which I <U+017F>hall put to you: What's the rea<U+017F>on we daily <U+017F>ee as many Dead come hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as ever did come?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:135343:50"/>
                  <speaker>Herv.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh! if they die, 'tis their own fault; the Phy<U+017F>icians are now no more in fault.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Era<U+017F>.</speaker>
                  <p>But this circulation of the blood, the<U+017F>e Conduits, the<U+017F>e Pipes of Conveyance, the<U+017F>e Re<U+017F>ervato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; all the<U+017F>e then are of no u<U+017F>e to cure?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Herv.</speaker>
                  <p>Perhaps men have not had plea<U+017F>ure as yet, to make any u<U+017F>e of all they have learnt of late but 'tis impo<U+017F><U+017F>ible but in time they'l fee great effects thereof.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Era<U+017F>.</speaker>
                  <p>Upon my word no hin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> will change. See you? There is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> certain mea<U+017F>ure of u<U+017F>eful know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledges, which came early to men whereunto they have made lit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tle addition, and they will no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> go far beyond it, if at all. The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> are thus much obliged to Nature that <U+017F>he did very <U+017F>peedily in<U+017F>pir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> them with what knowledge they <U+017F>tood in need of; for they ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:135343:50"/>
been undone, if <U+017F>he had left it to the <U+017F>lowne<U+017F>s of their rea<U+017F>on to find out. As for other things which are not <U+017F>o nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary, they are di<U+017F>covered by little and little, and in a long run of years.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Herv.</speaker>
                  <p>It would be <U+017F>trange that having a better knowledge of man; man cannot cure him bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: At that rate, why <U+017F>hould one go about to perfectionate the knowledge of the body of man? It would be better to let all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Era<U+017F>.</speaker>
                  <p>There would be a lo<U+017F>s of very plea<U+017F>ant knowledges; but as for the utility, I think that to di<U+017F>cover a new Conduit in man's body, or a new Star in the Sky, would come to one and the <U+017F>ame thing. Nature will have men at <U+017F>ome certain times <U+017F>ucceed one another by the means of death; they have the liberty to defend
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:135343:51"/>
<U+017F>elves again<U+017F>t her till <U+017F>uch an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in<U+017F>tant; but pa<U+017F>t that, it will be to no purpo<U+017F>e to make new di<U+017F>coveries in Anatomy, in vain will it be to penetrate fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and further into the Secrets of the frame of man's Body; Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will not be baffled, People will die after the u<U+017F>ual manner.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="dialogue">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:135343:51"/>
               <head>The Sixth Dialogue.</head>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Berenice, Co<U+017F>mus Medicis</hi> the Second.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Co<U+017F>mus</hi> of <hi>Medicis.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>SOme learned Per<U+017F>ons lately decea<U+017F>ed have ju<U+017F>t now told me <U+017F>ome News that troubles me very much. You mu<U+017F>t under<U+017F>tand that <hi>Galileus,</hi> who was my Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matician, had made a di<U+017F>covery of certain Planets that turn round about <hi>Jupiter,</hi> which, in honour of me, he called the Stars of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicis.</hi> But I am told that they are <U+017F>carce known now by that Name, and that they are but plainly call'd <hi>Jupiter</hi>'s <hi>Satellits.</hi> The World
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:135343:52"/>
mu<U+017F>t needs be very wicked now, and very envious of anothers glory.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Berenice,</speaker>
                  <p>No doubt of it, I <U+017F>el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom knew more remarkable ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of its malignity.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. Medicis,</speaker>
                  <p>You <U+017F>peak of it with little concern, after the good luck you have had. You had made a Vow that you would cut off your hair if your Hu<U+017F>band <hi>Ptolom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> came back victorious from I can not tell—what War. He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned having defeated his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; you Con<U+017F>ecrated your hai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in the Temple of <hi>Venus,</hi> and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> next day a Mathematician made i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> di<U+017F>appear, and publickly decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that they had been change<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> into a <hi>Con<U+017F>tellation,</hi> which h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> called <hi>Berenices</hi> Locks. To mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Stars pa<U+017F>s for a Womans hair, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> was far wor<U+017F>e than to give Prince his Name to new Planet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:135343:52"/>
however your hair has had <U+017F>uc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F>s, and tho<U+017F>e poor Stars call'd <hi>Medicis,</hi> could not have the like Fortune.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Berenice,</speaker>
                  <p>If I could give you my Cele<U+017F>tial hair, I would give it to comfort you; and I <U+017F>hould withal be <U+017F>o generous as not to pretend that you <U+017F>hould be much obliged to me for that pre<U+017F>ent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. Medicis,</speaker>
                  <p>It would be con<U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable though, and I wi<U+017F>h my Name were as <U+017F>ure to live as yours is.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Berenice,</speaker>
                  <p>Alas! in ca<U+017F>e all the Con<U+017F>tellations <U+017F>hould bear my Name, <U+017F>hould I be the better for it? It would be above in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and I my <U+017F>elf, I <U+017F>hould be <U+017F>till here below. Men are plea<U+017F>ant, they cannot <U+017F>teal away from Death them<U+017F>elves, and they <U+017F>trive to rob her of two or three Syllables that belongs to them. This is a pretty
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:135343:53"/>
Cheat they think to put upon her. Were it not better they would in an hand<U+017F>om way con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ent to die, they and their Names too?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. Med.</speaker>
                  <p>I am not of your mind: People die, but as little as is po<U+017F><U+017F>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and as dead as they are, they endeavour to fa<U+017F>ten upon life <U+017F>till, either in a piece of Marble which repre<U+017F>ents them, by <U+017F>tones rai<U+017F>ed up the one upon the other; ay, by ones one Tomb. A man drowns him<U+017F>elf, and hangs on all the<U+017F>e Hooks.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Berenice,</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, but tho<U+017F>e things which <U+017F>hould pre<U+017F>erve our Names from death, die them<U+017F>elves after their way. To what will you fix your immortality? A Town, an Empire it <U+017F>elf, can hardly be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>pon<U+017F>ible to you for it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:135343:53"/>
                  <speaker>C. Medicis,</speaker>
                  <p>The invention of giving ones Name to Stars, is not bad; they la<U+017F>t forever.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Berenice,</speaker>
                  <p>Yet after the manner as I hear people talk, the Stars too are liable to fail: They <U+017F>ay new ones come, and ancient ones go away; and you will <U+017F>ee that at length I <U+017F>hall not have one <U+017F>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle hair perhaps remaining in the Sky. At lea<U+017F>t that which cannot be wanting to our Names, is as I may <U+017F>ay, a Grammatical death; <U+017F>ome changes in the Letters does put them in a condition to be of no farther u<U+017F>e than to intangle the Learned. It is not long <U+017F>ince I <U+017F>aw here below two dead per<U+017F>ons, who had a very hot Conte<U+017F>t with one another. I drew near, I asked who they were; and I was told that the one was the great <hi>Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> and the other a <hi>Barbarian</hi> Emperour. Their Di<U+017F>pute was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:135343:54"/>
the preference of their pa<U+017F>t Greatne<U+017F>s. <hi>Con<U+017F>tantine</hi> <U+017F>aid, he had been Emperour of <hi>Con<U+017F>tantinople;</hi> and the <hi>Barbarian</hi> that he had been <U+017F>o of <hi>Stambole.</hi> The fir<U+017F>t <U+017F>aid, to <U+017F>et out his <hi>Con<U+017F>tantinople,</hi> that it was <U+017F>eated upon three Seas, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Euxin,</hi> upon the <hi>Bo<U+017F>pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> of <hi>Thracia,</hi> and upon the <hi>Propontides.</hi> The other replyed, that <hi>Stambole</hi> did al<U+017F>o command three Seas, The <hi>black Sea,</hi> the <hi><U+017F>treight,</hi> and the <hi>Sea Marmara.</hi> This relation of <hi>Con<U+017F>tantinople</hi> and <hi>Stambole</hi> did put <hi>Con<U+017F>tantine</hi> into a maze; but after he had exactly informed him<U+017F>elf of the <U+017F>ituation of <hi>Stambole,</hi> he was yet more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed, to find that it was <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tantinople,</hi> which he could not know again, becau<U+017F>e of the change of Names. <hi>Alas!</hi> <U+017F>aid he aloud, <hi>I <U+017F>hould have done as well to have left</hi> Con<U+017F>tantinople <hi>her fir<U+017F>t Name</hi>
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:135343:54"/>
                     <hi>of</hi> Bizantium. <hi>Who'l find out the Name of</hi> Con<U+017F>tantine <hi>in</hi> Stam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bole? <hi>He will indeed find there what he looks for.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C. Medicis,</speaker>
                  <p>In earne<U+017F>t, you comfort me a little, and I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>olved to have patience. When all is done, <U+017F>ince we could not choo<U+017F>e but die, it is pretty rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>onable that our Names <U+017F>hould die too; they are of no better quality then we.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:135343:55"/>
            <head>DIALOGUES OF SOME <hi>Modern Dead.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="dialogue">
               <head>The Fir<U+017F>t Dialogue.</head>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Britany. Mary</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Britany.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>FOR certain, my death did you a great kindne<U+017F>s: you, immediately upon it, cro<U+017F><U+017F>ed the Sea to go and marry <hi>Lewis</hi> XII. and <U+017F>eize upon the Throne which I left empty for you. But you enjoyed it but a while, and I was revenged of you by means of your
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:135343:55"/>
youth and beauty, which rendred you too too lovely in the King's eye; and, with overmuch facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, did comfort him in his lo<U+017F>s of me; for they ha<U+017F>tned his death, and hindred you from being Queen long.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>England,</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Truly, Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty did but ju<U+017F>t <U+017F>hew it <U+017F>elf to me, and pre<U+017F>ently di<U+017F>appeared.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Brit.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>And after this, you became Dutche<U+017F>s of <hi>Suffolk.</hi> A fair fall. For my part, Heaven be thanked, I have had another de<U+017F>tiny. When <hi>Charles</hi> VIII. died, I did not lo<U+017F>e my place by his death, and I married his Succe<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>or; which is an example of a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <U+017F>ingular happine<U+017F>s.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Engl.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Would you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve me, if I did tell you, that I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bore you any grudge for that happine<U+017F>s.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:135343:56"/>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Brit.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>No. I apprehend too well what it is to be Dutche<U+017F>s of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> having fir<U+017F>t been Queen of <hi>France.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Engl.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>But I loved the Duke of <hi>Suffolk.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Brit.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>That's nothing After one has once ta<U+017F>ted the <U+017F>weetne<U+017F>s of Royalty, is it po<U+017F><U+017F>ible to reli<U+017F>h any other?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Engl.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>It is, provided they be of love. I do a<U+017F><U+017F>ure you that you ought not to wi<U+017F>h me il<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for having <U+017F>ucceeded you. If, al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> along, I could have di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ed o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> my <U+017F>elf, I <U+017F>hould have been but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Dutche<U+017F>s; and I made a <U+017F>peed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> return into <hi>England,</hi> to take upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> me that Title, <U+017F>o <U+017F>oon as ever I wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> di<U+017F>charged of that of Queen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Brit.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Were you <U+017F>o lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> minded?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Engl.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Ambition, I mu<U+017F><gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> confe<U+017F>s, was of no concern to me
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:135343:56"/>
Nature has made <U+017F>ome plain plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ures for men, <U+017F>uch as are ea<U+017F>ie and quiet, and their imagination makes them <U+017F>ome that are intricate, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, and hard to come by: but Nature is more dexterous in creating them plea<U+017F>ures, than they are them<U+017F>elves. Why do not they commit that charge to her? She invented Love, which is very plea<U+017F>ing; and they have invented Ambition, which was needle<U+017F>s.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Brit.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Who tells you that men did invent Ambition? Nature is no le<U+017F>s bu<U+017F>ie in in<U+017F>piring de<U+017F>ires of elevation and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, than <U+017F>he is in working an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination in men to love.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Engl.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Ambition may be ea<U+017F>ily known to be a work of the imagination; <U+017F>he is the very form of it: <U+017F>he is re<U+017F>tle<U+017F>s, full of chymerical projects; <U+017F>he has no <U+017F>ooner attained her de<U+017F>ires, but <U+017F>he
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:135343:57"/>
out-goes them again. She aims <U+017F>till at a mark <U+017F>he never hits.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anne of Brit.</speaker>
                  <p>And unluckily, Love has a mark which he hits but too <U+017F>oon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mary of Engl.</speaker>
                  <p>That which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ues hereupon is, that one may of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes be happy through Love, and one can be <U+017F>o but once through Ambition; or, if it be po<U+017F><U+017F>ible to be <U+017F><gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, at lea<U+017F>t, tho<U+017F>e kind of plea<U+017F>ures are made for no great number of per<U+017F>ons; and con<U+017F>equently, Nature does not propo<U+017F>e them to Men, for her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours are always very general. Con<U+017F>ider Love; 'tis made for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one. None but <U+017F>uch as do <U+017F>eek out their happine<U+017F>s in a <U+017F>tate too elevated, do think that Nature has grudged them the <U+017F>weet delights of Love. A King who can make him<U+017F>elf <U+017F>ure of an hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>and Arms, cannot, perhaps, make
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:135343:57"/>
him<U+017F>elf <U+017F>ure of one heart. He knows not whether that which a man does for another per<U+017F>on, be not done out of a point of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. His Royalty deprives him of the <U+017F>incere<U+017F>t and the <U+017F>weete<U+017F>t plea<U+017F>ures.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Brit.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>You do not ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Kings much the more unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py by this inconvenience you find out in their condition. When a man <U+017F>ees his Will not only fulfilled, but prevented an infinite number of Fortunes depending upon a word, which he may utter when he plea<U+017F>es; <U+017F>o many cares, <U+017F>uch a multitude of de<U+017F>igns, <U+017F>o much ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerne<U+017F>s, <U+017F>uch an application to plea<U+017F>e, whereof he is the only ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; truly it is a comfort to a man, not to know exactly, whether he be loved for his degrees <U+017F>ake, or for his per<U+017F>on's <U+017F>ake. The plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ures of Ambition, <U+017F>ay you, are
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:135343:58"/>
de<U+017F>igned for too few: what you charge them with, as a fault, is their greate<U+017F>t charm. In point of good luck Exception flatters; and <U+017F>uch as reign are excepted with <U+017F>o much advantage from the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of other men, that though they <U+017F>hould lo<U+017F>e <U+017F>omething of the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ures which are common to all the world, they would <U+017F>till have more than they would de<U+017F>ire.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Engl.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Ah! judge of their lo<U+017F>s by the <U+017F>en<U+017F>ibility where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they receive tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>incere and common plea<U+017F>ures, when any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ent them<U+017F>elves. Hear what a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<U+017F>s of my own Blood told me here, the other day, who has reigned in <hi>England,</hi> both very long, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry happily, and without an Hu<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band too. She gave her fir<U+017F>t Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to <U+017F>ome <hi>Dutch</hi> Amba<U+017F><U+017F>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, who had in their Retinue an hand<U+017F>ome young man. So <U+017F>oon as he
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:135343:58"/>
<U+017F>aw the Queen, he turned him<U+017F>elf towards <U+017F>ome that were near him, and <U+017F>poke <U+017F>omething to them <U+017F>oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but with a Countenance that made her gue<U+017F>s pretty well what he <U+017F>aid; for Women are endued with an admirable in<U+017F>tinct. Tho<U+017F>e three or four words of this young <hi>Dutch-</hi>man, whieh <U+017F>he had not heard, remained more in her mind, than the whole <U+017F>peech of the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<U+017F><U+017F>adors: and, as <U+017F>oon as they were gone, <U+017F>he would needs <U+017F>ati<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie her <U+017F>elf in what <U+017F>he had imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed. She asked tho<U+017F>e to whom this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oung man had <U+017F>poken, what he had <U+017F>aid to them? They made her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<U+017F>wer, with great re<U+017F>pect, that it was what they did not dare to tell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gain to <U+017F>o great a Queen; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orbore telling it a long time. In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ine, when <U+017F>he made u<U+017F>e of her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b<U+017F>olute Authority, <U+017F>he was told, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat the <hi>Dutch-</hi>man had <U+017F>aid in a
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:135343:59"/>
low voice: <hi>Ah! this is an hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ome Woman;</hi> and had added <U+017F>ome gro<U+017F><U+017F>er expre<U+017F><U+017F>ion, but brisk, to <U+017F>hew that he liked her. They made the relation hereof with great apprehen<U+017F>ion; however, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing happened upon it, <U+017F>aving only, that when <U+017F>he di<U+017F>mi<U+017F><U+017F>ed the Amba<U+017F><U+017F>adors, <U+017F>he made a con<U+017F>ide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Pre<U+017F>ent to the young <hi>Dutch-man.</hi> See how, among all the<U+017F>e plea<U+017F>ures of Greatne<U+017F>s and Royal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, this of being thought hand<U+017F>om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> did touch her to the quick.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Brit.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>But, in fine, <U+017F>he would not have purcha<U+017F>ed it with the lo<U+017F>s of the other. Any thing that is too downright, is not fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Man's turn. It is not <U+017F>ufficient th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> plea<U+017F>ures do take with <U+017F>weetne<U+017F>s<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> they mu<U+017F>t agitate and tran<U+017F>port <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> man. How comes it to pa<U+017F>s, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Pa<U+017F>toral life, <U+017F>uch as the Poet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> de<U+017F>cribe it, had never any Being
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:135343:59"/>
but in their works, and would not be liked of, if put in practice? It is too <U+017F>weet, and too too plain.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Engl.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>I confe<U+017F>s, men have <U+017F>poiled all. But how hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens it, that the <U+017F>ight of the mo<U+017F>t Maje<U+017F>tical and mo<U+017F>t pompous Court in the World has not the power to allure them, <U+017F>o much as the <hi>Ideas</hi> do which <U+017F>ometimes they propo<U+017F>e to them<U+017F>elves of this <U+017F>ame Pa<U+017F>toral Life? meerly becau<U+017F>e they were made for it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Brit.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>In like manner, the <U+017F>haring in your plain and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<U+017F>turbed plea<U+017F>ures, is but to enter into tho<U+017F>e <hi>Chymera</hi>'s which men frame to them<U+017F>elves.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Engl.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Not at all. If it be true that there are but few per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ons that can make <U+017F>uch a di<U+017F>tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction as to begin with tho<U+017F>e kind of plea<U+017F>ures, people are willing, at lea<U+017F>t, to end with them when they
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:135343:60"/>
can. The Imagination has run over all fal<U+017F>e objects, and <U+017F>he comes back to the true ones.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="dialogue">
               <head>The Second Dialogue.</head>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Charles</hi> V. <hi>Era<U+017F>mus.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Era<U+017F>mus.</speaker>
                  <p>MAke no que<U+017F>tion of it: i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> there was any <U+017F>uch thing a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> place among the Dead, I would not yield you the precedency.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Charles</hi> V.</speaker>
                  <p>What? A Grammari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, one of Learning; and what is yet more, a man of Wit, would pretend to be better than a Prince that has been Ma<U+017F>ter of the better part of <hi>Europe?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:135343:60"/>
                  <speaker>Era<U+017F>mus.</speaker>
                  <p>Put <hi>America</hi> to it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>o, and I <U+017F>hall not fear you a jot the more. All this greatne<U+017F>s was, as one may <U+017F>ay, but a compo<U+017F>ition of many hazards; and if one <U+017F>hould di<U+017F>-unite all the parts that make it up, you would <U+017F>ee plainly that it was <U+017F>o. If <hi>Ferdinando,</hi> your Grandfather, had been a man of his word, little would have remained to you in <hi>Italy.</hi> If any other Princes but he had the wit to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that there were <hi>Antipodes, Chri<U+017F>topher Columbus</hi> would not have applied him<U+017F>elf to him, and <hi>America</hi> had not been in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of your States. If, after the death of the la<U+017F>t Duke of <hi>Burgun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, Lewis</hi> XI. had minded what he did, <hi>Maximilian</hi> had not had the Heire<U+017F>s of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> nor you had not had the <hi>Low-Countries.</hi> If <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Ca<U+017F>tyle,</hi> Brother to your Grandmother <hi>I<U+017F>abella,</hi> had not had
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:135343:61"/>
an ill Reputation among Women, or if his Wifes Hone<U+017F>ty had not been <U+017F>omething que<U+017F>tionable, <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>'s Daughter had pa<U+017F><U+017F>ed for her Daughter, and you would have mi<U+017F><U+017F>ed the Kingdom of <hi>Ca<U+017F>tille.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Charles</hi> V.</speaker>
                  <p>You make me trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. I fancy now at this very mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that I am lo<U+017F>ing either <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tille,</hi> or the <hi>Low-Countries, Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica</hi> or <hi>Italy.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Era<U+017F>mus.</speaker>
                  <p>Mock not. You would find it a task to make the one a little more <U+017F>olid, and the other <U+017F>omewhat more faithful. Take all, to the very impotency of you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Great Uncle, or the pertne<U+017F>s of your Great A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt, and you will find, that it will be but nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary for you. See what a brittle build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that is, which is founded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <U+017F>o many things depending up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hazard.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:135343:61"/>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Charles</hi> V.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed it is not po<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ible to with<U+017F>tand <U+017F>o <U+017F>trict an Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination as is yours. I mu<U+017F>t needs confe<U+017F>s, that all my Greatne<U+017F>s, and all my Titles do di<U+017F>appear in your pre<U+017F>ence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Era<U+017F>mus.</speaker>
                  <p>The<U+017F>e are the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties though you pretended to adorn your <U+017F>elf with all; I have <U+017F>tript you of them without any trouble. Do not you remember you have heard <U+017F>ay, that <hi>Cimon</hi> the <hi>Athenian,</hi> having taken <U+017F>eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Per<U+017F>ians</hi> Pri<U+017F>oners, did expo<U+017F>e to Sale, on one <U+017F>ide the Cloaths, and their Bodies quite naked on the other; and that whereas the Cloaths were extraordinarily rich, there was great crowding to buy them; but as to the men, no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy would meddle with them. In good earne<U+017F>t, I am apt to believe, that what did happen to the<U+017F>e <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ians,</hi> would be the lot of many
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:135343:62"/>
an one, if there <U+017F>hould be a <U+017F>epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration made of the per<U+017F>onal Merit from that which Fortune has be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>towed upon them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Charles</hi> V.</speaker>
                  <p>But what is this <U+017F>ame per<U+017F>onal Merit?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Era<U+017F>mus.</speaker>
                  <p>Is that a Que<U+017F>tion to be asked? All that is within us. The Mind, for example, Sciences.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Charles</hi> V.</speaker>
                  <p>And one may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully glory in them?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Era<U+017F>mus.</speaker>
                  <p>No doubt of it, the benefits of Fortune, as Gentility or Riches, are not it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Charles</hi> V.</speaker>
                  <p>What you <U+017F>ay, <U+017F>ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pri<U+017F>es me. Does not Sciences come to the Learned, as Riches do to the mo<U+017F>t part of <U+017F>uch as are rich? Is it not by way of Succe<U+017F><U+017F>ion? You learned men, you inherit of the Antients, as we do of our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. If all we enjoy was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathed unto us, all that you know was bequeathed to you al<U+017F>o.
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:135343:62"/>
And 'tis that which makes many learned men look upon what they have received from the Ancients, with the <U+017F>ame re<U+017F>pect as <U+017F>ome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ons do upon the Lands and the Hou<U+017F>es of their Ance<U+017F>tors, wherein they would be loth to make any alteration.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Era<U+017F>mus.</speaker>
                  <p>But the Great Ones are born<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Heirs to their Fathers Greatne<U+017F>s, and the Learned were not born Heirs to the Knowledge of the Ancients. Learning is not a Succe<U+017F><U+017F>ion that Man receives, it is a new Acqui<U+017F>ition which he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes to make; or if it be a Succe<U+017F><U+017F>ion, it is hard enough to come by, though it be very ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Charles</hi> V.</speaker>
                  <p>Well then; <U+017F>et the labour there is to gain the Goods of the mind, again<U+017F>t that a man meets with to pre<U+017F>erve the Goods of Fortune, then all is equal; for,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:135343:63"/>
in fine, if you regard difficulty alone, 'tis certain the concerns of the World have more in them, than the <U+017F>peculations of the Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net have.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Era<U+017F>mus.</speaker>
                  <p>But let us not talk of Learning, let us <U+017F>tick to the mind; that advantage does no ways de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon hazard.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Charles</hi> V.</speaker>
                  <p>It does not depend upon hazard? What, does not the mind con<U+017F>i<U+017F>t in a certain Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Brain? And is Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard the le<U+017F>s to be made of, for tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Birth of a well di<U+017F>po<U+017F>ed Brain, than if it were born of a Father that were a King? You were a great Wit; but ask all the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ophers, what did hinder that you were not a <U+017F>tupified Block-head? Almo<U+017F>t nothing, <U+017F>ome little di<U+017F>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ition of a Mu<U+017F>cle-<U+017F>tring; <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, in fine, that the exacte<U+017F>t Anatomy could never di<U+017F>cover.
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:135343:63"/>
And will the<U+017F>e Gentlemen, your Wits, dare to maintain, now, that they alone do enjoy Goods which are independent of Hazard; and they will think then, they have a Right to contemn all other men?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Era<U+017F>mus.</speaker>
                  <p>At your rate, to be rich, and to have Wit, is the <U+017F>ame Merit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Charles</hi> V.</speaker>
                  <p>To have Wit is the more happy hazard; but, at the bottom, it is <U+017F>till an hazard.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Era<U+017F>mus.</speaker>
                  <p>All is hazard then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Charles</hi> V.</speaker>
                  <p>It is <U+017F>o, provided you will give that name to an unknown quality. I leave it to you to judge, if I have not <U+017F>tript men better yet than you did: you only took from them <U+017F>ome advantages of Birth, and I do not <U+017F>o much as leave them tho<U+017F>e of the mind. If before they took a vanity in any thing, they did make them<U+017F>elves <U+017F>ure, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they had any Right to that
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:135343:64"/>
<U+017F>ame thing, there would be but little vanity in the World.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="dialogue">
               <head>The Third Dialogue,</head>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Alençon.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>The Duke.</speaker>
                  <p>BUT why have you flattered me <U+017F>o long with the hopes of marrying you, <U+017F>ince, in your <U+017F>oul, you were re<U+017F>olved to come to no conclu<U+017F>ion?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Q. <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>I have deceived many an one el<U+017F>e, that was not inferior to you. I was the <hi>Pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lope</hi> of my Age. You, the Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> your Brother, the Arch-Duke,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:135343:64"/>
the King of <hi>Swede,</hi> you were all my Suitors, that aimed at an I<U+017F>land far beyond that of <hi>Ithaca,</hi> I kept you in hand <U+017F>everal years, and in the end I laughed at you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <p>Here are in this place <U+017F>ome certain Dead, that would not yield that you were altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like <hi>Penelope:</hi> but there are no compari<U+017F>ons that are not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective in <U+017F>ome kind or other.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>If you were not as great a Buzzard <U+017F>till as ever, and that you could mind what you <U+017F>ay—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <p>That is well; be <U+017F>erious now, I advi<U+017F>e you. Thus you have ever made your Bravado's of—Witne<U+017F>s that great Country of <hi>America,</hi> which you made be called <hi>Virginia,</hi> in memory of a very doubtful quality. If, by good luck, that place were not in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World, the name it bears
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:135343:65"/>
would be very improper: but it is no matter, this is not the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ine<U+017F>s in que<U+017F>tion. Do <U+017F>o much as give me a rea<U+017F>on for your my<U+017F>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Conduct, and for all tho<U+017F>e projects of Marriage, which came to nothing. Is it that the <U+017F>ix Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages of <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. your Father, did teach you not to marry; as the continual Cour<U+017F>es of <hi>Charles</hi> V. taught <hi>Philip</hi> II. to <U+017F>tay con<U+017F>tant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>Madrid?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>I might keep to the rea<U+017F>on which you <U+017F>upply me with. Indeed my Father <U+017F>pent his whole life in marrying him<U+017F>elf, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marrying again; in repudiating <U+017F>ome of his Wives, and cau<U+017F>ing others to be beheaded. But the true <U+017F>ecret of my Conduct is, that I found nothing more pretty than to frame De<U+017F>igns, make Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, and execute nothing. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of what a man does ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:135343:65"/>
de<U+017F>ire, abates of the e<U+017F>teem of it; and things do not pa<U+017F>s from our imagination, to reality, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <U+017F>ome lo<U+017F>s. You come into <hi>England</hi> to marry me; then no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Balls, Fea<U+017F>ting, Rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cings; nay, I go <U+017F>o far as to give you a Ring. Hitherto every thing <U+017F>miles as much as po<U+017F><U+017F>ible; all con<U+017F>i<U+017F>ts but in Preparatives, and in <hi>Ideas:</hi> Be<U+017F>ides, that which does perfect the delight of Marriage, is already exhau<U+017F>ted. Here I <U+017F>tick, and di<U+017F>mi<U+017F>s you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <p>To be free with you, your Maxims would not have <U+017F>uit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with me; I <U+017F>hould have de<U+017F>ired <U+017F>omething more than <hi>Chymeras.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Ah! if men were debar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of <hi>Chymeras,</hi> what plea<U+017F>ures would they have left them? I <U+017F>ee well enough that you have had no <U+017F>en<U+017F>e of all the plea<U+017F>ures which attended your life; but you are
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:135343:66"/>
very unhappy indeed, that you did lo<U+017F>e them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <p>How? What delights were there in my life? I never <U+017F>ped in any thing. I was like to be King four <U+017F>everal times: fir<U+017F>t of all <hi>Poland</hi> was the place in agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, then <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>Low-Countries;</hi> at la<U+017F>t, <hi>France,</hi> in all appearance, was likely to fall to me: yet, for all this, I am come hither without Reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>And this is the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<U+017F>s you were not aware of. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways imaginations, hopes; and never any reality. You did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but prepare your <U+017F>elf for Royalty all your life-time, as I did all along prepare my <U+017F>elf for Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <p>But as I believe that a real Marriage might have fitted you, I tell you truly, that a real
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:135343:66"/>
Royalty would have plea<U+017F>ed me well enough.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Plea<U+017F>ures are not <U+017F>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid enough to bear a <U+017F>earch into their depth; they mu<U+017F>t be but ju<U+017F>t <U+017F>melled unto. They are like tho<U+017F>e boggy Grounds, which a man is obliged to run lightly over, without ever <U+017F>ettling his foot upon them.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="dialogue">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:135343:67"/>
               <head>The Fourth Dialogue.</head>
               <stage>
                  <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Cabe<U+017F>tan. Albertus Frederick </hi> of <hi>Brandebourg.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>A. F.</hi> of <hi>Bradebourg.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>I Love you the better for hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing been a fool as well as my <U+017F>elf. Tell me a little what your folly was.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cabe<U+017F>tan.</speaker>
                  <p>I was a Poet of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence,</hi> much <U+017F>et by in my Age; which cau<U+017F>ed my ruin. I fell in love with a Lady, whom I had rendred famous by my Writings. But <U+017F>he took <U+017F>uch a liking to my Ver<U+017F>es, that <U+017F>he began to fear le<U+017F>t I <U+017F>hould, <U+017F>ome time or other, apply them to <U+017F>ome other per<U+017F>on; and, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <U+017F>ecure her <U+017F>elf of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tancy
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:135343:67"/>
of my Mu<U+017F>e, <U+017F>he gave me a cur<U+017F>ed Drink that turned my Wits, and made me incapable of writing any more.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brand.</speaker>
                  <p>How long have you been dead?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cab.</speaker>
                  <p>Near upon four hundred years.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brand.</speaker>
                  <p>Sure, Poets were ever <U+017F>carce in your Age, <U+017F>ince people had <U+017F>o much e<U+017F>teem for them, as to poy<U+017F>on them in this manner. I am <U+017F>orry you were not born in my time; you might have made Ver<U+017F>es for all kind of hand<U+017F>ome Women, without any fear of Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cab.</speaker>
                  <p>I know it. I <U+017F>ee none of all tho<U+017F>e great Wits that come hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, make their complaints of having had my de<U+017F>tiny. But you, in what manner became you a fool?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:135343:68"/>
                  <speaker>Brand.</speaker>
                  <p>After a very rea<U+017F>onable manner. A King turned fool, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having had <U+017F>omething appear to him in a Fore<U+017F>t. But what I <U+017F>aw was far more terrible.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cab.</speaker>
                  <p>And what did you <U+017F>ee?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brand.</speaker>
                  <p>In what manner my Wedding was to be kept. I did marry <hi>Mary Eleonora</hi> of <hi>Cleve;</hi> and all along this great day of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing, I made <U+017F>uch judicious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections upon Marriage, that they put me out of my Wits.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cab.</speaker>
                  <p>Had you any good inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals in your <U+017F>ickne<U+017F>s?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brand.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cab.</speaker>
                  <p>So much the wor<U+017F>e: and I, for my part, I was yet more unfortunate: I recovered my Wits again.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brand.</speaker>
                  <p>I <U+017F>hould never have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved that that was a mi<U+017F>for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>une.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cab.</speaker>
                  <p>When a man turns Fool, he mu<U+017F>t be an ab<U+017F>olute one, and
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:135343:68"/>
continue <U+017F>uch an one. The<U+017F>e Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternatives of Rea<U+017F>on and Folly, and the<U+017F>e Returns again of perfect Rea<U+017F>on is the property of your petty Fools only, that are <U+017F>o but by accident, and which are but incon<U+017F>iderable in number. But behold tho<U+017F>e which Nature does daily produce in her natural cour<U+017F>e, and wherewith the World <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s filled; they are always Fools <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n an equal manner, and are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver cured.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brand.</speaker>
                  <p>For my part, I <U+017F>hould have imagined, that it were be<U+017F>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o be as little Fool as one could.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cab.</speaker>
                  <p>Ah! do you not know the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap><U+017F>e of folly. Folly hinders a man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rom knowing him<U+017F>elf; for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ght of his own <U+017F>elf is a <U+017F>ad one: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd, as 'tis never time to know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nes <U+017F>elf, <U+017F>o folly mu<U+017F>t not for<U+017F>ake <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> man one <U+017F>ingle moment.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:135343:69"/>
                  <speaker>Brand.</speaker>
                  <p>You may <U+017F>ay what you will; you <U+017F>hall not per<U+017F>uade me that there be any other fools, than tho<U+017F>e that are <U+017F>o, as both of us have been. The re<U+017F>t of men have all Rea<U+017F>on; el<U+017F>e the lo<U+017F>s of a man's Wits would be no lo<U+017F>s, and one could not di<U+017F>tingui<U+017F>h the Frantick from <U+017F>uch as were in their right Sen<U+017F>es.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cab.</speaker>
                  <p>The Frantick are only fools of another kind. The fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of all men, being of one <U+017F>ame nature, have agreed together with <U+017F>o much ea<U+017F>e, that they have been in<U+017F>trumental to the making up of the <U+017F>tronge<U+017F>t ties of Humane So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety: witne<U+017F>s that de<U+017F>ire of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, that fal<U+017F>e Glory, and <U+017F>everal other Principles, which give a motion to all that is done in the World. And none are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led fools now, but <U+017F>ome certain fools that are, as one may <U+017F>ay, out
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:135343:69"/>
of employment, and who<U+017F>e folly could not <U+017F>uit with that of the re<U+017F>t, nor enter into the common deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of life.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brand.</speaker>
                  <p>Tho<U+017F>e that are frantick, are <U+017F>uch great fools, that, for the mo<U+017F>t part, they call one another fool; but your other men call them<U+017F>elves wi<U+017F>e per<U+017F>ons.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cab.</speaker>
                  <p>Ah! What is it you <U+017F>ay? All men point at one another with their finger, and Nature has very judiciou<U+017F>ly <U+017F>etled that Order. The Solitary Man laughs at the Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier; but to be even with him, he goes not to trouble him at Court. The Courtier laughs at the Solita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man, but he lets him alone in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et in his retirement. If there were ever a <U+017F>ide to be taken, that were known to be the only rea<U+017F>onable <U+017F>ide, every one would embrace that <U+017F>ide, and there would be too much crowding: it is better to be
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:135343:70"/>
divided into <U+017F>everal little Troops<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> that embroil not one another, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cau<U+017F>e <U+017F>ome laugh at what the other do.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brand.</speaker>
                  <p>As dead as you are, I find you are a great fool with a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> your Arguments: you are not well recovered yet of the Drenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> was given you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cab.</speaker>
                  <p>And this is the <hi>Idea</hi> whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a fool mu<U+017F>t always conceive of another. True Wi<U+017F>dom would too much <U+017F>ingularize tho<U+017F>e enjo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed her: but the Opinion of Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dom renders all men equal, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> does no le<U+017F>s <U+017F>atisfie them.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="dialogue">
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:135343:70"/>
               <head>The Fifth Dialogue.</head>
               <stage>Agnes Sorel. Roxelana.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Agnes Sorel.</speaker>
                  <p>TO tell you the truth, I do not under<U+017F>tand your <hi>Turki<U+017F>h</hi> Gallantry. The Beauties of the <hi>Seraglio</hi> have a Lover that need only <U+017F>ay, <hi>My Will is <U+017F>o;</hi> they never ta<U+017F>te of the plea<U+017F>ure of Re<U+017F>i<U+017F>tance, and they never afford him the plea<U+017F>ure of Victory: that is to <U+017F>ay, that the Sultans and their Sultane<U+017F><U+017F>es do never enjoy the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights of Love.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Roxelana.</speaker>
                  <p>What will you have? the <hi>Turki<U+017F>h</hi> Emperors, who are <U+017F>trangely jealous of their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, have, upon Rea<U+017F>ons of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, neglected tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>o refined de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:135343:71"/>
of Love. They were afraid that <U+017F>uch Beauties as did not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>olutely depend upon them, would a<U+017F><U+017F>ume too great a power over their mind, and meddle too much with Affairs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Agnes Sorel.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, well, How know they whether it would be a misfortune? Love is often good for many things: and I that <U+017F>peak to you, if I had not been Mi<U+017F>tre<U+017F>s to a King of <hi>France;</hi> and if I had not had a great power over him, I know not whereabouts <hi>France</hi> would have been by this time. Have you heard in what a de<U+017F>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate condition our Affairs were in under <hi>Charles</hi> the Seventh, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to what a plight the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom was reduced; the <hi>Engli<U+017F>h</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing almo<U+017F>t Ma<U+017F>ters of it all?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Roxelana.</speaker>
                  <p>I have, as this Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tory has made a great noi<U+017F>e. I know that a certain Maid did
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:135343:71"/>
pre<U+017F>erve <hi>France:</hi> You are then the Maid? And how were you, the <U+017F>ame time, Mi<U+017F>tre<U+017F>s to the King?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Agnes Sorel.</speaker>
                  <p>You mi<U+017F>take your <U+017F>elf; I have no concern with the Maid you have been told of. The King, of whom I was beloved, had a mind to leave his Kingdom to Strangers that were U<U+017F>urpers, and go and hide him<U+017F>elf in a Country full of Mountains, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I <U+017F>hould not have been very well contented to follow him. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought my <U+017F>elf of a Stratagem to divert him from this de<U+017F>ign. I <U+017F>ent for an A<U+017F>tronomer, whom I dealt withal under-hand; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had made a <U+017F>hew of <U+017F>tudy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Nativity, he told me one day, in pre<U+017F>ence of <hi>Charles</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, that all the Planets were Cheats, or I <U+017F>hould in<U+017F>pire a pa<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ion of long continuance into a
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:135343:72"/>
great King. I pre<U+017F>ently <U+017F>aid to <hi>Charles; You will not take it ill then, Sir, that I go over to the Court of</hi> England; <hi>for you will be no longer King, and you have not loved me long enough to fulfil my de<U+017F>tiny.</hi> His fear of lo<U+017F>ing me made him re<U+017F>olve to be King of the <hi>French;</hi> and he began, at that very time, to re-e<U+017F>tabli<U+017F>h him<U+017F>elf. Behold how much <hi>France</hi> is obliged to Love, and how gallant that Kingdom ough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to be, though it were but by way of acknowledgment.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Roxelana.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis true. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mu<U+017F>t to my Maid again: Wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> did <U+017F>he do then? Could Hi<U+017F>tory be <U+017F>o much mi<U+017F>taken<g ref="char:punc"><U+25AA></g> as to attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to a young Country Mai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that which did belong to a Cour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Lady, the King's Mi<U+017F>tre<U+017F>s?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:135343:72"/>
                  <speaker>Agnes Sorel.</speaker>
                  <p>If Hi<U+017F>tory <U+017F>hould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e <U+017F>o far mi<U+017F>taken, it would be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o great wonder. Yet 'tis mo<U+017F>t certain, that the Maid did highly encourage the Soldiers; but I had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>efore-hand animated the King. She was a great help to this Prince, whom <U+017F>he found ready to engage with the <hi>Engli<U+017F>h:</hi> but, had it not been for me, <U+017F>he would not have found him in that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>ture. In <U+017F>hort, you will no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther que<U+017F>tion the <U+017F>hare I have in that great Affair, when you <U+017F>hall know the te<U+017F>timony which was given in my behalf in this, by one of <hi>Charles</hi> the Seventh's Succe<U+017F><U+017F>ors, in this <hi>Quatrine.</hi>
                     <q>
                        <l>Gentle <hi>Agnes,</hi> more Honour is thy due,</l>
                        <l>The Cau<U+017F>e being <hi>France,</hi> for to re<U+017F><g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cue.</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb n="128" facs="tcp:135343:73"/>
Then what, in a Cloi<U+017F>ter, can be done</l>
                        <l>By devout Hermit, or enclo<U+017F>ed Nun.</l>
                     </q>
What <U+017F>ay you to it <hi>Roxelana?</hi> You will own, that if I had been a Sultanne<U+017F>s; like you, and had not had a Right to threaten <hi>Charles</hi> the Seventh as I did, he had been undone.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Roxelana.</speaker>
                  <p>I wonder at the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity you take in this petty Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. You had no difficulty to gain very much upon the mind of a Lover, you that were free, and your own Mi<U+017F>tre<U+017F>s: but I, as much a Slave as I was; I did, for all that, make the Sultan <U+017F>ubmit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me. You made <hi>Charles</hi> the Seventh King, almo<U+017F>t again<U+017F>t his Will; and I made <hi>Soliman</hi> my Hu<U+017F>band, in <U+017F>pight of him<U+017F>elf.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:135343:73"/>
                  <speaker>Agnes Sorel.</speaker>
                  <p>But how? They <U+017F>ay, the Sultans never marry.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Roxelana.</speaker>
                  <p>I grant it: Howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, I was re<U+017F>olved to marry <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liman,</hi> though I could not bring him to it out of hopes of an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine<U+017F>s which he had not, as yet, obtained. I will tell you a <U+017F>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem that goes beyond yours. I began to build Temples, and to do <U+017F>everal other works of Piety; after which, I made <U+017F>hew of a deep Melancholy. The Sultan asked me the rea<U+017F>on of it a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>and and a thou<U+017F>and times: and when I had made as much a do as was nece<U+017F><U+017F>ary, I told him, that the cau<U+017F>e of my trouble was, becau<U+017F>e all my good Actions, as our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors had told me, did me no good; and that, as I was a Slave, I did but labour <U+017F>or <hi>Soliman,</hi> my Lord. Hereupon <hi>Soliman</hi> made me free, to the end, that the Merit of my
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:135343:74"/>
good Actions might redound to my own <U+017F>elf. But when he had a mind to live with me as formerly, and treat me like a Beauty of the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> I made as if I were much <U+017F>urpri<U+017F>ed; and repre<U+017F>ented unto him, in a very <U+017F>erious manner, that he had no Right over the Per<U+017F>on of a free Woman. <hi>Soliman</hi> had a tender Con<U+017F>cience: he went to a Doctor of the Law, with whom I did deal under-hand, to con<U+017F>ult about this Ca<U+017F>e. His An<U+017F>wer was, that <hi>Soliman</hi> <U+017F>hould beware of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending any thing over me, who was no more his Slave; and that, unle<U+017F>s he did marry me, I could be no longer his. Now he is more in Love than ever. He had but one Choice to make, but a very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary one, and dangerous to boot for a Sultan: However, he made it, and married me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:135343:74"/>
                  <speaker>Agnes Sorel.</speaker>
                  <p>I mu<U+017F>t confe<U+017F>s, 'tis a brave thing to make tho<U+017F>e <U+017F>ub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, who do <U+017F>o fore-arm them<U+017F>elves again<U+017F>t our Power.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Roxelana.</speaker>
                  <p>Men may do as much as in them lies: when they are laid hold on by their Pa<U+017F><U+017F>ions, one may lead them where one plea<U+017F>e. Let me return to life again, and let me have the mo<U+017F>t domineering man in the world; I will handle him as I will my <U+017F>elf, <U+017F>o I have a great deal of Wit, Beauty enough, and but little Love.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="dialogue">
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:135343:75"/>
               <head>The Sixth Dialogue.</head>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Jane</hi> the Fir<U+017F>t of <hi>Naples. An<U+017F>elme.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Jane</hi> of <hi>Naples.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>HOW? Can you tell me no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is to come? You have not forgot all your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer A<U+017F>trology?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An<U+017F>elme.</speaker>
                  <p>And how is it po<U+017F><U+017F>ible to put it in practice? We have neither Sky nor Stars here.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Jane</hi> of <hi>Naples.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>'Tis no matter. I will di<U+017F>pence with you, for ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>erving the Rules <U+017F>o exactly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An<U+017F>elme.</speaker>
                  <p>It would be pretty, that a dead man <U+017F>hould prophecy. But yet, upon what?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Jane</hi> of <hi>Naples,</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Upon me, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what concerns me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:135343:75"/>
                  <speaker>An<U+017F>elme.</speaker>
                  <p>That is a good one: You are dead, and will be <U+017F>o <U+017F>till: This is all I have to foretell of you. Is our Condition <U+017F>uch, that our Concerns may change?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Jane</hi> of <hi>Naples.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>No. But yet, that is it which does cruelly trouble me: And though I know nothing will happen to me, if you would; for all that, fore-tell me <U+017F>omething; it would employ me. You cannot imagine what a <U+017F>ad thing it is, to have no time to come to look upon. Come; <U+017F>ome little Prophe<U+017F>ie, pray you, <U+017F>uch as you will.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An<U+017F>elme.</speaker>
                  <p>To behold your re<U+017F>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<U+017F>ne<U+017F>s, one would think you were yet living. Thus one is too above. One cannot be what one is there, with patience: we anticipate al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways what we <U+017F>hall be; but here we mu<U+017F>t be more wi<U+017F>e.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:135343:76"/>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Jane</hi> of <hi>Naples.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Ah! Have not men rea<U+017F>on to do as they do? The time pre<U+017F>ent is but an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>tant, and it would be a pitiful ca<U+017F>e, they <U+017F>hould be reduced to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit their fore-<U+017F>ight there: Is it not better they <U+017F>hould extend it as far as it is po<U+017F><U+017F>ible, and gain <U+017F>ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing upon time to come? They po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s them<U+017F>elves, however, of <U+017F>o much before-hand.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An<U+017F>elme.</speaker>
                  <p>But they borrow <U+017F>o much upon time to come, by their imaginations, and by their hopes, that, when it is pre<U+017F>ent, they find that it is quite <U+017F>pent, and make no u<U+017F>e of it. In the mean time, they do not break them<U+017F>elves of their impatience, nor of their re<U+017F>tle<U+017F>s humour. Mens great Lure is, <hi>Time to come</hi> <U+017F>till; and we A<U+017F>trologers know it better than any. We boldly tell them, that there are cold Signs
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:135343:76"/>
and hot Signs; that <U+017F>ome are Male, and <U+017F>ome are Female; that <U+017F>ome Planets are good, and <U+017F>ome bad; and that there are others that, in them<U+017F>elves, are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good nor bad; but they take upon them either of the two Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, according as they fall or light in company. And all the<U+017F>e flames are very well accepted of, becau<U+017F>e it is believed they lead to the knowledge of time to come.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Jane</hi> of <hi>Naples.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Why, do they not truly? I would have you that have been my A<U+017F>tronomer, tell me <U+017F>omething that is ill of A<U+017F>trology.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An<U+017F>elme.</speaker>
                  <p>Hear me. A dead man would not tell a lie: I did deceive you with this A<U+017F>trology that you value <U+017F>o.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Jane</hi> of <hi>Naples.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Oh! Herein I do not believe you your own <U+017F>elf. How could you have fore-told me, that I <U+017F>hould be married four
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:135343:77"/>
times? Was there the lea<U+017F>t ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, that a per<U+017F>on that was any whit rational, would engage in Matrimony four times one after the other? You mu<U+017F>t needs have read it in the Heavens.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An<U+017F>elme.</speaker>
                  <p>I con<U+017F>ulted them far le<U+017F>s than I did your inclinations: but, after all, <U+017F>ome Prophe<U+017F>ies that fall out right, prove nothing. Shall I carry you to a dead per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/><U+017F>on, who will tell you a pretty plea<U+017F>ant <U+017F>tory? He was an A<U+017F>tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomer, and gave no more credit to A<U+017F>trology than I did. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thele<U+017F>s, to try whether there was any thing of certainty in his Art, he did apply his whole care, one day, to ob<U+017F>erve the Rules exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and did fore-tell <U+017F>ome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Events in one per<U+017F>on, harder by much to gue<U+017F>s at, than your four Marriages. All he fore-told did come to pa<U+017F>s: Never was he
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:135343:77"/>
more <U+017F>urpri<U+017F>ed. He pre<U+017F>ently looked over his A<U+017F>trological Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations, which had been the Ground of his Predictions, know you what he found? He had made a mi<U+017F>take; and, if his Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations had been right, he <U+017F>hould have fore-told the quite contrary of what he did foretell.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Jane</hi> of <hi>Naples.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>If I did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this were true, I <U+017F>hould be much concerned it <U+017F>hould not be known in the World, that they might undeceive them<U+017F>elves in A<U+017F>tronomers.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An<U+017F>elme.</speaker>
                  <p>There are other-gui<U+017F>e <U+017F>tories than this known, and more to their di<U+017F>advantage; and yet their Trade holds good. People will never be di<U+017F>-abu<U+017F>ed in any thing that concerns <hi>Time to come;</hi> it has too powerful a Charm. Men, for example, <U+017F>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice all they have to one Hope;
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:135343:78"/>
and all they had, and what they have lately purcha<U+017F>ed, they <U+017F>till <U+017F>acrifice it to another Hope: and this <U+017F>eems to be a malicious Order, e<U+017F>tabli<U+017F>hed in Nature, to bereave them <U+017F>till of what they po<U+017F><U+017F>e<U+017F>s. Men do little care to be happy in the moment then pre<U+017F>ent, they put off being <U+017F>o to <hi>a Time to come,</hi> as though that time <U+017F>hould be of another Make, than this that is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready come.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Jane</hi> of <hi>Naples.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>No, it is not of another Make; but it is good to fancy it <U+017F>o.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An<U+017F>elme.</speaker>
                  <p>And what is the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of this fine Opinion? I know a little Fable that will inform you. I did formerly learn it at the Court of Love, it was a kind of Academy, which was held in your Country of <hi>Provence. A man was thirsty, and was <U+017F>at down by a Fountain. He would not drink of</hi>
                     <pb n="139" facs="tcp:135343:78"/>
                     <hi>the Water that was running before him, becau<U+017F>e he hoped, that in <U+017F>ome <U+017F>hort time better would come.</hi> This time being pa<U+017F>t; <hi>This is <U+017F>till the <U+017F>ame Water,</hi> <U+017F>aid he, <hi>this is not that which I will drink of; I had rather tarry a little longer yet.</hi> At length; <hi>as the Water was <U+017F>till the <U+017F>ame, he <U+017F>tayed <U+017F>o, that the Spring happened to dry up, and he drank not at all.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Jane</hi> of <hi>Naples.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>As much as hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to me. And I believe that, of all the Dead that are here, there is not one who was not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of Life <U+017F>ooner than he had made the u<U+017F>e of it, he did intend. But what matters it? I reckon, the plea<U+017F>ure of fore-<U+017F>eeing, hoping, of fearing too, and of having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore one <hi>a Time to come,</hi> to be great things. A wi<U+017F>e man, in your Opinion, would be like we Dead, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> whom the Pre<U+017F>ent, and the
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:135343:79"/>
Time to come are perfectly alike: and this wi<U+017F>e man would, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, find it as irk<U+017F>ome as I do.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An<U+017F>elme.</speaker>
                  <p>Alas! Man's Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is pretty, if it be <U+017F>uch as you believe it is. He is born to aim at all, and <U+017F>o enjoy nothing; to be always going, and arrive at no place.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>

